[INTRIGUING MUSIC]
[引人入胜的音乐]
DAVID MALAN: All right, so this is CS50.
大卫·马兰：好的，这是 CS50。
And this is week 1, zero index, so to speak.
这是第一周，可以说，从零开始。
And it's not every day that you can say that you've learned a new language,
你并不每天都能说你学习了一门新的语言，
but today is that day.
但今天是那一天。
Today, we explore a more traditional and older language called C.
今天，我们将探索一种更传统、更古老的语言，叫做 C。
And rest assured that even if what you're about to see-- no pun intended--
请放心，即使你将要看到的内容——我并没有说双关语——
looks very cryptic, very unusual, particularly if you're
看起来非常神秘，非常不寻常，特别是如果你
among those less comfortable, cling to the ideas from last week,
是那些不太舒服的人，那就坚持上周的思路，
week zero, wherein we talked about some of those fundamentals of functions
第零周，我们讨论了一些函数的基础知识
and loops and conditionals, all of which are coming back today.
循环和条件语句，所有这些今天都会回来。
Indeed, whereas last week, and with problem set 0,
事实上，上周，以及在习题集 0 中，
we focused on learning how to program with Scratch,
我们专注于学习如何用 Scratch 编程，
which, again, you might have played with as a younger student days back.
你可能在小时候玩过。
Today, we focus on C instead.
今天，我们将专注于 C 语言。
But along the way, we're going to focus, as always, frankly,
但在此过程中，我们始终如一地关注，坦率地说，
on learning how to solve problems.
学习如何解决问题。
But among the goals for today and really on an entire class like this
但今天的目标，以及这门课的目标，
is just to give you week after week all the more tools for your toolkit,
只是每周给你提供更多工具，
so to speak, via which to do exactly that.
可以用这些工具来完成这些。
So for instance today, we'll learn how to solve problems all the more
例如，今天，我们将学习如何用更多的方法来解决问题
so with functions, as per last week.
使用函数，就像上周一样。
We'll do the same with variables.
我们也会用变量做同样的事情。
We'll do the same with conditionals, with loops, and with more.
我们也会用条件语句、循环等等做同样的事情。
But we'll also learn at the end of today's class
但我们也会在今天课的最后学习
really how not to solve problems.
如何不能解决问题。
It turns out as powerful as Macs, PCs, cell phones are nowadays,
事实证明，尽管现在的 Mac、PC、手机功能强大，
there's actually certain things that they can't do very well
但实际上，它们有些事情做不好，
and information they can't represent very well.
它们无法很好地表示某些信息。
And that actually leads to a lot of real-world problems, both past
这实际上会导致很多现实世界中的问题，无论是过去
and surely future.
还是将来。
So more on what we're not going to be able to do with programming before
所以，在学习更多关于编程无法做到的事情之前，
long.
我们先来看看。
But beyond that, let's come back to this picture here.
除此之外，让我们回到这张图片。
So this was the very first program that I wrote,
这是我写的第一个程序，
that you wrote presumably in some form.
你可能也以某种形式写过。
And all it does is say "Hello, world."
它只做了一件事，就是说 "Hello, world"。
But as promised, today, this puzzle piece, or these puzzle pieces together,
但正如承诺的那样，今天，这块拼图，或者说这些拼图放在一起，
are going to very quickly start to look more like this.
会很快变得像这样。
And I've deliberately color coded it in a way so that the text on the screen
我特意用颜色编码了它，这样屏幕上的文本
now kind of resembles the puzzle piece.
现在有点像拼图了。
So if I go back, notice that we had this, when green flag clicked puzzle
所以如果我回到这里，你会注意到，我们有这个，当绿旗被点击时，这块拼图
piece, mostly in yellow with the green flag, that sort of kicks off
这块拼图主要是黄色的，上面有绿色的旗帜，它开始
the whole process once you actually click
整个过程，一旦你点击
the button at top right of Scratch's user interface.
Scratch 用户界面右上角的按钮。
And then there's the purple block which actually is the verb, the action,
然后是紫色块，它实际上是动词，是动作，
the function that does something.
执行某个功能的函数。
So if I bring us back over to what we're about to see today,
所以让我们回到今天将要看到的内容，
there's going to be some boilerplate, so to speak, some orange text here
屏幕上会有一些模板，可以说是橙色的文字，
on the screen that for now you just type and take for granted,
现在你只需要输入并视作理所当然，
like you need to write your code like that.
就像你必须那样写你的代码一样。
But more interesting is going to be the purple.
但更有趣的是紫色部分。
And we're going to see today that the function previously
我们今天将看到之前
called "say" in Scratch is now called "printf" in this language called C.
在 Scratch 中叫做 "say" 的函数，现在在这门叫做 C 的语言中叫做 "printf"。
But in white here, you'll see similar text to our white oval
但在这里的白色部分，你会看到类似于我们上周的白色椭圆的文字，
last week, whereby that's where user input, like your input
上周，那是用户输入，就像你作为程序员的输入
as the programmer, can actually go.
可以实际输入的地方。
So there's a lot of distraction.
所以有很多干扰。
And honestly, it's these kinds of things that
说实话，正是这些东西
tend to distract and get frustrating early on when
在学习编程初期容易造成干扰，让人感到沮丧，
learning to code for the first time.
第一次学习编程的时候。
But the ideas, most importantly, are going to be the same.
但最重要的是，这些想法会是一样的。
So how are we going to go about using this.
那么我们如何使用它呢？
Well, it turns out, like last week, you're
事实证明，就像上周一样，你会
going to start writing something called source code.
开始编写一些叫做源代码的东西。
So code as we know it, quote, unquote, is more technically called
所以我们所知道的代码，引号内的“代码”，在技术上更准确地称为
"source code."
“源代码”。
That's what you and I as humans actually write.
那就是你我作为人类实际编写的东西。
And indeed it might look a little something like we just saw.
而且确实它看起来有点像我们刚刚看到的。
But unfortunately, computers only speak this, binary--
但不幸的是，计算机只能理解这种语言，二进制——
zeros and ones-- more properly known as machine code, in other words,
零和一——更准确地说，是机器代码，换句话说，
those same patterns of zeros and ones last week, someone guessed,
上周，有人猜到了那些相同的零和一的模式，
print out "hello, world" on the screen because one of those patterns
在屏幕上打印出 "hello, world" 因为其中一个模式
is an H. Another pattern is an E, an L, and L, and an O, and so forth.
是一个 H。另一个模式是 E、L、L、O 等等。
And then other patterns of those zeros and ones are commands or instructions
然后，那些零和一的其他模式就是命令或指令
to the computer that literally say, show H-E-L-L-O comma "world" on the screen.
对计算机来说，实际上就是说，在屏幕上显示 H-E-L-L-O 逗号 "world"。
But machine code would not be nearly as much fun
但机器代码如果真的用零和一写的话，就没有那么有趣了
to write if it were indeed in zeros and ones.
了。
Entirely for us, ideally, you and I are going
理想情况下，完全是为了我们，你我都会
to write source code, which conceptually is sort of up here, high level.
去编写源代码，从概念上讲，它就像是这里，高级别。
But we're going to need a program to convert it to the lower-level machine
但我们需要一个程序来将其转换为低级别的机器
code so that we don't spend our lives actually having to read and write
代码，这样我们就不用花一辈子的时间去读写
zeros and ones, which back in the day, kind of in yesteryear,
零和一，在过去，也就是前几年，
you kind of did with things called punch cards
你用的是叫做打孔卡的东西
and holes on physical sheets of paper.
以及纸质卡片上的孔。
We're beyond that because after years and years of innovation,
我们已经超越了那一步，因为经过多年的创新，
folks have given us higher-level languages instead.
人们给了我们更高等级的语言。
So here's what we're going to need to do today.
所以今天我们需要做的事情是。
If at the end of the day you and I are writing source code
如果最终你我编写的是源代码
but we want machine code as output, we need something
但我们想要机器代码作为输出，我们需要一些东西
in the middle that's going to convert that source code to machine code.
在中间来将源代码转换为机器代码。
You and I are not going to have to learn or talk
我们不必学习或谈论
about really any more zeros and ones.
关于更多关于零和一的知识。
And the type of program we're going to start using today and introduce you to
今天我们要开始使用并介绍给你的程序类型
is called a compiler.
叫做编译器。
So a compiler is a program that translates one language to another.
所以编译器是一个将一种语言翻译成另一种语言的程序。
And it can be any two languages.
可以是任意两种语言。
But today, and often, we'll talk about it in the context of source code
但是今天，通常情况下，我们会从源代码的角度来讨论它
to machine code.
到机器码。
So this is Apple or Google or Microsoft or folks from other companies
所以这是苹果、谷歌、微软或其他公司的员工
or even volunteers who have written software that do this conversion.
甚至还有志愿者编写了执行这种转换的软件。
You and I are essentially going to download a free compiler
我们实际上要下载一个免费的编译器
and use it to actually get our computer to understand the source
并使用它来让我们的计算机真正理解源代码
code that you and I write in these higher-level languages.
我们用这些高级语言编写的代码。
So where are we going to do that?
所以我们要在哪里做呢？
Well, we could actually give you instructions
好吧，我们实际上可以给你一些说明
and you could download the appropriate free open-source software
你可以下载相应的免费开源软件
onto your own Mac or PC.
到你的Mac或PC上。
The reality is that creates so many technical support headaches because we
现实情况是，这会导致很多技术支持方面的麻烦，因为我们
all have slightly different computers.
大家的电脑都略有不同。
We all have slightly different versions of Windows or macOS or Linux
我们都有稍微不同的 Windows、macOS 或 Linux 版本
or other operating systems.
或其他操作系统。
And that, too, tends to be a distraction at the beginning of any course
这在任何课程的开始阶段，也往往会让人分心
like this or learning programming.
比如这门课，或者学习编程。
So we're going to use the cloud instead.
所以我们要使用云来替代。
We're going to use a URL of the form https://cs50.dev.
我们将使用 https://cs50.dev 格式的 URL。
And what this will do for you is put inside of your browser window
这将为你做的就是把你的浏览器窗口里
absolutely everything you need for the course, but it's going to use software,
放进去你需要的所有课程内容，但它会使用软件，
software called Visual Studio code, otherwise known as VS Code,
叫做 Visual Studio Code 的软件，也被称为 VS Code，
that's actually free itself.
它本身是免费的。
It's very popular in industry.
它在行业内非常流行。
It's what "real" programmers use every day.
这是“真正的”程序员每天都在使用的。
But it's a cloud-based version thereof.
但它是一个基于云的版本。
And so everything will just work for you out of the box.
所以一切都将为你开箱即用。
But toward the end of CS50, the goal is going
但在 CS50 的最后，目标是
to be to get you off of CS50's infrastructure,
让你摆脱 CS50 的基础设施，
to get you to download this freely available software onto your own Mac
让你下载这个免费的软件到你的 Mac 上
or PC if you so choose so that those training wheels, so to speak,
或者你的 PC 上，如果你愿意的话，这样那些辅助轮，这么说吧，
can come off.
就可以取下来了。
And then even if you never take another class again,
然后即使你再也不上其他课程了，
you don't need any class's infrastructure moving forward.
你不需要任何课程的基础设施。
You'll have everything you want and need on your own Mac or PC.
你将拥有你在自己的 Mac 或 PC 上需要的一切。
But for now, it'll save us a bit of time.
但现在，这将为我们节省一些时间。
So in just a bit, I'm going to go to that URL myself on my computer.
所以过一会儿，我将在我自己的电脑上访问那个 URL。
And I and you will see a user interface that
你和我都会看到一个用户界面，它
looks a little something like this.
看起来有点像这样。
The colors might be different based on your settings.
颜色可能会根据你的设置而有所不同。
Fonts might be different, and so forth.
字体也可能不同，等等。
But in general, it consists of a few different regions.
但总的来说，它包含几个不同的区域。
So over here at the top is where we are going to start writing code today.
所以这里上方是我们今天将开始编写代码的地方。
So it's a tabbed interface like any number of programs nowadays.
所以它是一个带标签的界面，就像现在许多程序一样。
And this is that same C code we saw a moment ago.
而这是我们刚才看到的相同的C代码。
So this is where, in a moment, I'm going to start to type it.
所以这里，一会儿，我将开始输入。
Over here at the bottom is what we're going to call
这里下方是我们所说的
a terminal window, or a console.
终端窗口或控制台。
And the terminal window is where we're going to type commands
而终端窗口是我们输入命令的地方
for compiling our code, for running our code.
用于编译我们的代码，用于运行我们的代码。
And we'll see today a contrast between a graphical-user interface,
我们今天将看到图形用户界面之间的对比，
or GUI, which has menus and icons and things
或GUI，它有菜单、图标和各种东西
you click and are very familiar with, versus a command-line interface,
你可以点击，你非常熟悉，与命令行界面相比，
or CLI.
或CLI。
And so we're using both of these together.
所以我们同时使用这两者。
And command-line interface just means, down here, you only use your keyboard.
命令行界面只是意味着，在下方，你只使用键盘。
You can click, click, click if you want with your mouse.
如果你愿意，可以用鼠标点击、点击、点击。
It's not going to generally do much because a command-line interface takes
它通常不会做太多，因为命令行界面接受
commands at the keyboard.
键盘上的命令。
So in a weird sense, it's going to feel like taking
所以从某种奇怪的意义上说，这将感觉像是
a step backwards from the Macs, the PCs, the iPhones, and Android phones we all
从我们所有人使用的Mac、PC、iPhone和Android手机倒退一步
have, which are very graphical.
这些都是非常图形化的。
But it turns out, once you become a "computer" person or a programmer,
但事实证明，一旦你成为一个“计算机”人或程序员，
you can be a lot more productive, a lot more efficient, I dare say,
你可以更有成效，更有效率，我敢说，
by learning to harness the command-line interface
通过学习利用命令行界面
and using both types of interfaces for what each is good at.
并为每个界面擅长的事情使用这两种类型的界面。
So more on that in just a bit.
稍后会详细介绍。
Over here at left, you're going to see soon a folder interface like Mac OS
这里左侧，你很快就会看到一个类似Mac OS的文件夹界面
or Windows where any of the files or folders we create in CS50
或Windows，我们在CS50中创建的任何文件或文件夹
are going to end up, as well.
也会出现在这里。
So it gives you the best of both worlds.
所以它让你拥有两个世界的精华。
You can point and click on the left, or you can type commands at the bottom,
你可以在左侧点选，也可以在下方输入命令，
as we'll soon see.
我们很快就会看到。
And then along here is the so-called activity bar,
然后这里就是所谓的活动栏，
where there's just VS Code-specific features but also CS50-specific
这里只有VS Code特有的功能，但也包含CS50特有的功能。
features.
功能。
And if you're in your own version of CS50.dev,
如果你在自己的CS50.dev版本中，
you click through in the dot dot dot menu
你可以点击省略号菜单
or zoom out so you can see everything.
或者缩小，这样你就可以看到所有内容。
You'll see CS50's own rubber duck, virtually speaking,
你会看到CS50自己的橡皮鸭，虚拟地说，
that will be there throughout the course to answer
它将在整个课程中出现，以回答
any and all of your questions, as well.
你所有的问题。
So more on that soon, too.
很快也会有更多关于这方面的信息。
So here's the code that I propose that we write first,
所以这是我建议我们首先编写的代码，
just like we wrote our very first Scratch program to say "hello, world."
就像我们编写第一个Scratch程序来说“hello, world.”一样。
So let's go ahead and do exactly this.
所以让我们继续做这件事。
I'm going to switch over to this screen here,
我将切换到这个屏幕，
where I've already logged into CS50.dev on my computer.
我已经在我的电脑上登录了CS50.dev。
And just to keep the focus on the code, I've hidden the activity bar.
为了将重点放在代码上，我已经隐藏了活动栏。
I've hidden the File Explorer, so to speak.
可以说，我已经隐藏了文件资源管理器。
So you're seeing here the area where all of my tabs are about to go
所以你在这里看到的是我的所有标签即将出现的地方
and the terminal window, where all of my commands are going to go.
以及终端窗口，我的所有命令都将在这里运行。
But I've just simplified the UI to keep our focus
但我只是简化了用户界面，以保持我们关注
on the interesting parts for now.
现在有趣的的部分。
So how do I go about actually writing and compiling and running some code?
那么，我如何实际编写、编译和运行一些代码呢？
Well, the teaser is going to be these three steps.
好吧，预告将是这三个步骤。
One of these is a command called, aptly, Code.
其中一个命令叫做，恰如其分地，Code。
And Code is just going to let me to open or create a new file,
Code 只是允许我打开或创建一个新文件，
like a file called "hello.c."
例如一个名为“hello.c”的文件。
Make is going to be, for now, my compiler that
Make 目前将是我的编译器，
allows me to make the program, that is convert source code into machine
允许我创建程序，即将源代码转换为机器代码
code, so from C to zeros and ones.
代码，所以从 C 转换为零和一。
And then weirdly, but we'll soon see why,
然后奇怪的是，但我们很快就会明白为什么，
./hello is going to be the command to run my actual code,
./hello 将是运行我的实际代码的命令，
so the textual equivalent of like double-clicking on a Mac or a PC icon
所以相当于在 Mac 或 PC 上双击图标
or tapping an icon on your phone.
或点击手机上的图标。
So that's it.
就是这样。
These three commands are going to allow me to write, to compile, and to run
这三个命令将允许我编写、编译和运行
code ultimately.
最终代码。
So let's go ahead and do that.
所以让我们继续做下去。
I'm back in my VS Code interface.
我回到了我的 VS Code 界面。
I'm going to go ahead and run "code hello.c."
我将继续运行“code hello.c”。
And notice a couple of details here.
注意这里的一些细节。
So one, there's this weird dollar sign, which has nothing to do with currency,
所以，一个是这个奇怪的美元符号，它与货币无关，
but it's just a common convention in the programming world
而它只是编程世界中的一个通用约定
to represent your prompt.
代表你的提示符。
So if a TF, if I ever say, go to your prompt,
所以，如果 TF，如果我曾经说过，去你的提示符，
we really mean, go to your terminal window.
我们实际上指的是，去你的终端窗口。
Go to the dollar sign.
去美元符号。
And the dollar sign is where you type the command.
而美元符号是您输入命令的地方。
Sometimes it's a different symbol, but a dollar sign is conventional.
有时它是一个不同的符号，但美元符号是约定俗成的。
Now that I've typed "code" space "hello.c,"
现在我已经输入了“code”空格“hello.c”，
I'm going to go ahead and hit Enter.
我将继续按下 Enter 键。
And maybe not surprisingly, this gives me
也许并不令人惊讶，这给了我
a brand new tab, a new file if you will, called "hello.c."
一个全新的标签，如果你愿意，一个新的文件，叫做“hello.c”。
And just like Word documents have their own file extension, like DOC, DOCX,
就像 Word 文档有自己的文件扩展名，例如 DOC、DOCX，
and Excel files have .XLSX and PDFs have .PDF and GIFs have .GIF and so forth,
Excel 文件有 .XLSX，PDF 文件有 .PDF，GIF 文件有 .GIF，等等，
so do C files have a file extension by convention that is .C.
所以 C 文件也按照惯例有文件扩展名，即 .C。
Now, a couple of minor points.
现在，一些小细节。
Notice that, by convention, I'm almost always
注意，按照惯例，我几乎总是
going to name my files in lowercase.
将我的文件命名为小写。
By convention, I'm never going to use spaces in my file names.
按照惯例，我永远不会在文件名中使用空格。
And my file extension, too, is going to be lowercase.
我的文件扩展名也是小写。
Long story short, accidentally hitting the spacebar
长话短说，意外地按下空格键
or using file names with spaces just tends
或者使用包含空格的文件名，往往
to make life harder when you're in a command-line environment.
在命令行环境中，会让生活更难。
So just beware silly, stupid things like that.
所以要注意像这样愚蠢的事情。
So all lowercase, no spaces for now.
现在都是小写，没有空格。
So my cursor is literally blinking because the program
我的光标不停地闪烁，因为程序
wants me to write some code.
想要我写一些代码。
I'm going to do this from memory.
我要凭记忆写。
It'll take you presumably some time to acquire the same instincts.
你可能需要一些时间才能获得相同的直觉。
But I'm going to go ahead and type this first line here,
但我现在先输入第一行，
pronounced "include standard io.h"--
读作“include standard io.h”——
more on that soon--
稍后会详细介绍——
int main(void), with some parentheses thrown in.
int main(void)，加了一些括号。
Notice what's about to happen here is a little interesting.
注意即将发生的事情有点意思。
In the code I want to type, I want what we'll
在我的代码中，我想要我们所说的
call curly braces, the sort of squiggles that you
花括号，就是你
don't use often in English, at least, but are there
在英语中并不经常使用，但它们就在
on your keyboard somewhere.
你的键盘上。
But notice what VS Code does, and a lot of programming environments,
但注意 VS Code 的操作，以及许多编程环境，
is it finishes part of my thought.
它会完成我的一部分想法。
So I'm only going to type a left curly brace,
所以我只需要输入一个左花括号，
but notice I actually get two of them.
但注意我实际上得到了两个。
And if I hit Enter, notice that not only does it scooch one down a bit,
如果我按下回车，注意它不仅向下移动了一点，
it also indents my cursor because, just like with pseudocode last week,
它还缩进了我的光标，就像上周的伪代码一样，
whenever you're doing something logically that should only
当你在逻辑上做某事时，它应该只
happen if the thing above it happens, similarly
发生在它上面发生的情况下，类似地
is indentation going to be a thing when we actually write code.
缩进将成为我们真正编写代码时的一件事。
So VS Code and programs like it just try to save us
所以 VS Code 和类似的程序只是试图为我们节省
keystrokes so I don't have to waste time hitting the spacebar
按键，所以我不用浪费时间按下空格键
or hitting Tab or wasting my human time like that.
或按下 Tab 键，或浪费我的人类时间。
All right, so with that said, I'm going to go ahead
好吧，话虽如此，我将继续
and type the last of these lines, "printf,"
输入最后一行，"printf"，
where the F is going to mean "formatted," and then a parentheses.
其中 F 代表“格式化”，然后是一个括号。
And notice it gave me two.
注意它给了我两个。
It gave me the second one for free.
它免费给了我第二个。
Sometimes it will get confused.
有时它会感到困惑。
And you can certainly override this, delete it, and start over.
你当然可以覆盖它，删除它，然后重新开始。
And now, unlike Scratch, in C, It turns out
现在，与 Scratch 不同，在 C 语言中，事实证明
I'm going to need to use double quotes anytime
我需要随时使用双引号
I'm using an English word or phrase or any human language for that matter.
我使用英语单词或短语，或者任何人类语言。
"Hello" comma "world."
“Hello” 逗号 “world”。
And then at the very end of my line, much like English uses periods,
然后在我的行末，就像英语使用句号一样，
I'm going to use a semicolon in C.
我会在 C 语言中使用分号。
So that's a lot of talking, but it's not much coding.
所以说了很多，但代码并不多。
It's technically six lines of code.
从技术上讲是六行代码。
But honestly, the only interesting one intellectually, as we'll soon see,
但老实说，从智力上来说，唯一有趣的是，正如我们很快就会看到的，
is really line 5.
实际上是第五行。
Like, that is the equivalent of that, say, block.
就像，它等同于那个，比如，块。
Now here's where I'll cross my fingers, hoping
现在，我祈祷
that I didn't make any typographical errors.
我没有犯任何打字错误。
It's going to automatically save for me.
它会自动为我保存。
And I'm going to go back to my terminal window where now I'm
我将回到我的终端窗口，在那里我正在
going to do that second command, "make" space "hello."
接下来执行第二个命令，"make" 空格 "hello"。
Common mistake-- you do not say "make hello.c," because you
常见的错误是，不要说“make hello.c”，因为你
already made that file.
已经创建了这个文件。
You say "make hello," which is the name of the program that in this case I do
你要说“make hello”，这是程序的名称，在本例中，我想
want to create.
创建它。
And Make is smart.
而 Make 很智能。
It's going to look in my folder.
它会查看我的文件夹。
And if it sees a file called "hello.c," it's
如果它看到一个名为 "hello.c" 的文件，它会
going to convert that source code to machine code
将该源代码转换为机器码
and save the results in a simpler shorter-named file just called
并将结果保存在一个更简单、更短名称的文件中，名为
"hello," like an icon on your desktop.
"hello"，就像你桌面上一个图标一样。
Now, hopefully nothing will happen.
现在，希望不会发生任何事情。
And that is a good thing, quite paradoxically.
这其实是一件好事，听起来很矛盾。
If you do anything wrong when programming, odds are you're
如果你在编程时犯了任何错误，很可能你会
going to see one or many more lines of error sort of yelling
看到一行或多行错误信息，就像在
at you that you made a mistake.
告诉你你犯了错误。
Seeing nothing happen is actually a good sign.
什么都没有发生其实是一个好兆头。
So the last command, to run my code, recall our three steps here.
所以最后一个命令，运行我的代码，回顾一下我们之前的三个步骤。
We've written code to create the file, Make to compile the file from source
我们写了代码创建文件，使用 Make 将文件从源代码
code to machine code.
编译成机器码。
So lastly is "./hello."
所以最后是“./hello”。
So this now is the equivalent of my double-clicking on a Mac or PC
所以这现在相当于我在 Mac 或 PC 上双击
or single tapping on a phone.
或者在手机上单点。
Enter.
回车。
[SIGHS] So close!
[叹气] 真是太接近了！
All right, it's pretty good.
好吧，还不错。
I got the H-E-L-L-O comma space "world."
我得到了 H-E-L-L-O，逗号，空格，"world"。
But there's something a little stupid about my output.
但我的输出有一点不太聪明。
What might rub some of you aesthetically the wrong way?
什么东西可能会让你们觉得有点不美观？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: The dollar sign.
学生：美元符号。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so the dollar sign looks like I was like, "hello,
大卫·马兰：是的，所以美元符号看起来就像我在说，“hello，
world" dollar sign in my output.
world”，输出时带了一个美元符号。
But no, that's just kind of a remnant of my prompt starting with a dollar sign.
但不是，这只是我的提示以美元符号开头的一个残留。
And this is a little nitpicky, but this just doesn't feel right,
这有点吹毛求疵，但感觉不太对，
doesn't look right.
看起来也不对。
It's not quite correct.
它不太正确。
So how can I go about fixing this?
那么我该如何解决这个问题？
Well, here's where, at least initially, it's
好吧，至少现在，
going to take some introduction to just new syntax in C to fix this.
需要引入一些 C 语言中的新语法来解决这个问题。
The simplest instinct might be to do this.
最简单的想法可能是这样做。
Well, let me just hit Enter like that.
好吧，让我像这样按回车键。
But this should soon, if not already, rub you
但这很快，如果没有的话，也会让你
the wrong way because in general, we're going
感到不对劲，因为总的来说，我们
to see that programming in C and in Python
会发现，在 C 语言和 Python 语言中
and other languages tends to be line-based.
和其他语言中，编程往往是基于行的。
Like, you should really start and finish your thought on one line.
就像，你应该真正地在一行代码中开始并完成你的想法。
So if you're in the habit of hitting Enter like this
所以，如果你习惯于像这样按回车键
and finishing your thought on the next line,
并在下一行完成你的想法，
generally programming languages don't like that.
通常情况下，编程语言不喜欢这样做。
So this is, in fact, not going to do what we expect.
事实上，这并不会按我们预期的那样执行。
And just to show you as much, I'm going to do this.
为了让你看得更清楚，我将这样做。
Let me go back to my terminal window here.
让我回到我的终端窗口。
I'm going to rerun "make hello" after making that change.
我将修改后重新运行"make hello"。
Enter.
回车。
And there we have it, like the first of our erroneous outputs.
这就是第一个错误输出。
And it's yelling at me.
它在对我大喊。
It's missing a terminating character.
它缺少一个终止符。
And there's some red in here, some green, drawing my attention to it.
这里有一些红色和绿色，吸引我的注意力。
Sometimes these error messages will be straightforward.
有时这些错误消息会很直白。
Sometimes you're going to rack your brain a bit to figure them out.
有时你需要费点脑筋才能弄明白它们。
But for now I've kind of spoiled it.
但现在我已经说破了。
Obviously Enter is not the right solution.
显然，回车不是正确的解决方案。
So let me clear my terminal window just to hide that error.
让我清除我的终端窗口，以便隐藏那个错误。
Let me delete this.
让我删除这个。
And let me propose now that I add this incantation here.
现在，我建议在这里添加这个咒语。
So backslash n, it turns out, is going to be
事实证明，反斜杠 n 将会
the sort of magical way of ensuring that you actually get
一种确保你真正获得的魔术方法
a new line at the end of your output.
你输出中的最后一行。
So let me go ahead now and rerun "make hello," because I've changed my code.
所以我现在重新运行“make hello”，因为我已经修改了代码。
I need to now reconvert, recompile the source code to new machine.
我现在需要重新转换，重新编译源代码到新的机器。
"./hello."
And now, there is the canonical "hello, world" program
现在，我们有了规范的“hello，world”程序
that I hoped to write in the first place.
我一开始就想写这个程序。
So for now, don't worry about the include.
现在，不用担心包含。
Don't worry about the standard io.
不用担心标准输入输出。
Don't worry about int or main or void or the curly braces.
不用担心int、main、void或者花括号。
Focus primarily on line 5 here.
主要关注这里的第5行。
And over the course of today and next week,
在今天和下周，
we'll start to tease apart the other characters
我们将开始拆解其他字符
that, for now, you should take at face value.
这些字符现在你可以先照单全收。
Questions, though, on any of the steps we've just done?
关于我们刚刚执行的任何步骤，有什么问题吗？
Yeah?
有吗？
STUDENT: Why is the backslash n inside the apostrophes?
学生：为什么反斜杠 n 在单引号内？
DAVID MALAN: Sure, why is the backslash n inside of the quotation marks,
大卫·马兰：当然，为什么反斜杠 n 在引号内？
if you will?
如果你愿意这么说的话？
So short answer is that's just where it needs
简短的回答是，它就应该放在那里
to be because inside of the quotes is the input that you want printf
因为在引号内是你想要 printf 输出的内容
to output to the screen.
到屏幕上。
So if you want printf, this function, to output a new line,
所以如果你希望 printf 函数输出一个新行，
it must be included in the quoted text that you give it.
它必须包含在你给它的引号文本中。
STUDENT: So the backslash n [INAUDIBLE].
学生：所以反斜杠 n [听不清]。
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·马兰：没错。
Backslash n is a special pattern that "printf no" means, OK, I should
反斜杠 n 是一种特殊模式，代表 “printf no” 意思，好的，我应该
move the cursor to the next line.
将光标移到下一行。
Good question.
好问题。
Other questions on any of these steps?
关于这些步骤，还有其他问题吗？
Yeah?
有吗？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
大卫·马兰：好问题。
So what if you actually want to print backslash n?
那么，如果你真的想打印反斜杠 n 呢？
Things get a little tricky there.
事情就变得有点棘手了。
Let me go ahead and propose that we do this.
让我来提议我们这样做。
So it turns out-- and this is often the case in programming--
结果是——在编程中经常出现这种情况——
when you want a literal character to appear,
当你想要一个字面字符出现时，
you actually put another backslash in front of it.
你实际上要在它前面放另一个反斜杠。
But this is not going to be something we do often.
但这不是我们经常做的事情。
But there is in fact a solution to that.
但实际上有一个解决方案。
But let me propose that beyond that now we compare it
但我建议，除此之外，现在我们把它
against what we've actually done.
与我们实际做的事情进行比较。
So here is the first Scratch program we wrote with the green flag there.
所以这是我们用绿色的旗帜编写的第一个 Scratch 程序。
Here, recall, is the mental model that I proposed
这里，请回忆，是我提出的心理模型
we have for almost everything we do whereby functions are just
我们几乎对所有我们做的事情都有，函数仅仅是
an implementation, say, in code of algorithms, step-by-step instructions
一个实现，比如，在代码中的算法，一步一步的指令
for solving problems.
用于解决问题。
The inputs to functions, recall from last week,
函数的输入，回忆上周，
are called arguments, or in some contexts parameters.
被称为参数，或者在某些情况下叫做参数。
And sometimes functions can have side effects.
而有时函数会有副作用。
Like last time with Scratch, there was the speech bubble
就像上次用 Scratch 时一样，有一个气泡
that magically appeared next to the cat's mouth
神奇地出现在猫的嘴巴旁边
as a sort of side effect of using the Say block.
作为使用说块的副作用。
So just like this then, we had the white oval as input.
所以就像这样，我们有白色椭圆作为输入。
The Say block was the function last week.
上周，说块是函数。
And then we had this here, side effect.
然后我们有了这个，副作用。
Well, how do we compare these things left to right?
那么，我们如何从左到右比较这些东西？
Well, here's the Say block at left.
好的，这是左边的说块。
Let's compare now to the C code at right.
现在让我们把它与右边的 C 代码进行比较。
Notice a couple of things to adapt from Scratch to C. Print
注意从 Scratch 到 C 的一些调整。打印
is almost the name of the function.
几乎是函数的名字。
It is technically "printf," for reasons we'll eventually see.
严格来说是“printf”，原因我们最终会看到。
Notice the parentheses in C are kind of evocative of the oval in Scratch.
注意 C 中的括号有点让人联想到 Scratch 中的椭圆。
And that's probably why MIT chose an oval, because a lot of languages
这也许就是 MIT 选择椭圆的原因，因为很多语言
use parentheses in this way.
以这种方式使用括号。
You still write "hello, world" just as we did last week in Scratch.
你仍然像上周在 Scratch 中一样写“hello, world”。
But per our demo thus far, you do need the double quotes--
但根据我们到目前为止的演示，你需要双引号——
and double quotes, not single quotes-- double quotes on the left and right.
双引号，而不是单引号——左右两边都有双引号。
And in order to get that new line, you need the backslash n.
为了得到换行，你需要反斜杠 n。
And one more thing is missing.
还有一件事是缺失的。
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: Semicolon.
学生：分号。
DAVID MALAN: The semicolon to finish your thought.
大卫·马兰：分号来结束你的想法。
So all of these sort of stupid things now
所以所有这些愚蠢的事情现在
that honestly you will forget initially if you've never programmed before,
说真的，如果你以前没有编程过，你一开始会忘记，
but you'll soon-- within days, within weeks--
但你很快——在几天之内，几周之内——
develop the muscle memory where all of that stuff just jumps off,
形成肌肉记忆，在那里所有这些东西都会跳出来，
jumps off the page right at you.
直接从页面上跳出来。
All right, so this backslash n is generally known,
好的，所以这个反斜杠 n 通常被称为，
just so you know, as an escape sequence.
你应该知道，作为一个转义序列。
And so backslash n allows us to specify a character that
所以反斜杠 n 允许我们指定一个字符，
might otherwise be hard to type.
否则可能难以键入。
But let's tease apart some of the other things atop that function already.
但让我们先来了解一下该函数顶部的其他一些内容。
So include stdio.h.
所以包含 stdio.h。
It turns out that in C, a lot of the functionality that
事实证明，在 C 语言中，很多功能
comes with the language is tucked away in separate files.
都是隐藏在单独的文件中的。
So if you want to use certain functions, you have to tell the compiler,
所以如果你想使用某些函数，你必须告诉编译器，
hey, I want to do some standard input and output.
嘿，我想进行一些标准输入和输出。
Like, I want to print some things on the screen.
比如，我想在屏幕上打印一些东西。
And that's because, for now, you can think of printf
这是因为，就目前而言，你可以把 printf
as living in this file, stdio.h.
看作是存在于这个文件 stdio.h 中。
That's a bit of a white lie for now.
这现在有点像善意的谎言。
But in stdio.h is essentially a declaration for printf
但是 stdio.h 本质上是对 printf 的声明，
that will teach the compiler how to print things to the screen.
它会告诉编译器如何将内容打印到屏幕上。
So "hash include" here simply tells the compiler
所以这里的 "井号包含" 只是告诉编译器，
before it does anything else essentially go ahead and find
在它做任何其他事情之前，基本上继续查找
on the local hard drive a file called stdio.h
本地硬盘驱动器上的一个名为 stdio.h 的文件
and copy/paste it there so I know now about printf.
并将其复制粘贴到那里，这样我就会知道 printf 了。
So this thing, this .h file, is what we'll technically call a header file.
所以这个东西，这个 .h 文件，我们技术上会称之为头文件。
And if you've ever heard this word, especially
如果你曾经听说过这个词，尤其是
if you have programmed before, it represents essentially what
如果你以前编写过程序，它基本上代表了我们
we'll start calling a library.
将开始称为库。
So a library in the world of programming is just code
所以编程世界中的库就是代码，
that someone else wrote that you can use.
是由其他人编写的，你可以使用。
It's usually free and open source, which means
它通常是免费的开源软件，这意味着
you can literally see the code that someone else wrote,
你可以直观地看到其他人编写的代码，
or sometimes you pay for it.
或者有时你需要为此付费。
Sometimes it's closed source, which maybe Microsoft wrote it.
有时它是闭源的，比如微软编写的。
They won't show you the code, but they will let you use the zeros and ones.
他们不会向你展示代码，但他们会让你使用 0 和 1。
So libraries are super useful because honestly
所以库非常有用，因为说实话，
even I don't really know how printf works.
即使我也不知道 printf 是如何工作的。
I've taken for granted for 25 years that if I use printf,
我 25 年来一直认为，如果我使用 printf，
stuff prints on the screen.
内容就会打印在屏幕上。
But someone smarter than me had to actually write
但是，比我更聪明的人必须实际编写
the code in C that figures out how to get the H, the E, the L-L-O, and so
用 C 语言编写的代码，它会弄清楚如何获取 H、E、L-L-O 等等，
forth onto the Mac screen, the PC screen, the phone screen, or somewhere
到 Mac 屏幕、PC 屏幕、手机屏幕或其他地方。
else.
其他地方。
So libraries allow us to stand on each other's shoulders
所以库允许我们站在彼此的肩膀上，
and so that someone else can do the hard work,
这样其他人就可以完成艰苦的工作，
and we can now solve problems that are more interesting to us,
而我们现在可以解决对我们更有趣的问题，
not the basic commodity stuff that everyone might want in their code.
而不是每个人可能在他们的代码中想要的那些基本商品。
So again, library is code that someone else wrote.
所以再说一次，库是其他人编写的代码。
A header file in C is just a file ending in ".h"
C 语言中的头文件只是一个以 ".h" 结尾的文件，
that gives you access to the same.
它可以让你访问相同的东西。
And so for instance, if you to learn more about these,
所以，例如，如果你想了解更多关于这些的信息，
there are, what are called in the world of programming, manual pages.
在编程世界中，有一些被称为手册页面的东西。
And these are textual files, like a documentation of sorts,
它们是文本文件，就像某种文档，
via which you can just learn how a function works
通过它，你可以学习一个函数是如何工作的
or how you can use its inputs or arguments.
或者如何使用它的输入或参数。
The reality is they're written for folks who aren't in CS50.
现实情况是，它们是为那些不在 CS50 的人写的。
They're written for folks who aren't just learning how to program.
它们是为那些不仅仅学习如何编程的人写的。
They're written for and by folks who have been programming for years.
它们是为那些已经编程多年的人写的，也是由他们写的。
And so frankly, they're a little hard to understand.
坦白地说，它们有点难理解。
And so CS50 has its own version thereof at this URL, manual.cs50.io,
因此，CS50 有它自己的版本，网址为 manual.cs50.io，
where you'll see not only the official documentation for C, the language,
在那里，你不仅能看到 C 语言的官方文档，
but also staff-written simplifications in layperson's terms
还能看到员工用通俗易懂的语言写的简化版
what all of the various popular functions are, what their inputs,
以及各种流行函数是什么，它们的输入是什么，
and what their outputs are.
以及它们的输出是什么。
So for instance, under stdio.h, you can actually go to that website.
例如，在 stdio.h 下，你可以访问那个网站。
You can go to a URL like this, where stdio.h is in there.
你可以访问类似这样的 URL，其中包含 stdio.h。
And you can actually see the documentation therefore.
你实际上可以看到它的文档。
So let me go ahead and do this.
所以让我来做这件事。
I'm going to go ahead in my browser here,
我在我的浏览器里这样做，
I'm going to go to manual.cs50.io.
我将访问 manual.cs50.io。
And let me go ahead here and select those functions
让我在这里选择那些函数
that are frequently used in CS50.
在 CS50 中经常使用。
And under stdio.h, you'll see a bunch of functions,
在 stdio.h 下，你会看到很多函数，
only one of which we've even discussed called printf.
其中只有一个我们讨论过，叫做 printf。
I'm going to click on printf there.
我将点击那里的 printf。
And you'll see an interface that at first glance
你会看到一个界面，乍一看
might be a little overwhelming, but it's going
可能有点让人不知所措，但它会
to start to look more and more familiar.
越来越熟悉。
So first of all, you'll see that if you want to use printf under Synopsis,
首先，你会看到，如果你想在概述中使用 printf，
you need to include this header file.
你需要包含这个头文件。
Like, you literally copy and paste that line into your own code.
就像，你真的把那行代码复制粘贴到你的代码里。
You'll also see this, which for now is a bit arcane,
你还会看到这个，目前来说有点神秘，
but this is kind of a hint as to what the function is going to look like.
但它有点提示了这个函数的样子。
But more on that soon.
但更多内容很快就会讲到。
But more importantly, you can read a description about it.
但更重要的是，你可以阅读它的描述。
And because these descriptions, when you're in less comfortable mode,
因为这些描述，当你处于不太舒服的状态时，
are written by me and the course's teaching fellows, teaching assistants,
是由我和这门课的助教、助教写的，
and course assistants, you'll find them to be much more in layperson's terms.
以及课程助理写的，你会发现它们更通俗易懂。
And so long story short, rely on this site
所以长话短说，当你想要学习如何使用某个函数时，
once you want to learn how to use some function
依赖这个网站
and also what other functions exist.
以及了解其他函数的存在。
In fact, if I go back to the main page here,
事实上，如果我回到这里的主页，
you'll see that there are all of these functions like are frequently
你会看到所有这些函数，就像经常
used in CS50.
在 CS50 中使用。
And there's hundreds more that come with C.
还有数百个 C 语言自带的函数。
But learning a programming language is not about learning all of those
但学习一门编程语言不是要学习所有这些函数，
but rather just getting a sense of where you find answers to questions when
而是当你想要尝试新的东西时，了解在哪里找到问题的答案。
you do want to try something new.
当你想要尝试新的东西时。
But what is important to know for CS50 today
但今天对 CS50 来说重要的是，
is that we have our own header file called cs50.h which has functions
我们有一个名为cs50.h的头文件，其中包含函数
that we have written just to make life easier
我们编写的这些函数只是为了让生活更轻松
in the first few weeks of the class.
在课程的前几周。
These are training wheels that we'll eventually take off.
这些是辅助轮，我们最终会把它卸掉。
But it turns out in C, especially if you've
但在C语言中，尤其是如果你之前已经
programmed before, it's actually really hard and annoying just
编写过程序，实际上真的很困难和烦人，仅仅
to get input from users, to get them to type a word or a number or something
从用户那里获取输入，让他们输入一个单词或数字或其他东西
else.
其他。
Like, C does not make this easy, in part because it's one of the earliest
就像，C语言并没有让这个变得容易，部分原因是它是最早的语言之一
languages that wasn't zeros and ones.
不是0和1。
So you have to do a lot of the heavy lifting yourself.
所以你必须自己做很多繁重的工作。
But we'll put on these training wheels today and for a few weeks
但是我们今天和接下来的几周会使用这些辅助轮
so that we can focus really on the intellectually interesting ideas of C
这样我们就可以真正专注于C语言中智力上有趣的想法
and programming without getting bogged down in certain weeds
以及编程，而不会陷入某些杂草丛生的细节
that we will come back to before long.
我们很快就会回来。
So for instance, CS50's own documentation is there at that URL.
例如，CS50自己的文档就在那个URL上。
But within the library are these functions,
但在库中是这些函数，
a function called get_string to get a string of text.
一个名为get_string的函数，用于获取字符串文本。
"String" is a synonym for just text in a programming language.
“字符串”在编程语言中只是文本的同义词。
So get_string will prompt the human for a string of text.
所以get_string会提示用户输入一个字符串文本。
Get_int is shorthand for "get integer," if you
Get_int是“获取整数”的简写，如果你
want to get a number from the user.
想从用户那里获取一个数字。
Get_float is a little more arcane-- get a floating point number,
Get_float稍微难懂一点——获取一个浮点数，
like a real number with a decimal point in it.
就像带有小数点的实数。
And dot, dot, dot, there are others, as well.
等等，还有其他。
So this is to say within CS50, we've got some user-friendly functions via which
所以这意味着在CS50中，我们有一些用户友好的函数，通过这些函数
we can actually get some input.
我们可以实际获取一些输入。
And let's go ahead and use one of these, for instance get_string
让我们继续使用其中之一，例如get_string
because recall that last week our second program in Scratch
因为还记得上周我们在Scratch中的第二个程序
was this one here, where we didn't just say "hello, world."
就是这个，我们不仅仅是说“hello, world”。
We said "hello, David," or "hello, Carter,"
我们说“hello, David”或“hello, Carter”
"hello, Julia," whoever it was typing their name in.
“hello, Julia”，无论是谁在输入他们的名字。
But to do that, we needed this Ask block in Scratch.
但是要做到这一点，我们需要Scratch中的“问”模块。
And then we used the Say block.
然后我们使用“说”模块。
And then we used the Join block to make all of this work.
然后我们使用“连接”模块来使这一切正常工作。
So let's translate this program now into C
所以让我们现在把这个程序翻译成C语言
because it's a little more interesting and representative of the kind of code
因为它更有趣，并且代表了我们将要编写的代码类型
we'll start to write.
我们将开始编写。
But we need a slightly different mental model.
但我们需要一个稍微不同的思维模型。
Still have a function here, which is the implementation in code of an algorithm.
这里仍然有一个函数，它是算法的代码实现。
We still have some inputs called arguments.
我们仍然有一些被称为参数的输入。
But previously, I said that the Say block and, in turn,
但之前我说“说”模块，反过来，
printf have side effects, which is just something visually, typically,
printf有副作用，这仅仅是视觉上，通常是
that happens on the screen.
出现在屏幕上。
Other functions actually have, what we called last week, return values.
其他函数实际上拥有，我们上周称之为，返回值。
And this is kind of analogous to a function maybe doing something for you,
这类似于一个函数可能为你做一些事情，
writing down the answer on a slip of paper, and then handing you,
将答案写在纸条上，然后递给你，
the programmer, the slip of paper to do whatever
作为程序员，你就可以对纸条上的答案做任何事
you want with it without just broadcasting it
你想怎样就怎样，不用像在屏幕上用对话框一样广播出去。
to the world with, like, a speech bubble on the screen.
就像在屏幕上用对话框一样广播出去。
So a return value is germane for a program like this
所以，对于像这样的程序来说，返回值非常重要
because recall when we used the Ask block and I typed in my name,
因为还记得我们使用“询问”模块的时候，我在里面输入了自己的名字，
where did my name end up initially?
我的名字最初在哪里？
It didn't go on the screen yet.
它还没有出现在屏幕上。
Where did it end up?
它最终在哪里？
STUDENT: In an answer.
学生：在“答案”里。
DAVID MALAN: In an "answer" puzzle piece.
大卫·马兰：在一个“答案”拼图块里。
And that special oval puzzle piece I claimed at the time
我当时说，那个特殊的椭圆形拼图块
represents a return value, so the metaphorical piece of paper
代表着返回值，所以，这块纸条（打个比方）
that the answer is written down on so that I can then use it later.
用来写答案，这样我以后就能用它。
So that's what we want to get to now in C,
所以，这就是我们现在在 C 语言中要达成的目标，
a return value that I can then do anything I want,
一个返回值，这样我就能用它做任何想做的事，
whether it's print it to the screen, change it in some way,
无论是打印到屏幕上，还是以某种方式更改它，
save it in a database, or anything else.
把它保存到数据库里，或者做其他任何事情。
So here, for instance, is what we did with Scratch,
所以，举个例子，我们在 Scratch 中是这样做的，
the input to the Say block-- or the Ask block was "what's your name," quote,
“说出”模块的输入，或者说“询问”模块的输入是 “你的名字是？”，引号，
unquote.
引号。
The function, of course, is the Ask function.
当然，这个函数就是“询问”函数。
And the return value was "answer."
返回值是 “答案”。
If we now consider how we might translate this to C,
如果我们现在考虑如何将它翻译成 C 语言，
it's going to look a little weird at first.
乍一看可能有点奇怪。
But it's going to follow a pattern today, next week, the week
但它会遵循一个模式，今天，下周，下下周
after any time we do code like this.
无论我们何时编写类似的代码，都会遵循这个模式。
So get_string, I claim, is going to be the most analogous function in C
所以，我认为，get_string 将是 C 语言中与“询问”模块最类似的函数
to the Ask block.
类似于“询问”模块。
And to be clear, this is a CS50-specific thing, training wheels of sorts.
需要明确的是，这是 CS50 独有的东西，是某种辅助工具。
But we'll show you in a few weeks what this function is doing and how you
但我们会在几周内向你们展示这个函数的功能，以及如何在对语言本身感到舒适后
cannot use it moving forward once you're comfortable with the language itself.
不再使用它。
Notice I've put parentheses, left and right,
请注意，我在左右两侧添加了括号，
as sort of a placeholder for user input.
作为用户输入的占位符。
And that user input is going to be "what's your name?"
而用户输入将是“你的名字是？”
But I can't just put "what's your name" in parentheses.
但我不能直接在括号里写“你的名字是？”
What do I minimally need to add in there, too?
我至少还需要添加什么？
STUDENT: Quotes.
学生：引号。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so the double quotes, left and right.
大卫·马兰：没错，左右两侧都要加上双引号。
So let me go ahead and add those in.
所以，让我添加一下。
I left a space here, not for a new line.
我在此留了一个空格，不是为了换行。
I could move the cursor to the next line.
我可以将光标移到下一行。
But I minimally at least want to move the cursor at least one space over
但我至少要将光标向右移动一个空格
just so it looks pretty, so that when I'm prompted for my name,
这样看起来会更美观，当我被要求输入名字时，
there's a space between the question and my answer.
问题和答案之间会有一个空格。
But it could also be backslash n.
也可以是反斜杠 n。
That's just an aesthetic choice on my part.
这只是我个人的审美选择。
But what do I do with the answer that comes back from get_string?
但我如何处理从 get_string 返回的答案？
This is where the text is going to look different today.
这就是文本在今天看起来不同的原因。
In C, you start to use an equals sign from left to right respectively.
在 C 语言中，你开始使用等于号，从左到右依次排列。
And on the left, you put the name of the variable in which you
在左侧，你放入变量的名称，用于
want to store that return value.
存储那个返回值。
So a return value is kind of a conceptual thing.
所以返回值是一种概念性的东西。
You can do with it what you want.
你可以用它做任何你想做的事情。
And if I want to store it longer term in a variable,
如果我想长期将它存储在一个变量中，
like x or y or z in math class, I can just give it a name here-- x
就像数学课上的 x、y 或 z 一样，我可以在这里给它一个名称——x
or y or z or, more reasonably, "answer," or any other English word.
或者 y 或 z，或者更合理地，"answer"，或者任何其他英文单词。
No spaces, generally lowercase, same heuristics as before, but this means
一般来说，没有空格，小写字母，与之前的启发式方法相同，但这意味着
now, ask the user, what's their name?
现在，问用户，他们的名字是什么？
Whatever they type in, go ahead and store it from right
无论他们输入什么，都从右
to left in this variable called "answer."
到左存储在这个名为“answer”的变量中。
But C's not done with us yet.
但 C 语言还没有完成。
If you've learned Python or certain other languages,
如果你学过 Python 或其他一些语言，
you'd kind of be done writing code at this point.
你基本上就已经完成代码编写了。
In C, though, you additionally have to tell the compiler what type of variable
然而，在 C 语言中，你还需要告诉编译器你想要使用哪种类型的变量
you want to use.
。
So if it's a string of text, you say "string."
所以，如果是文本字符串，就说“string”。
If it's an integer, a number, you say "int," as we might have seen before.
如果是整数，也就是数字，就说“int”，就像我们之前可能看到过的一样。
So it's a little more pedantic.
所以它更加迂腐。
It's more annoying, frankly, the more onus on you and me, the programmers.
坦率地说，它更烦人，对我们这些程序员来说，负担更重。
But this just helps the compiler know how
但这只是帮助编译器知道如何
to store it in the computer's memory.
在计算机的内存中存储它。
And I'm so close to being done with this line of code, but what's missing?
我已经快完成这行代码了，但还缺少什么？
STUDENT: Semicolon.
学生：分号。
DAVID MALAN: So semicolon.
大卫·马兰：所以是分号。
And mark my words, if you've never programmed before, sometime this week,
记住我的话，如果你以前从未编程过，本周的某个时候，
this semester, you will forget a semicolon.
这个学期，你会忘记写分号。
You will raise your hand.
你会举手。
You'll get frustrated because you can't understand why your code's not working.
你会感到沮丧，因为你无法理解为什么你的代码无法运行。
You will run into stupid issues like that.
你会遇到这样的愚蠢问题。
But do take faith that they are stupid issues.
但相信它们是愚蠢的问题。
It doesn't mean it's not clicking for you or you're not a programmer.
这并不意味着你没有理解或者你不是一名程序员。
It just takes time to see these things if it's a new language to you.
如果你学习的是一门新的语言，理解这些东西需要时间。
So there now is my semicolon.
所以现在我的分号已经写上了。
All right, let's go ahead then and do something
好了，让我们继续做一些
with that return value using the second of the big puzzle pieces in Scratch.
关于返回值的事情，使用 Scratch 中第二大块拼图。
So when I wanted to say, "hello, David," or whatever the human's name is,
所以当我想要说“你好，大卫”，或者说任何人的名字的时候，
I kind of stacked my puzzle pieces like this.
我把我的拼图块堆叠起来，就像这样。
This is actually similar to Python and maybe some other languages some of you
这实际上类似于 Python，也许还有一些其他语言，你们中的一些人
have learned.
已经学习过。
But C is a little bit different.
但 C 语言略有不同。
And the closest analog to this Scratch solution is going to look like this.
与这个 Scratch 解决方案最相似的方案将看起来像这样。
I still use printf because printf is the equivalent of Say.
我仍然使用 printf，因为 printf 等同于 Say。
Inside of my parentheses, I'm going to go ahead and say, weirdly, "hello, %s."
在我的括号内，我将说，奇怪的是，“hello，%s”。
So there's no real analog in C of Join.
所以C语言中没有类似于Join的函数。
Instead, there's a way to specially format text using printf, hence the F
相反，可以使用printf函数以特殊格式化文本，因此F
in "printf."
是“printf”中的。
And what you do in printf is you type whatever English word
在printf中，你可以输入任何你想输入的英文单词
or human words that you want.
或者你想输入的任何人类语言的单词。
You then use %s a placeholder.
然后使用 %s 作为占位符。
If you want a string of text to be added to your own text,
如果你想将一段文本添加到自己的文本中，
you literally write "%s."
你只需要输入"%s"。
And let me anticipate a question from the crowd-- how do you print out %s?
让我来预判一个来自人群的问题——如何打印出 %s？
There's a solution to that, too, if you literally ever want to print out %s.
当然也有解决方法，如果你真的想打印出 %s。
But it's deliberately a weird choice of characters
但它有意选择了一些奇怪的字符
so that the probability that we ever need to type this ourselves
这样一来，我们自己需要输入这些字符的可能性
is just low that no one really worries too much about it.
就很低，所以没人会真正为此感到担忧。
All right, but that's not quite enough.
好了，但这还不够。
In addition to saying "hello", comma, space, placeholder %s--
除了输入"hello", 逗号, 空格, 占位符 %s--
and just for vocabulary sake, that's a format code.
顺带一提，那是一个格式代码。
Again, "format" being the F in printf.
再次强调，“format”是printf中的F。
I still need my double quotes around the whole thing.
我仍然需要在整个内容周围使用双引号。
In this case, to match my previous program,
在这种情况下，为了与我之前的程序匹配，
I am going to go ahead and add the backslash n
我将添加反斜杠n
to move the cursor to the next line.
将光标移动到下一行。
And now I've left a crazy amount of room here, but that's deliberate.
现在我在这里留下了大量的空间，但这是故意的。
Does anyone have an instinct for what I'm probably
有人能猜到我接下来可能会
going to want to add after the quotes but still inside of the parentheses?
在引号之后，但仍然在括号内的内容吗？
STUDENT: The answer.
学生：答案。
DAVID MALAN: So answer itself.
大卫·马兰：所以是答案本身。
I need to somehow tell printf with a second input,
我需要用一个额外的输入告诉printf，
otherwise known as an argument, what I want to substitute for that %s.
也就是一个参数，我想用什么来替换 %s。
And so I put a comma and then the name of the variable
所以我放了一个逗号，然后是变量的名称
that I want printf to figure out how to plug in here.
我想让printf计算出如何将它插入这里。
So honestly it's a little annoying, and this is kind of a dated approach.
老实说，这有点烦人，而且这是一种过时的做法。
Newer, more modern languages, like we'll see later
更新、更现代的语言，比如我们稍后会看到的
in the course, Python and JavaScript, actually
课程中的Python和JavaScript，实际上
have much more user-friendly ways of doing it.
有更友好的方法来实现它。
But once you wrap your mind around the heuristics, the rules here,
但是一旦你理解了这些启发式方法，这些规则，
it's just formatting a string by plugging in whatever you want
它只是通过将你想要的任何内容插入
into this format string, so to speak.
这个格式字符串来格式化字符串，可以这么说。
And again, the comma here is important.
再次强调，这里的逗号很重要。
This signifies that it takes one input at left and a second input at right.
这表示它在左侧接收一个输入，在右侧接收第二个输入。
But notice this comma.
但请注意这个逗号。
There's technically two commas.
从技术上来说，有两个逗号。
But I'm not claiming that this function takes three inputs.
但我不是说这个函数接收三个输入。
Why?
为什么？
This comma I'm pointing out doesn't mean the same.
我指出的这个逗号并不意味着相同的意思。
STUDENT: It's because that comma's part of the quotation marks
学生：因为那个逗号是引号的一部分
and it's been part of the string.
并且是字符串的一部分。
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·马兰：没错。
This comma that I'm pointing to is part of the quotation marks and therefore
我指出的这个逗号是引号的一部分，因此
part of my string of English text.
这是我英文文本的一部分。
So this is just English grammar.
所以这仅仅是英语语法。
This is sort of C syntax.
这有点像 C 语言语法。
And again, these are the sort of annoying little details
而且，这些是那种让人头疼的小细节
that we're using the same symbol for different things, but context matters.
我们用相同的符号来表示不同的东西，但上下文很重要。
So just stare at your code, look carefully left to right,
所以仔细盯着你的代码，从左到右仔细观察，
and generally the answer will pop out, no pun intended.
通常答案会跳出来，没有双关语的意思。
OK, questions now on this syntax before we actually write it and run it?
好的，现在在我们实际编写并运行之前，对这个语法有什么问题吗？
Yeah?
是的？
STUDENT: Why is the backslash n not after the answer?
学生：为什么反斜杠 n 不在答案之后？
DAVID MALAN: Why is the backslash n not after the answer?
大卫·马兰：为什么反斜杠 n 不在答案之后？
So the way functions work, including printf,
函数的工作方式，包括 printf，
is that you pass to them one argument inside of the parentheses.
就是你向它们传递一个括号内的参数。
And then if you have a second argument, you put it after this comma here.
然后如果你有一个第二个参数，你把它放在这个逗号之后。
But the way printf works is that its first argument is always a string
但是 printf 的工作方式是，它的第一个参数始终是一个字符串
that you want to be formatted for you.
你想要格式化的内容。
So anything you want printed on the screen has to go in those quotes.
所以你想在屏幕上打印的任何东西都必须放在这些引号中。
And you can perhaps extrapolate from this.
也许你可以从这里推断出来。
If I actually wanted to say multiple things in this sentence, so "hello,"
如果我确实想在这句话中说很多东西，比如 "hello"，
maybe first name, last name, I could actually do "hello" comma, %s, space,
也许是名，姓，我可以做 "hello" 逗号，%s，空格，
%s, if I had two variables, one called First Name, one called Last Name.
%s，如果我有两个变量，一个叫做名，一个叫做姓。
But then I would need another comma for a third input to the function.
但是，我需要另一个逗号作为函数的第三个输入。
And so it's very general purpose in that sense.
所以从这个意义上说，它非常通用。
Questions?
有问题吗？
Yeah?
是的？
STUDENT: Can you abstract this further by [INAUDIBLE] the "hello" [INAUDIBLE]??
学生：你能通过 [听不清] "hello" [听不清] 来进一步抽象它吗？
DAVID MALAN: OK, so can you abstract away the format string itself, "hello,"
大卫·马兰：好的，所以你能将格式字符串本身抽象出来吗， "hello"，
comma answer?
逗号答案？
Short answer, yes, but not nearly as easily in C
简短的答案是，是的，但 C 语言远不如其他语言那样容易。
as you can in other languages.
像其他语言那样容易。
So that's why we're keeping it simple for now.
所以我们现在把它保持简单。
But you're going to love something like Python or JavaScript,
但你会喜欢像 Python 或 JavaScript 这样的东西，
where a lot of this complexity goes away.
很多复杂性消失了。
But you'll see also in Python and JavaScript and other languages,
但你也会在 Python 和 JavaScript 以及其他语言中看到，
they still are inspired by syntax like this.
它们仍然受到像这样的语法的启发。
So just understanding it now will be useful for multiple languages
所以现在理解它将对多种语言有用
down the line.
在未来。
All right, so let's actually do something with this code
好的，让我们用这段代码做点什么
rather than just talk about what it might be doing for us.
而不是仅仅讨论它可能为我们做了什么。
Let me go over to, for instance, VS Code again.
让我再次回到 VS Code。
And I'm going to go ahead now and remove this middle line of printf.
我现在将继续删除这行 printf 代码。
I'm still in my same file called "hello.c."
我仍然在我的同一个名为 "hello.c" 的文件中。
I'm going to clear my terminal window just to eliminate distraction.
我将清除我的终端窗口，以消除干扰。
And to do that, I can literally type "clear."
为此，我可以直接输入 "clear"。
But this is just for aesthetic's sake.
但这只是为了美观。
That's not functionally that useful.
这在功能上并不实用。
Or you can hit Control L to achieve the same on your keyboard.
或者你可以按下 Control L 在你的键盘上实现同样的效果。
But I'm going to go back to line 5 here, where I previously just
但是我要回到第 5 行，我之前只是
said "hello, world."
说了“你好，世界”。
And I'm going to do this instead.
而我将改为这样做。
I'm going to give myself a variable called string.
我将给自己一个名为字符串的变量。
Sorry, I'm going to give myself a variable called
对不起，我将给自己一个名为
answer, the type of which is string.
答案的变量，其类型为字符串。
I'm going to set it equal to whatever the return
我将把它设置为 get_string 函数的返回值
value is of get_string, asking an English question, "what's your name?"
，它会询问一个英文问题，“你叫什么名字？”
with just a single space just to move the cursor over,
后面只加一个空格，以便将光标移过去，
followed by a semicolon.
后面跟一个分号。
Then I'm going to go ahead and say printf, quote,
然后我要继续说 printf，引号，
unquote, "hello, placeholder, backslash n,"
引号，“你好，占位符，反斜杠 n”，
comma, and then what goes here again?
逗号，然后这里又是什么？
STUDENT: Answer.
学生：答案。
DAVID MALAN: This is where answer goes.
大卫·马兰：答案应该放在这里。
And then I just need a semicolon on the right of that.
然后我只需要在它右边放一个分号。
But I think now that I'm done.
但我认为我现在已经完成了。
But let me point out a couple of details.
不过，让我指出几个细节。
This got very colorful, very pretty quickly.
它很快就变得五颜六色，非常漂亮。
And it's not like the black and white code I had on the screen a moment ago.
这不像我刚才屏幕上的黑白代码。
This is because what programs like VS Code do for us is it "pretty" prints,
这是因为像 VS Code 这样的程序为我们做了“美观”打印，
or rather it syntax highlights our code for us.
或者更确切地说，它为我们语法高亮显示代码。
So syntax highlighting means just add some colors to the code
所以语法高亮显示意味着只是在代码中添加一些颜色
so that different ideas pop out.
以便不同的想法脱颖而出。
So you'll notice, for instance, that printf here, get_string here
所以你会注意到，例如，这里的 printf，这里的 get_string
are in purple because they represent functions, just like the Say block.
都是紫色的，因为它们代表函数，就像“说”块一样。
Here, "what's your name?", quote, unquote, in VS Code
这里，“你叫什么名字？”，引号，引号，在 VS Code 中
is a light blue instead of white.
是浅蓝色而不是白色。
But it's still going to be consistent if I use strings of text elsewhere,
但如果我在其他地方使用文本字符串，它仍然是一致的。
as well.
也是。
So I didn't type anything special.
所以我没有输入任何特殊的东西。
This isn't like Microsoft Word or Google Docs,
这不像 Microsoft Word 或 Google Docs，
where I'm highlighting and changing colors of things.
我在那里高亮显示并改变事物颜色。
This is all happening automatically.
这一切都是自动发生的。
But it's just unicode text.
但它只是 Unicode 文本。
It's just being interpreted automatically
它只是被自动解释
and having these colors applied so that things pop out more usefully visually.
并应用这些颜色，以便事物在视觉上更有效地突出显示。
Now, I've unfortunately made a mistake.
现在，我不幸地犯了一个错误。
But I'm going to deliberately induce this one because you, too,
但我要故意诱发这个错误，因为你也会
will probably make this mistake.
很可能犯这个错误。
I'm going to go ahead and run "make hello"
我将继续运行“make hello”
again, because I've changed my code.
再次，因为我修改了我的代码。
So I have to regenerate the machine code from the new source code.
所以我必须从新的源代码重新生成机器代码。
But unfortunately, when I hit Enter now, my God,
但不幸的是，当我按下回车键时，我的天啊，
the errors don't even fit on the screen.
这些错误甚至无法显示在屏幕上。
So let me make this bigger.
所以让我把它放大一点。
I'm going to click the little caret symbol here just
我将点击这里的小插入符号
to make my terminal bigger for just a moment.
以便将我的终端放大一会儿。
And you'll see that there's more lines of errors
你会看到还有更多行的错误
than there are of code that I actually wrote,
比我真正写下的代码还要多，
often which is written pretty arcanely, again, for programmers who've
这些代码通常写得非常深奥，再次强调，是为那些
been writing code for 10, 20 years.
已经写了 10 年、20 年代码的程序员写的。
But there are some details that pop out.
但有一些细节很突出。
So notice the problem is definitely with hello.c.
所以请注意，问题肯定出在 hello.c 上。
So great, it is my fault. This syntax here means that line 5 is the problem.
太好了，是我的错。这里的语法意味着第 5 行有问题。
And this next 5 means character 5.
而接下来的 5 代表第 5 个字符。
So you can literally triangulate your bug, your mistake by going to line 5
所以你可以通过找到第 5 行
and then over five, and it's somewhere in that area.
然后向右移动 5 个字符，错误就在这个区域。
Specifically, "the area is use of undeclared identifier string.
具体来说，是“区域是使用未声明的标识符 string”。
Did you mean standard in?"
你是想说标准输入吗？”
I don't think I did.
我不这么认为。
Like, I do want string, and then there's some other complexity here.
比如，我确实想要 string，但这里还有一些其他复杂性。
But what's important here is not the specifics of this error but really
但这里重要的是不是这个错误的具体内容，而是
the implication that it doesn't recognize the word
它无法识别“string”或“get_string”这两个词，
"string" or "get_string."
这一点。
Now, why might this be?
为什么会出现这种情况呢？
Yeah?
是吧？
STUDENT: You said that in order to [INAUDIBLE]
学生：你说过为了 [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·马兰：没错。
Because we are using get_string, which I claimed
因为我们正在使用 get_string，我声称
is a CS50 thing that we'll use for a few weeks,
这是 CS50 的东西，我们会用几周，
C does not know about it out of the box, so to speak.
但 C 语言并不知道它，就好像它没有自带这个功能一样。
I have to teach the compiler that get_string exists,
我必须告诉编译器 get_string 存在，
just like I taught the compiler that printf exists by including
就像我告诉编译器 printf 存在一样，通过包含
the appropriate header file.
相应的头文件。
And in this case, quite simply, it's called includeCS50.h.
在这种情况下，很简单，它叫做 includeCS50.h。
That now teaches the compiler, oh, someone else
这现在告诉编译器，哦，其他人
wrote this function already, get_string, and with it this type of variable
已经写了这个函数，get_string，以及这种类型的变量
called "string."
叫做“string”。
So now if I go back to my terminal window
所以现在如果我回到我的终端窗口
and rerun the exact same command, "make hello"-- maybe crossing my fingers--
并重新运行完全相同的命令，“make hello”——也许我会祈祷一下——
now nothing in fact goes wrong because the compiler
现在实际上不会出错，因为编译器
has been brought up to speed with all of the functionality it needs.
已经了解了它需要的所有功能。
And now if I do ./hello, Enter, there it is, what's my name?
现在如果我运行 ./hello，按回车，它就出现了，你的名字是什么？
And notice the cursor is one space over just
请注意，光标只是向右移动了一个空格，
because I thought that looked prettier than having the cursor right
因为我认为这样看起来比光标紧挨着问号更漂亮。
next to the question mark.
紧挨着问号。
D-A-V-I-D as my input, and Enter.
我输入 D-A-V-I-D，按回车。
And "hello, David."
然后就显示“hello, David”。
Questions on any of this code thus far?
到目前为止，对任何代码有疑问吗？
Questions?
有问题吗？
Any of the code.
任何代码都可以。
No?
没有？
All right, so let's introduce some other functionality into the mix.
好的，让我们把一些其他的功能引入进来。
It turns out that there are other types of data,
事实证明，还有其他类型的数据，
other types of variables in the world, not just strings
其他类型的变量，不仅仅是字符串，
but indeed, per before, we have things called
事实上，像之前一样，我们有叫做
integers, "int" for short, floating point values, "float" for short,
整数，简称为 “int”，浮点数，简称为 “float”，
and a few others as well.
以及其他一些。
So rather than only focus on string, let's
与其只关注字符串，不如让我们
get a little more interesting with numbers
用数字来点缀一下
here and see what we can do with something like integers, again
看看我们能用整数做些什么，再一次
"int" for short, by taking a look at not get_string, as before, but now
简称“int”，不再像之前那样查看 get_string 函数，而是
how about get_int.
看看 get_int 函数。
And for this, I'm going to give us a few other tools in our toolkit,
为此，我将为我们的工具箱提供一些其他的工具，
those format codes to which I alluded earlier, like %s,
我之前提到的那些格式代码，比如 %s，
fortunately are pretty straightforward.
幸运的是，它们非常简单直观。
And here is a list of most of the popular format codes
这里列出了大多数常用的格式代码
that you might ever care about with printf.
你可能永远会关心 printf 函数的格式代码。
In particular, we saw %s for string.
特别是，我们看到了 %s 代表字符串。
And you can perhaps guess which one we're going to use for integers.
也许你可以猜出我们会用哪个格式代码来表示整数。
STUDENT: %i.
学生：%i。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so %i is what we're going to use for integers.
大卫·马兰：是的，所以我们用 %i 来表示整数。
And this is the kind of thing that you can
而这种信息你可以
consult in the manual pages or a slide like this.
在手册页面或类似这样的幻灯片中找到。
There's only a few of them that you might frequently use.
其中只有几个你可能会经常使用。
But let's go ahead and use integers in a more interesting context, not
但让我们在更有趣的上下文中使用整数，而不是
just using functions.
仅仅使用函数。
But let's revisit this idea of conditionals.
但让我们重新审视条件语句的概念。
And conditionals in Scratch were like these proverbial forks in the road.
Scratch 中的条件语句就像谚语中所说的岔路口。
Like, do you want to do this thing or this thing or this other thing?
就像，你想要做这件事，还是做那件事，或者做另外一件事？
It's a way of making decisions in a program, which
这是一种在程序中做出决策的方式，它
is going to be super useful and pretty much omnipresent in any problems
将非常有用，并且几乎无处不在我们试图解决的任何问题中
that we try to solve.
我们试图解决。
So let me give you a few more building blocks
所以让我给你展示一些 C 语言中的构建块
in C by doing the side-by-side comparison again.
通过再次进行并排比较。
So here in Scratch is how we might say if two variables, x and y,
所以，在 Scratch 中，我们可以这样说，如果两个变量，x 和 y，
one is less than the other, then go ahead and say, quote, unquote,
其中一个小于另一个，那么就继续说，引号引起来，
"x is less than y."
“x 小于 y”。
So kind of a stupid program.
所以这是一个有点愚蠢的程序。
But just to show you the basic syntax for Scratch,
但只是为了向你展示 Scratch 的基本语法，
this is how you would ask the question, if x is less than y, then say this.
这就是你如何提出这个问题，如果 x 小于 y，那么就说这句话。
So Say is the function.
所以 Say 是函数。
"If" is the conditional.
“If” 是条件语句。
And the green thing here we called, what?
而这里的绿色部分我们称之为，什么？
What did we call it?
我们称之为？
Yeah?
对吗？
STUDENT: A Boolean.
学生：布尔值。
DAVID MALAN: A Boolean or a Boolean expression,
大卫·马兰：布尔值或布尔表达式，
which is just a fancy way of saying a question whose
这只是一个花哨的说法，表示一个问题的
answer is true or false, yes or no, 1 or 0, however you want to think about it.
答案是真或假，是或否，1 或 0，无论你如何思考它。
In C, the code is going to look like this.
在 C 语言中，代码将看起来像这样。
So it'll take a little bit of habit, a little bit of muscle memory to develop.
所以这需要一些习惯，需要一些肌肉记忆的培养。
But you're going to say "if," then in parentheses,
但你要说“if”，然后在括号里，
you're going to say "x less than y," assuming x and y are variables.
你要说“x 小于 y”，假设 x 和 y 是变量。
You're then going to use these curly braces.
然后你将使用这些大括号。
And then if you want to say, quote, unquote, "x is less than y"
然后，如果你想说，引号引起来，“x 小于 y”
in C, what function should we use here presumably?
在 C 语言中，我们应该在这里使用哪个函数呢？
So printf.
所以是 printf。
So printf, quote, unquote, "x is less than y."
所以是 printf，引号，"x is less than y"。
So it's a bit of a mouthful, but again notice the pattern.
它看起来有点复杂，但再次注意这个模式。
Name of the function is printf.
函数的名称是 printf。
In the parentheses, left and right, is the argument to printf,
在括号中，左右括号之间是传递给 printf 的参数，
which is, quote, unquote, "x is less than y."
也就是引号，"x is less than y"。
And again, just for aesthetics, to move the cursor to the next line,
同样，仅仅为了美观，为了将光标移动到下一行，
which you don't have to worry about in Scratch because everything's
在 Scratch 中你不需要担心这个问题，因为所有的内容
in speech bubbles, we're adding a backslash n, as well.
都在气泡中，我们也添加一个反斜杠 n。
So notice that these curly braces, as they're
所以请注意，这些花括号，就像它们
called, much like the orange puzzle piece here,
被称为的那样，就像这里橙色的拼图一样，
are kind of hugging the code like this.
像这样包围着代码。
And I'll note that technically speaking in C,
我还要指出，从技术上讲，在 C 语言中，
If you only have one line of code inside of your conditional,
如果你在你的条件语句中只有一行代码，
you can actually omit the curly braces altogether.
你可以完全省略花括号。
And the code will still work if you have one single line of code.
如果你只有一行代码，代码仍然可以运行。
Why?
为什么？
Just saves people some keystrokes.
只是为了让大家省点按键。
If you have two lines, three lines, or more in there,
如果你有两行、三行或更多行代码，
you need the curly braces.
你需要花括号。
But I'll always draw it with the curly braces in class
但我上课时总是用花括号来画它
so it resembles Scratch as closely as possible.
这样它就尽可能地像 Scratch 一样。
As an aside to some of you who have programmed before,
顺便说一句，对于那些之前已经编程过的人，
you might be cringing now because like you really
你现在可能很痛苦，因为你真的
like your curly brace to be over here instead of here, that,
喜欢把你的花括号放在这里而不是那里，那是
too, is a stylistic choice.
也是一种风格的选择。
And we'll talk, too, about this in the class.
我们也会在课堂上讨论这个问题。
Aesthetically, stylistically there are certain decisions we can make.
从美学和风格上来说，我们有一些决定可以做。
But generally in a class, in a company, you as a student or an employee
但一般来说，在课堂上，在公司里，你作为一名学生或员工，
would simply standardize on one set of rules, so to speak.
只需简单地统一一套规则，也可以这么说。
So we'll use these rules for formatting our code in class consistently.
所以我们将在课堂上始终使用这些规则来格式化我们的代码。
All right, any questions on this snippet of C code?
好了，这段 C 代码有什么问题吗？
All right, a couple of others then.
好了，再看另外几个。
So here is how, in Scratch, we might have a two-way fork in the road.
所以，在 Scratch 中，我们可能会有一个岔路口。
If x is less than y, say x is less than y, else say x is not less than y.
如果 x 小于 y，就说 x 小于 y，否则就说 x 不小于 y。
In C, It's going to look pretty much the same.
在 C 语言中，它看起来几乎是一样的。
But notice I'm adding an "else" keyword here with another set of curly braces.
但请注意，我在此处添加了一个“else”关键字，并带有一组新的花括号。
I'm going to have a couple of more printf's.
我将再添加几个 printf。
But in C, even though it's clearly keyboard based,
但在 C 语言中，即使它明显是基于键盘的，
it's just text, no more puzzle pieces, it's kind of the same shape,
它只是文本，不再有拼图，它形状也差不多，
so to speak, and it's definitely the same idea.
可以这么说，而且它绝对是同一个想法。
So it's following a pattern.
所以它遵循一个模式。
What about a three-way fork in the road, if x is less than y,
那么三叉路口呢，如果 x 小于 y，
then say x is less than y, else if x is greater
就说 x 小于 y，否则如果 x 大于
than y, say x is greater than y, else if x equals y, then say x is equal to y.
y，就说 x 大于 y，否则如果 x 等于 y，就说 x 等于 y。
Well, you can probably see where this is going.
好吧，你可能已经猜到它会往哪里发展了。
On the right-hand side, it looks almost the same.
在右边，它看起来几乎是一样的。
In fact, if I add in the printf's, it's really almost the same,
事实上，如果我加上 printf 语句，它真的几乎是一样的，
at least logically.
至少从逻辑上来说。
But there is at least one curiosity, seemingly a typo
但至少有一个奇怪的地方，看起来像个打字错误
but it's not this time.
但这次不是。
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: The double equals.
学生：双等于号。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, the double equal signs does not match Scratch,
大卫·马兰：是的，双等号在 Scratch 中并不匹配，
but it's not in fact a bug or a mistake in C. Anyone
但它实际上不是 C 语言中的错误。任何人都
have an intuition for why I did use two equal signs instead of one here?
能直觉地知道我为什么在这里用两个等号而不是一个等号吗？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: Because otherwise it could be mistaken for a variable.
学生：因为否则它可能会被误认为是变量。
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·马兰：没错。
Well, otherwise it would be mistaken for a variable, specifically
好吧，否则它会被误认为是变量，特别是
assignment of a variable.
变量的赋值。
So recall that in previous code, when we used the get_string function,
所以回想一下，在我们之前的代码中，当我们使用 get_string 函数时，
we used an equals sign to assign, from right to left, the value of a variable.
我们使用等号从右到左给变量赋值。
And that's a reasonable decision.
这是一个合理的决定。
"Equal" kind of means that the two should ultimately
“等于”的意思是，这两个最终应该
be equal even though you think about it from going right to left.
相等，即使你从右到左考虑它。
Unfortunately, the authors of C kind of [? painted ?] themselves into a corner.
不幸的是，C 语言的作者把自己逼到一个角落里。
And presumably, decades ago when they realized, oh, shoot,
而且可以推测，几十年前当他们意识到，糟糕，
we've already used a single equal sign, how
我们已经使用过一个等号了，如何
do we represent equality of two values, the answer they came up with was,
来表示两个值的相等呢？他们想出的答案是，
all right, we'll just use two instead.
好吧，我们只需要用两个。
And thus was born this decision.
就这样，这个决定诞生了。
Is it the best one?
这是最好的吗？
Who knows?
谁知道呢？
Crazy enough, in other languages, like JavaScript,
更疯狂的是，在其他语言中，比如 JavaScript，
you have not just one, but two, but also three equal signs
你不仅有一个，还有两个，甚至还有三个等号
in a row to solve yet another problem.
排成一行，用来解决另一个问题。
So reasonable people will disagree as to how good or bad these decisions are.
所以，理性的观点会对这些决定是好是坏有不同的看法。
But in C, this is what you must do.
但在 C 语言中，你必须这样做。
But there's a bad design decision here, too.
但这里也有一个糟糕的设计决策。
It's still correct, the code, left and right.
代码仍然是正确的，左右两边。
But I bet I could critique the quality of the design of both the Scratch code
但我敢打赌，我可以批评 Scratch 代码和 C 代码的设计质量，为什么？
and the C code for reasons, what?
因为什么？
STUDENT: Do we have to do else if x equals [INAUDIBLE]??
学生：我们必须做 else if x 等于 [听不清]？
DAVID MALAN: OK, no, really good intuition.
大卫·马兰：好的，不，直觉很好。
Do we have to ask this third question, "else if x equals y?"
我们必须问第三个问题吗，“else if x 等于 y”？
So short answer, no, logically, right?
所以简而言之，不，从逻辑上来说，对吧？
Just based on arithmetic, either x is less than y or x is greater than y
仅仅基于算术，要么 x 小于 y，要么 x 大于 y
or, what's the only other possible answer?
或者，还有什么其他可能的答案？
They must be equal, logically.
它们必须相等，从逻辑上来说。
So technically, you're just kind of wasting the computer's time
所以从技术上来说，你只是在浪费电脑的时间
by asking this question because it already knows,
因为你问了这个问题，而它已经知道了，
at that point, the answer.
到那时，答案。
And you're wasting your time as the programmer bothering
而且你作为程序员，在浪费时间，去麻烦
to type out more code or more puzzle pieces
去写更多代码或更多拼图块。
than you need because logically one stems from the other.
比你需要的多，因为从逻辑上讲，两者是相互关联的。
So I can tighten this up, get rid of the "else, if," just use an "else."
所以我可以简化一下，去掉“else, if”，直接用“else”。
And I can do the same thing over here in C, thereby avoiding
在C语言中也可以做同样的事情，从而避免
the double equal sign altogether, but not because it's wrong
完全使用双等号，但不是因为它错误
but because you're wasting time, because now you're potentially asking only two
而是因为你在浪费时间，因为现在你可能只问了两个
questions, two Boolean expressions, instead of 50% more by asking
问题，两个布尔表达式，而不是通过询问增加 50%
a total of three questions at most.
最多三个问题。
Other questions then on this kind of code, logically or otherwise?
还有其他关于这种代码的问题吗，无论是逻辑上的还是其他方面的？
No?
没有？
All right, so if we have these puzzle pieces, so to speak, at our disposal,
好的，如果我们拥有这些拼图，我们可以使用它们，
how can we go about actually using these?
我们该如何使用它们？
Well, suppose that we actually want to do something with values.
假设我们真的想对值做点什么。
Let's introduce variables in C, as well.
让我们在C语言中也引入变量。
We saw an example using a string a moment ago.
我们之前看到了一个使用字符串的例子。
But what about with something like integers?
但整数呢？
Well, you might not have used this in Scratch.
你可能没有在Scratch中使用过它。
But here's the orange puzzle piece in Scratch
但在Scratch中，橙色的拼图块
via which you can create a variable called counter to count things.
可以让你创建一个名为“counter”的变量来计数。
And you can set it equal to some value like 0.
你可以把它设置为某个值，例如 0。
Now, you can perhaps guess where we're going with this.
现在，你可能猜到我们下一步要做什么了。
If I want in C a variable called counter and I want to set it equal to 0,
如果我在C语言中想要一个名为“counter”的变量，并且想要把它设置为 0，
I use a single equal sign because logically you
我使用单等号，因为从逻辑上讲，你
read it from right to left, or technically it's
从右到左读取它，或者从技术上讲，它是
executed from right to left.
从右到左执行的。
But that's not enough in C. What's missing from the screen?
但这在C语言中还不够。屏幕上缺少什么？
STUDENT: Data type.
学生：数据类型。
DAVID MALAN: I need a what?
戴维·马兰：我需要什么？
STUDENT: You need a data type.
学生：你需要数据类型。
DAVID MALAN: So we need a data type.
戴维·马兰：所以我们需要数据类型。
And if it's going to be an integer, indeed I'm going to use int.
如果它要成为一个整数，我确实要使用“int”。
And now the other mistake I keep making is--
现在我一直在犯的另一个错误是——
STUDENT: Semicolon.
学生：分号。
DAVID MALAN: So a semicolon at the end of the line.
戴维·马兰：所以行末需要一个分号。
So it's a little more verbose than some languages.
所以它比一些语言更啰嗦。
But if you read it left to right, this is
但如果你从左到右阅读，这就是
how you tell C to give you a variable called counter of type int
你告诉C语言给你一个名为“counter”的变量，类型为“int”
and initialize it to a value of 0.
并将它初始化为 0。
That's all.
就这些了。
All right, how about, in Scratch, if you want to change that variable by 1,
好的，在Scratch中，如果你想将这个变量改变 1，
by adding 1 to it?
给它加上 1？
In Scratch, it's super simple.
在Scratch中，这非常简单。
You just change it by 1 or even negative 1
你只需将它更改为 1 甚至负 1
if you want to go up or down respectively.
如果你想分别向上或向下。
In C, it turns out you have a few different ways to do this.
在C语言中，你实际上有几种不同的方法可以做到这一点。
And this looks like it's not mathematically possible,
这看起来在数学上是不可能的，
but that's because equals is assignment, recall.
但那是因为等号是赋值，还记得吗？
So this line of code is not saying that counter equals counter plus 1,
所以这行代码不是说“counter 等于 counter 加 1”，
because that's just not possible using typical numbers.
因为使用普通数字这是不可能的。
But this means take counter's value, add 1 to it,
但这意味着取计数器的值，加 1，
and assign it back to the counter variable.
并将其重新赋值给计数器变量。
So it's like incrementing counter in this way.
所以这就像这样递增计数器。
But this is such a common thing in C and in programming
但在 C 语言和编程中，这是非常常见的
to increase or decrease the values of variables,
增加或减少变量的值，
there's a more succinct syntax.
有一个更简洁的语法。
This is identical.
这完全一样。
And it might take you a little practice to get used to it,
你可能需要练习一下才能习惯它，
but it just saves you some keystrokes.
但这节省了你一些按键。
But it similarly adds 1, or whatever number you use there.
但它同样加 1，或者你在那里使用的任何数字。
And this is such a common operation in C especially
这在 C 语言中尤其是一个很常见的操作
that there's an even tighter way of executing the same idea.
因此有一个更紧凑的方式来执行相同的想法。
And you can literally just say counter++ and then semicolon in this case.
在这种情况下，你可以直接说 counter++，然后分号。
All three are exactly the same.
这三种方式完全相同。
All three are perfectly correct.
这三种方式都是完全正确的。
But you'll learn over time that typing less on the screen
但你最终会明白，在屏幕上少打字
is probably going to save you some time.
可能可以节省你一些时间。
Meanwhile, if we wanted to do the opposite and do something like minus 1
同时，如果我们想要做相反的操作，比如减 1
in Scratch, we could similarly do minus minus in C. Or we could do--
在 Scratch 中，我们可以类似地在 C 语言中使用减减。或者我们可以做--
yeah, we could do minus minus in C here at right.
是的，我们可以在这里在 C 语言中使用减减。
All right, so just some additional building blocks, translating
好的，所以只是一些额外的构建块，将
from scratch to C. Why don't we go ahead and try using this perhaps
从 Scratch 翻译到 C 语言。为什么我们不尝试使用它呢？
in the following way?
用以下方式？
Let me go ahead and go back to VS Code.
让我回到 VS Code。
And let me propose that we do something like this.
我建议我们做这样的事情。
In VS Code, I'm going to go ahead and clear my terminal window.
在 VS Code 中，我将清除我的终端窗口。
I'm going to close "hello.c" by just clicking
我将通过点击来关闭 "hello.c"
the X. I'm going to go ahead and create a new file called "compare.c"
X。我将创建一个名为 "compare.c" 的新文件
because the purpose in life of this program
因为这个程序的生命意义
is going to be to compare integers on the screen.
将是在屏幕上比较整数。
This time I'm not going to mess up.
这一次我不会搞砸。
I'm going to preemptively include CS50.h.
我会预先包含 CS50.h。
I'm going to preemptively include stdio.h.
我将预先包含 stdio.h。
And here, too, is a very common mistake in learning C. It is not "studio.h."
这里也是学习 C 语言时的一个很常见的错误。它不是 "studio.h"。
So when you email us asking why "studio.h" is not working,
所以当你给我们发邮件问为什么 "studio.h" 不起作用时，
that's because that is not the word.
那是因为那个词不对。
It is "standard io.h," meaning standard input and output,
它是 "standard io.h"，意思是标准输入和输出，
stuff involving the screen and the keyboard.
涉及屏幕和键盘的东西。
Then I'm going to go ahead and, just as before, int main(void),
然后，就像之前一样，我将继续 int main(void)，
but we'll come back to that eventually as to what it means.
但我们最终会回到它的含义。
And now inside of "main," which is just where the main part of my program goes,
现在在 "main" 中，它只是我的程序的主要部分所在，
again you can think of this as being analogous to "when green flag clicked."
你可以把它想象成类似于 "当绿色旗帜被点击时"。
This just kicks everything off.
这只是启动一切。
I'm going to go ahead and do two things.
我将做两件事。
I'm going to go ahead and get an integer called x,
我将获得一个名为 x 的整数，
and I'm going to prompt the user for that int
并提示用户输入该整数。
and just say something like, "what's x?", space.
然后说类似“x是多少？”，后面加空格。
Then I'm going to do int y equals get_int, quote, unquote, "what's y?",
然后我要做 int y 等于 get_int，引号，引号，"y是多少？"，
space.
加空格。
And then let's just do something simple like, if x is less than y,
然后让我们做一些简单的，例如，如果x小于y，
then go ahead and print out, quote, unquote,
就打印，引号，引号，
"x is less than y backslash n," semicolon.
"x小于y，换行符"，分号。
So it's not a very deep program.
所以这不是一个非常复杂的程序。
It's just going to do what most any human brain could do pretty quickly.
它只是在做大多数人类的大脑可以很快完成的事情。
But it's at least demonstrating how we might use now
但这至少说明了我们现在如何使用
something like a conditional in code.
像代码中的条件语句这样的东西。
So let me go ahead and re--
所以让我继续 re--
let me compile this code for the first time, make compare, enter.
让我第一次编译这段代码，输入 make compare，回车。
Nothing bad happens, which is good. "./compare" is how I run the program.
没有出现错误，这很好。"./compare" 是我运行程序的方式。
And just to tease this apart, dot, as we'll soon see,
为了更清楚地解释，点，正如我们很快就会看到，
essentially means that the file is in your current folder.
本质上意味着该文件位于您的当前文件夹中。
So dot means in your current folder.
所以点代表当前文件夹。
And we'll eventually see that dot dot means your parent
我们最终会看到双点代表您的父级
folder, like the one that contains wherever
文件夹，就像包含我所在位置的那个
I am on my computer's hard drive.
在我的电脑硬盘上。
All right. ./compare.
好的。./compare。
What's x?
x是多少？
1.
2 for y.
y是2.
And hopefully it should say that x is less than y.
希望它会显示x小于y。
So pretty straightforward.
所以非常简单明了。
Proof by example.
例子证明。
And hopefully this would work in other cases, too.
希望这在其他情况下也能奏效。
But if I flip that around and I rerun it, ./compare, and I do 2 and 1,
但是如果我反过来，重新运行，./compare，输入2和1，
nothing's going to happen.
什么也不会发生。
But you would expect that because there's
但你会期望是这样的，因为有
only one Boolean expression deciding whether or not
只有一个布尔表达式决定是否
I should actually type this out.
我应该实际把它输入出来。
So what's going on?
所以发生了什么？
Well, if this helps you, you might find it
好吧，如果这对你有所帮助，你可能会发现它
useful to think about the logic of any program, be it in Scratch or C,
对于理解任何程序的逻辑，无论是 Scratch 还是 C，都很有帮助。
as kind of a flowchart of sorts.
可以把它想象成一种流程图。
And we'll put up a few of these over time just in case
我们会不时地展示一些流程图，以防
you're a particularly visual thinker.
你是个特别善于视觉思考的人。
And this represents what it is I just did.
这代表了我刚刚做的操作。
So here in this picture is where the program starts conceptually.
所以在这张图片中，程序从概念上开始运行。
And any time you see a diamond, think of that as a Boolean expression,
当您看到菱形时，把它想象成一个布尔表达式，
a question that's being asked.
一个被问到的问题。
And the question being asked is, is x less than y?
而被问到的问题是，x是否小于y？
That has two possible answers, true or false, yes or no respectively.
这个问题有两个可能的答案，分别是真或假，即“是”或“否”。
So let me propose, per the arrow, that if the answer is true, then print out,
所以让我们假设，根据箭头，如果答案是真，则打印出来，
per this rectangle, "x is less than y," just quote, unquote, and then stop.
根据这个矩形，"x小于y"，引号，引号，然后结束。
That's it for the program.
这就是程序的全部内容。
But logically, if x is not less than y, that
但从逻辑上讲，如果x不小于y，那么
is that question's answer is false, we'll just skip right to the end
问题的答案是假，我们直接跳到末尾
and stop.
并结束。
So this is a control-flow diagram.
这是一个控制流程图。
It's just a pictorial way that you could write
它只是用图形的方式让你可以在
on a piece of paper that just represents what it is the program is doing.
纸上表示程序正在做的事情。
And this gets a little more interesting if now we
如果我们现在做点其他事情，它会更有趣。
do something else with the code.
对代码做点其他事情。
For instance, instead of just concluding that it's less than 1 or the other,
例如，与其只是得出小于1或其他结论，
let's go back to the code here.
我们回到这里的代码。
Let me clear my terminal window.
让我清除我的终端窗口。
And let me add an "else."
让我添加一个 "else"。
So else, go ahead and print out "x"--
所以 else，继续打印出 "x" --
I don't think I want to say this-- "greater than y."
我不认为我想说这个 -- "大于 y"。
It's not quite right.
不太对。
What would be reasonable to say here?
这里合乎逻辑的说法是什么？
STUDENT: "x is not less than y.
学生: "x 不小于 y。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, subtle, but "x is not less than y" because it could be equal.
戴维·马兰: 是的，微妙，但 "x 不小于 y"，因为它可能等于 y。
We don't know if we're only checking two scenarios here.
我们不知道我们在这里是否只检查了两种情况。
So if I recompile this, make compare, ./compare.
所以如果我重新编译这个，make compare, ./compare。
Now if I do 1, comma 2, I still get the same answer.
现在如果我输入 1，逗号 2，我仍然得到相同的答案。
If I rerun ./compare 2, comma 1, I now get the opposite answer.
如果我重新运行 ./compare 2，逗号 1，我现在得到相反的答案。
It's not as good as might be ideal.
这并不像理想的那么好。
It'd be nice to know if it's equal to or greater than.
如果知道它等于或大于，会更好。
But at least that's all of the code that we have here.
但至少这是我们这里所有的代码。
And just to now paint a picture, if I go back
为了画一个图，如果我回到
to my control-flow diagram, my flow chart here,
我的控制流程图，我的流程图在这里，
this is what it looked like before logically.
从逻辑上来说，它以前是这样的。
Now that I've added in a second branch, so to speak,
现在，我已经添加了第二个分支，这么说吧，
now, if the answer is false, I first print out x is not less than y,
现在，如果答案是错误的，我首先打印出 x 不小于 y，
and then I stop the program.
然后我停止程序。
So same idea, but the decision tree, if you will,
所以，同样的想法，但是决策树，如果你愿意，
if you've taken a 10 or the like, is getting a little bit bigger now
如果你学过 10 或类似的课程，现在决策树会变得稍微大一些
conceptually.
在概念上。
All right, what if we do something more than this?
好吧，如果我们做更多的事情呢？
Let's actually have that third condition.
让我们实际实现第三种情况。
Let me go back into my code here.
让我回到这里的代码。
I'm going to hide the terminal window just to make room for more code.
我要隐藏终端窗口，以便为更多代码腾出空间。
And I'm going to say, "else if x is greater
我要说，“else if x 大于
than y," then go ahead and say not "x is not less than y,"
y，” 那么继续说，不是 "x 不小于 y"，
but rather "x is greater than y."
而是 "x 大于 y"。
And then down here, I'll do an "else if x equals equals y,"
然后在这里，我会添加一个 "else if x 等于等于 y"，
then I can go ahead and say printf, "x is equal to y backslash n,"
那么我就可以继续说 printf，"x 等于 y 反斜杠 n"，
close quote.
关闭引号。
All right, so now if I run it-- let me open my terminal window again.
好的，所以现在如果我运行它--让我重新打开我的终端窗口。
Let me rerun make compare.
让我重新运行 make compare。
Let me rerun ./compare.
让我重新运行 ./compare。
1 and 2 are the same.
1 和 2 是相同的。
Let me rerun it.
让我重新运行它。
2 and 1 are the same.
2 和 1 是相同的。
Let me rerun it a third time.
让我第三次重新运行它。
1 and 1 are now in fact equal.
1 和 1 现在实际上是相等的。
So this works correctly.
所以这是正确的。
But why did I make a point of using these "else if"s?
但是我为什么要特意使用这些“else if”呢？
Put another way, couldn't I just make my life a little simpler
换句话说，我不能让我的生活更简单一些吗？
and just say, if this, then that?
直接说，如果这样，那就那样？
If this, then that.
如果这样，那就那样。
Just ask all three questions.
只需问三个问题。
Keep the code simple.
保持代码简单。
Don't bother with these else's.
别管这些else。
Would this work for me?
这对我来说有用吗？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: It just seems like [INAUDIBLE] the program
学生：这看起来就像 [听不清] 程序
doesn't have to run the rest.
不必运行剩下的部分。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so it saves a little bit of time because in this case,
大卫·马兰：对，因此这节省了一点时间，因为在这种情况下，
just like in English, this is like asking three separate questions.
就像在英语中一样，这就像在问三个不同的问题。
And it's not harnessing any information from previous questions
而且它没有利用之前问题的任何信息
in order to decide whether you should bother asking that other question.
来决定是否需要问另一个问题。
In other words, if x is less than y-- and you already
换句话说，如果x小于y——而且你已经
figured that out because it's 1 and 2 respectively-- you're
弄清楚了，因为它们分别是1和2——你会
going to print this.
打印这个。
Why would you waste time asking this question when
为什么你要浪费时间问这个问题，当
it's not going to be true?
它不会是真的？
Why would you waste time asking this question when
为什么你要浪费时间问这个问题，当
it's not going to be true?
它不会是真的？
And so the point I wanted to make here, which
所以我想在这里强调的是，
is that if we visualize that particular design,
那就是如果我们可视化那个特定的设计，
what the flow chart looks like is actually this.
流程图的样子实际上是这样的。
And let me zoom in at the top.
让我放大顶部的图像。
If you ask the question "is x less than y," well,
如果你问“x是否小于y”，那么
you're going to go ahead and say, x less than y.
你就会继续说，x小于y。
Then if you go down to the next question,
然后如果你往下看下一个问题，
you're still going to ask is x greater than y.
你仍然会问x是否大于y。
And then below that, you're still going to ask is x equal equal to y?
然后在下面，你仍然会问x是否等于y？
So no matter what x and y are, you're asking one, two, three questions all
所以无论x和y是什么，你都会问一个、两个、三个问题，所有
of the time.
的时间。
But if we actually go in and do what we did the first time,
但如果我们真的进去，做我们第一次做的事，
where if I go back to my code and I undo this edit and add back the "else if"s--
如果我回到我的代码，撤销这个编辑，并添加回“else if”——
and now let me go back to the flow chart,
现在让我回到流程图，
which I claim is bad because it's one, two, three questions, one
我声称它很糟糕，因为它是一个、两个、三个问题，一个
or two of which might not be necessary-- now if I visualize what I just did,
或者两个可能是不必要的——现在如果我可视化我刚才做的事情，
the flow chart gets a little more complicated looking,
流程图看起来稍微复杂了一些，
but it's going to be better designed, more efficient.
但它将设计得更好，更有效率。
Why?
为什么？
Well, because if I start at the top here, I ask one question,
嗯，因为如果我从这里开始，我问一个问题，
is x less than y.
x是否小于y。
If the answer is true, OK.
如果答案是正确的，好的。
I say x less than y.
我说x小于y。
And then, boom, I sort of cheat and go all the way
然后，砰，我有点作弊，直接走到
to the end of the program and stop, having asked only one question.
程序的末尾并停止，只问了一个问题。
If, though, x is not less than y, OK, fine, I'll ask you a second question.
但是，如果x不小于y，好的，没问题，我会问你第二个问题。
But if the answer is true, boom, I print out x is greater than y,
但如果答案是正确的，我就会输出 x 大于 y，
and then I stop.
然后就停止。
And only in a perverse case where x actually
只有在一种极端情况下，x 实际上
equals y, which I'm going to claim is very unlikely or infrequent,
等于 y，我声称这不太可能或不常发生，
only then am I going to ask one, two, three questions to figure out whether
只有在那时，我才会问一、二、三个问题来确定是否
or not to print something at all.
是否要输出任何内容。
So this is what we mean by distinguishing between correctness
这就是我们所说的区分代码的正确性，
of code-- because it's still correct--
因为它仍然是正确的，
but this version is better designed because hopefully you're
但这个版本设计得更好，因为希望你会
going to go down this branch or this branch rather than the longest one
走这条分支或这条分支，而不是最长的那条分支
frequently.
经常。
Any questions now about this code or this visualization thereof?
现在关于这段代码或它的可视化有任何问题吗？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: I don't know if [INAUDIBLE]
学生：我不知道是否[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: A perfect segue.
戴维·马兰：完美的过渡。
Why did I bother, though, even asking this question?
不过，我为什么要费心问这个问题呢？
Don't need to because when I hit this button--
不需要，因为当我按下这个按钮时，
hopefully I have the right slide in place--
希望我的幻灯片放对了位置，
this would be even better than that design.
这将比那个设计更好。
So thank you for teeing that up.
感谢你提出这个问题。
This is the same picture.
这是同一张图片。
It sort of got bigger because there's fewer nodes,
它变大了，因为节点更少了，
fewer shapes in the picture.
图片中的形状更少了。
Notice that if x less than y, boom, we say as much, and we stop.
请注意，如果 x 小于 y，我们会这么说，然后停止。
If x is not less than y but it's greater than y, boom, we stop.
如果 x 不小于 y，但它大于 y，我们会停止。
Or if it's not greater than, we immediately
或者，如果它不大于，我们会立即
conclude x indeed is equal to y.
得出结论 x 确实等于 y。
And again, we stop.
我们再次停止。
So this picture is about as efficient and as
所以，这张图的效率和
well designed as we can make our logic.
设计得都尽可能好。
That's about as good as we can solve this problem.
这就是我们能解决这个问题的最佳方法。
So if I go back to my code now to make my C code
所以，如果我现在回到我的代码中，让我的 C 代码
match that, the only thing I need to do is stop wasting the computer's time.
与之匹配，我唯一需要做的是停止浪费计算机的时间。
Don't ask that third question.
不要问第三个问题。
Just logically, mathematically conclude that of course it's
从逻辑上和数学上得出结论，它当然会
going to be equal at that point in the story.
在故事中的那个时刻相等。
All right, any other questions on this?
好的，关于这个还有其他问题吗？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Sorry, a little louder?
戴维·马兰：抱歉，能大声一点吗？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
戴维·马兰：真是个好问题。
What if I put in something that's not a number?
如果我输入了非数字的内容呢？
So here, too, is where the CS50 library and the implementation of get_int
所以，这也是 CS50 库和 get_int 实现发挥作用的地方
will be your friend.
将成为你的好帮手。
So for instance, if I run ./compare and I want to compare cats and dogs,
例如，如果我运行 ./compare，我想比较猫和狗，
I could type in "cats," Enter.
我可以输入 "cats"，然后回车。
It's just going to prompt me again and again.
它会一直提示我输入。
It's not going to let me type in "dogs" either.
它也不会让我输入 "dogs"。
It's going to force me to give it an integer.
它会强制我输入一个整数。
C does not do that by default.
C 语言默认不会这样做。
And in fact, as we'll soon see over the course of CS50,
事实上，正如我们将在CS50课程中很快看到，
C is actually a very dangerous language at the end of the day
C实际上是一种非常危险的语言
because it just trusts that the human is doing what it wants.
因为它只是相信人类正在做它想做的事。
And as such, a lot of today's software that is hacked in some ways,
因此，当今许多以某种方式被黑客攻击的软件，
if it's using C or another language called C++,
如果它使用C或另一种叫做C++的语言，
are actually very vulnerable to certain types of hacking,
实际上非常容易受到某些类型的黑客攻击，
whereas other languages that we'll get to in the class are less so for reasons
而我们将在课堂上学习的其他语言则不会，原因是
like this.
像这样。
All right, so besides this, let's consider just one other data type.
好的，除了这个之外，让我们再考虑一种数据类型。
how about.
怎么样？
So besides strings, besides chars, there's some others on this list here.
除了字符串，除了字符，这里还有其他一些东西。
Sorry, besides strings, besides integers,
抱歉，除了字符串，除了整数，
there's this other data type here in C known as a char for a single character.
在C中，这里还有另一种数据类型被称为char，用于表示单个字符。
So here, let me just tease this apart.
所以，让我把这些分开。
A string is indeed a string of text.
字符串确实是一串文本。
It is zero or more characters together.
它是由零个或多个字符组成的。
A char is always precisely one character.
char始终是一个字符。
Not all languages bother distinguishing between a single character
并非所有语言都关心区分单个字符
and a string of characters.
和字符串。
But in C, a string is typically multiple characters,
但在C中，字符串通常由多个字符组成，
but technically can be zero.
但从技术上讲可以是零。
Coincidentally, it could be one.
巧合的是，它可以是一个。
But it's capable of being more.
但它可以包含更多字符。
But a char is literally, as the word implies, a single character.
但是，char字面意思是，正如这个词所暗示的，一个字符。
All right, given that, notice that in the CS50 library,
好的，考虑到这一点，请注意，在CS50库中，
besides get_string, besides get_int, we also have get_char,
除了get_string，除了get_int，我们还有get_char，
so another handy function for just getting a single character
所以，另一个用于获取单个字符的便捷函数
from the user.
来自用户。
Now, why would it be useful to get a single character from the user?
现在，为什么从用户那里获取单个字符有用呢？
Well, what if you're just doing something
好吧，如果你只是在做一些事情
that you and I do pretty frequently when you install new software
你和我在安装新软件时经常做的事情
or fill out some form?
或者填写一些表格？
You agree to some form of terms and conditions.
你同意某种形式的条款和条件。
So in fact, let me go back over to VS Code here.
实际上，让我回到VS Code这里。
And let me propose that I create a new program called agree.c,
让我提议创建一个名为agree.c的新程序，
so something akin to asking for the user's agreement.
所以，类似于询问用户的同意。
So in VS Code, I'm going to type "code agree.c."
所以，在VS Code中，我要输入"code agree.c"。
And I'm going to do some quick boilerplate.
我将进行一些快速操作。
So include CS50.h, include stdio.h, int main(void).
所以，包含CS50.h，包含stdio.h，int main(void)。
And then inside of main, which is like the "green flag clicked,"
然后在main内部，就像"绿色旗帜被点击"，
I'm going to do this.
我要做这个。
Go ahead and get a character from the user,
继续从用户那里获取一个字符，
and ask them something simple like, "Do you agree?,"
并询问他们一些简单的问题，比如："你同意吗？"，
expecting a yes/no response.
期待一个是/否的回应。
But at the beginning of this line, I need to put the return value somewhere.
但是，在这行的开头，我需要把返回值放到某个地方。
So I'm going to put it in a variable called
所以，我把它放在一个叫做
C. And in programming, if you're just getting a single value,
C的变量中。在编程中，如果你只是获取一个值，
it's OK sometimes to use X and Y or C when you're using--
在某些情况下，使用 X 和 Y 或 C 时是可以的，当你使用--
in larger programs, you'll benefit from using actual words like "answer,"
在更大的程序中，使用像“答案”这样的实际单词会更有益，
like we did from the get go.
就像我们从一开始就做的那样。
But C has to be a specific type.
但 C 必须是特定的类型。
So I'm going to literally say "char," and then
所以我将直接说“char”，然后
I'm going to finish my thought with a semicolon.
我会用分号结束我的想法。
And here's now how I could check if the user agrees or not.
现在，我可以检查用户是否同意。
I could do something like this.
我可以做这样的事情。
If the value of C equals equals, quote, unquote,
如果 C 的值等于等于，引号，引号，
lowercase 'y,' then go ahead and print out "Agreed backslash n."
小写“y”，然后继续打印“同意反斜杠 n”。
Else if the variable C has a value equal to lowercase 'n', let's go ahead
否则，如果变量 C 的值等于小写“n”，让我们继续
and print out, say, "Not agreed," as though I'm agreeing or not to some
并打印出，比如，“不同意”，就好像我同意或不同意某些
terms and conditions.
条款和条件。
But notice these are not typos.
但请注意，这些不是打字错误。
What did I do ever so subtly different from last time I used text?
我做了什么与上次使用文本时略有不同的事情？
Yeah?
对吧？
STUDENT: Single quotes instead of double quotes.
学生：单引号而不是双引号。
DAVID MALAN: Single quotes instead of double quotes.
大卫·马兰：单引号而不是双引号。
So here's the heuristic.
所以这是启发式方法。
When using strings, which are generally multiple characters,
当使用字符串时，字符串通常是多个字符，
have to use double quotes.
必须使用双引号。
When using a single character, you should use single quotes
当使用单个字符时，应该使用单引号
around the single character.
围绕单个字符。
So let me go ahead now and, make agree.
所以我现在就去做，让它同意。
Nothing went wrong, which is good. ./agree, Enter,
一切顺利，这很好。 ./同意，回车，
and let me go ahead and type in y for yes.
然后我继续输入 y 代表是。
It seems to work.
它似乎有效。
Let me run it again. ./agree. n for no, and it seems to work.
我再运行一次。 ./同意。n 代表否，它似乎有效。
And just if I type in something random like question mark, I don't know,
如果我输入一些随机的东西，比如问号，我不知道，
it doesn't crash.
它没有崩溃。
It just ignores me because I only had two Boolean expressions there.
它只是忽略了我，因为我只在那里写了两个布尔表达式。
But notice that it's actually a little buggy arguably.
但请注意，它实际上可能有点错误。
Let me run it again. ./agree, Enter.
我再运行一次。 ./同意，回车。
How about capital Y because, like, my Caps Lock is down.
大写 Y 怎么样，因为我的大小写锁定键被按下了。
OK, it just ignores me.
好的，它只是忽略了我。
Let me do it again. ./agree, capital N because my-- oops--
我再做一次。 ./同意，大写 N 因为我的-- 哎呀--
because my Caps Lock is down.
因为我的大小写锁定键被按下了。
OK, it just ignores me.
好的，它只是忽略了我。
But this should make sense because I'm literally checking for lowercase.
但这应该是合理的，因为我实际上是在检查小写字母。
So how could I fix this?
那么我该如何解决这个问题？
How could I fix this without just changing lowercase to uppercase,
我该如何解决这个问题，而不仅仅是将小写字母改为大写字母，
because that would then break it in the other direction?
因为那样做会破坏另一个方向的代码？
Yeah?
对吧？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, let's just add another branch here, so to speak.
大卫·马兰：是的，我们可以在这里添加另一个分支，可以这么说。
So if variable C equals equals capital Y, then I can go ahead here
所以如果变量 C 等于等于大写 Y，那么我可以在此处继续
and say printf agreed.
并说 printf 同意。
And then let me close my terminal to make more room.
然后我关闭我的终端以腾出更多空间。
Otherwise, down here, else if C equals equals capital N,
否则，在下面，else if C 等于等于大写 N，
let's go ahead and again say printf not agreed.
让我们继续说 printf 不同意。
And I claim that this would actually now work.
我声称这实际上现在可以工作了。
It's a four-way fork in the road, but I'm at least
这是一条四岔路口，但至少
checking for lowercase, uppercase, lowercase, uppercase for y and n
我正在检查 y 和 n 的小写、大写、小写、大写。
respectively.
分别。
I claim that this is correct, but this too,
我声称这是正确的，但这也
even if you've never programmed before, should start today
即使你以前从未编程过，也应该从今天开始
to rub you the wrong way.
让你不爽。
Like, we can do better.
就像，我们可以做得更好。
This isn't the best design.
这不是最好的设计。
Why might that be?
为什么呢？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: Could you change the character c to be uppercase, like before you even
学生：你可以将字符 c 更改为大写，就像在您甚至
[INAUDIBLE]?
[听不清]？
DAVID MALAN: Ah, clever.
大卫·马兰：啊，聪明。
So could we change the variable c to just be forced to uppercase
所以我们能否将变量 c 强制转换为大写
or maybe forced to lowercase?
或者强制转换为小写？
No matter what the human types, we just do that ourselves so that way
无论人类输入什么，我们自己就那样做，这样
we can just simplify this again to two possible scenarios.
我们就可以再次将它简化为两种可能的情况。
I love that, but we haven't seen any functions yet
我喜欢那样，但我们还没有看到任何函数
in C that would let me change things to uppercase or lowercase.
在 C 中，可以让我将事物更改为大写或小写。
So we'll get there, but a good instinct and correct.
所以我们会做到这一点，但这是一个很好的直觉，而且是正确的。
Other thoughts?
还有其他想法吗？
STUDENT: Use "or."
学生：使用“或”。
DAVID MALAN: So we could use "or" in some sense, like a logical "or."
大卫·马兰：所以我们可以某种意义上使用“或”，就像逻辑上的“或”。
What I don't like about this, to be clear, is that it's repeating itself.
让我说明一下，我不喜欢它的一点是，它在重复自己。
And there's this principle in programming, and in life in general,
并且编程中，以及生活中一般都遵循这样一个原则：
like, don't repeat yourself unnecessarily.
不要不必要地重复自己。
And by that I mean I literally have the same line 10 as 14.
我的意思是，我的第 10 行和第 14 行完全一样。
I have the same line 18 as 22.
我的第 18 行和第 22 行完全一样。
And if anything, one, I literally wasted twice as much time as I needed to.
而且，如果有什么的话，我实际上浪费了我所需时间两倍的时间。
Put another way, per our discussion of Scratch,
换句话说，根据我们对 Scratch 的讨论，
what if I go in and just change something like,
如果我进去只更改某些东西，比如
I want to be more excited, like "Agreed!"?
我想更兴奋一些，比如“同意！”？
Well, I might forget to change it in the other place.
好吧，我可能会忘记更改另一个地方。
And let's just claim for today's purposes that that looks stupid,
并且就今天而言，我们假定这看起来很蠢，
it's a bug, because I want them to be consistent.
这是一个错误，因为我希望它们保持一致。
So don't invite situations where you might change something
所以不要制造你可能在一个地方更改某些东西，
in one place but not another.
而另一个地方不更改的情况。
Just only write it in one place total.
总共只写在一个地方。
So I like this idea of "or"-ing things together.
所以我喜欢将事物“或”在一起的这个想法。
So let me go ahead and delete what I just did.
所以让我继续删除我刚刚做的东西。
And just to be clear, too, while this is on the screen, when you highlight code
并且为了说明一下，当你在屏幕上高亮代码时，
in VS Code based on how we've configured it, these dots just show you
在 VS Code 中，根据我们的配置，这些点只显示了
how much I've indented because in C, stylistically, the convention
我缩进了多少，因为在 C 中，风格上，惯例
is generally to indent four spaces and maybe four more spaces.
通常是缩进四个空格，可能还会再缩进四个空格。
So those dots just help you count without having
所以这些点只是帮助你计数，而无需
to manually eyeball things yourself.
手动估算。
But let me delete those lines.
但是让我删除这些行。
Let me delete these lines.
让我删除这些行。
And this is going to look a little weird,
这看起来会有点奇怪，
but the way you can "or" two thoughts together, so to
但你可以将两个想法“或”在一起，
speak, like "or" them together, is you don't say "or,"
也就是说，将它们“或”在一起，你不用说“或”，
but you use two vertical bars, which syntactically
而是使用两个竖线，在语法上
means the English word "or."
意味着英文单词“或”。
And you can just ask the other question, if C equals,
然后你可以问另一个问题，如果C等于，
quote, unquote, capital 'Y.'
引号，引号，大写“Y”。
And then down here, I can say or C equals equals capital 'N.'
然后在这里，我可以说或者C等于等于大写“N”。
So it adds a little more code to each of those lines,
所以它在每一行都添加了一些额外的代码，
but it doesn't add redundancy, because I've not duplicated my printf.
但它没有添加冗余，因为我没有复制我的printf。
I've not added more curly braces unnecessarily.
我没有不必要地添加更多花括号。
Now as an aside, there's the opposite of "or", logically is the word "and."
顺便说一下，"或"的反义词，在逻辑上是“和”。
Just so you've seen it, I could do this.
为了让你看到它，我可以这样做。
"&&" in C is how you express that the thing on the left must be true
在 C 语言中，"&&" 表示左侧的东西必须为真
and the thing on the right must be true.
右侧的东西也必须为真。
But why would this make no sense in this context of line 8?
但这在第 8 行的语境中为什么没有意义呢？
STUDENT: It can't be uppercase and lowercase.
学生：它不能同时是大写和小写。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, at least to my knowledge,
大卫·马兰：是的，至少据我所知，
a character can't be both lowercase and uppercase.
一个字符不能同时是小写和大写。
That just makes no logical sense.
这在逻辑上没有意义。
So indeed "or" is what we want in this case.
所以，在这种情况下，我们确实想要“或”。
Other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
STUDENT: In CS50.h, is there a way to directly compare strings [INAUDIBLE]??
学生：在 CS50.h 中，有没有办法直接比较字符串 [听不清]？
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
大卫·马兰：好问题。
Via CS50.h, is there a way to compare strings.
通过 CS50.h，有没有办法比较字符串。
Short answer, no.
简短的回答，没有。
But C is going to give us that capability.
但 C 会给我们这种能力。
And in fact, next week, among the things we'll do is actually compare strings.
事实上，下周，我们会做的事情之一就是比较字符串。
And if you've programmed before, you'll see in C
如果你之前做过编程，你会在 C 语言中看到
that it actually doesn't work the way that you might expect.
它实际上并不像你预期的那样工作。
But that's a problem, too, that we will solve.
但这也是一个我们会解决的问题。
But that transcends CS50.
但这超出了 CS50 的范围。
That's a question for C. Other questions on this kind of logic?
这是一个关于 C 语言的问题。关于这种逻辑还有其他问题吗？
Just to make this real then, anytime you click one of those EULAs
为了使这变得真实，当你点击任何一个 EULA
or terms and conditions on a form in a piece of software,
或者软件中表单上的条款和条件时，
odds are there is code as simple as this underneath the hood.
很可能在幕后有像这样的简单代码。
Maybe it's graphical.
也许它是图形化的。
Maybe it's checking for you clicking this button
也许它检查你是否点击了这个按钮
or maybe hitting the Enter key.
或者也许是按了回车键。
But underneath the hood is presumably some kind
但在幕后，可能有一些
of conditional checking for those kinds of outputs.
条件检查，用于这些类型的输出。
All right, how about another building block
好的，再来一个构建块
from last time, which we'll now translate to C,
来自上次，现在我们将它翻译成 C 语言，
namely loops, things that happen again and again?
即循环，一遍又一遍重复的事情？
And these, too, are everywhere in code.
这些代码在代码中无处不在。
So in Scratch, here's how we might meow three times, super simple.
所以在 Scratch 中，我们可以这样发出三次喵喵声，超级简单。
In C, it's going to look a little weird.
在C语言中，这看起来有点奇怪。
But you will get used to this over time if you've never programmed before.
但如果你以前从未编程过，随着时间的推移，你会习惯的。
It looks like a mouthful, OK.
看起来很长，好吧。
But let's tease it apart line by line.
但让我们逐行地分析它。
And you'll see that you won't have that reaction frequently because it's all
你会发现你不会经常有这种反应，因为这一切
going to start to look very similar to itself.
将开始看起来非常相似。
But what are we doing here?
但我们在这里做什么呢？
In C, you don't have the luxury of these cute and fun puzzle pieces
在C语言中，你没有这些可爱有趣的拼图块的奢侈
that just do the work for you, repeat three times.
它们只是为你完成工作，重复三次。
In fact, in C and programming in general, sometimes
事实上，在C语言和一般编程中，有时
the work is on us to actually figure out, OK,
工作需要我们自己弄清楚，好吧，
how can I use functions, variables, conditionals, and loops
我如何使用函数、变量、条件语句和循环
and implement some idea like repetition, like looping?
来实现一些像重复、循环这样的想法？
And in C, here's how this might work.
在C语言中，这可能就是这样工作的。
How can I go about doing something like printing "meow" three times?
我如何才能做到像打印三次"喵"这样的事情？
Well, I know about variables now.
好吧，我现在了解变量了。
We're about to see loops.
我们马上就要看到循环了。
And I've seen how I can update variables by plussing or minusing
而且我看到了如何通过加或减来更新变量
some value to them.
它们的值。
Let's combine those ideas.
让我们把这些想法结合起来。
So first, I'm doing what with this highlighted line in English?
那么首先，用英语来说，我对这行高亮显示的代码做了什么？
If a friend cared to ask you, like, 'what is this line of code doing'
如果一个朋友想问你，比如，“这行代码在做什么”
later today, what would you say?
今天晚些时候，你会怎么说？
STUDENT: It's creating a variable called "counter" and setting it equal to 3.
学生：它创建了一个名为“计数器”的变量，并将其设置为 3。
DAVID MALAN: Good, it's creating a variable called "counter"
大卫·马兰：很好，它创建了一个名为“计数器”的变量
and setting it equal to 3.
并将其设置为 3。
I'll use slightly new jargon.
我将使用稍微不同的术语。
I'm defining a variable, would be the term of our "called counter"
我正在定义一个变量，用我们的术语来说就是“叫做计数器”
and setting it equal to 3.
并将其设置为 3。
So I'll use my hand to represent the counter.
所以我将用我的手来代表计数器。
And that's all a variable is.
这就是变量的全部。
It's like storage in some case that I'm representing information, using
在某种情况下，它就像存储，我正在使用它来表示信息，
my hand in this case or the computer's memory here.
在这种情况下，我的手或这里计算机的内存。
Now what happens when using a loop in C?
现在，在C语言中使用循环时会发生什么？
There's different types of loops, one of which is called a for loop-- oop--
有不同类型的循环，其中一种叫做for循环-- oop--
one of which is called a while loop-- spoiler.
其中一种叫做while循环--剧透。
A while loop works like this.
while循环的工作原理如下。
Inside of parentheses is a Boolean expression just like inside
在括号内是一个布尔表达式，就像在
of a conditional that asks a question.
条件语句中那样，它会问一个问题。
But this time the question is going to determine,
但这一次，这个问题将决定，
do you keep going through the loop again and again and again?
你是否要一遍又一遍地循环下去？
So it's not a one-time thing potentially.
所以它可能不是一次性的事情。
It is checked again and again and again to decide
它会一遍又一遍地检查，以决定
when it is time to stop looping, to stop cycling.
何时停止循环，停止循环。
All right, so it's asking this question first.
好的，所以它首先问这个问题。
Is counter greater than 0?
计数器是否大于 0？
OK, obviously the answer is true because I'm still holding up three fingers.
好吧，很明显答案是正确的，因为我仍然举着三个手指。
So what happens?
那么会发生什么呢？
C goes inside of the curly braces per the indentation
C 按照缩进规则进入花括号内
and executes printf of "meow," which prints out a "meow" on the screen.
并执行 `printf` 打印 "meow"，这将在屏幕上显示一个 "meow"。
The next line of code executes, which, recall,
接下来执行代码行，请记住，
is the same as just subtracting 1 from counter.
它等同于从计数器中减去 1。
So I think I take down one finger, so I'm left with two.
所以我想我应该放下一个手指，只剩下两个手指了。
And what happens next?
接下来会发生什么？
Well, this you just kind of have to memorize.
这个你只能记住它了。
Once you get to the end of the inside of a loop,
当你到达循环内部的结尾时，
you go back to the beginning of a loop here
你会回到这里循环的开头
and ask the same question, the same Boolean expression.
并问相同的问题，相同的布尔表达式。
So is 2 greater than 0?
那么 2 是否大于 0？
OK, obviously so.
好的，显然是的。
So you go into it, you print a "meow."
所以你进入它，打印一个 "meow"。
You go into it and decrement counter further by one.
你进入它并将计数器再减 1。
So now my hand is holding up one.
现在我的手举起了一根手指。
Now we wrap back around to the Boolean expression.
现在我们回到布尔表达式。
Is 1 greater than 0?
1 是否大于 0？
Obviously.
显然。
We print out a third "meow."
我们打印了第三个 "meow"。
We then decrement counter again, and my hand goes to zero.
然后我们再次减去计数器，我的手变为零。
We go back around once more.
我们再次回到开头。
Is 0 greater than 0?
0 是否大于 0？
No.
不。
And now the program just terminates.
现在程序就终止了。
Or if there were more code here, it would just
或者如果有更多代码，它将
jump outside of the curly braces and keep going lower on the screen.
跳出花括号，继续向下执行。
So that's all that's happening.
这就是发生的所有事情。
And so this is what MIT has the luxury of doing with pictures.
因此，MIT 有条件用图片来进行演示。
But at MIT, someone probably essentially wrote
但 MIT 的某人可能编写了
code that looks like this to give us the illusion, the abstraction of this.
看起来像这样的代码来给我们这种错觉，这种抽象。
So what we're learning today is how they invented these puzzle pieces
所以我们今天学到的是他们是如何用这些低级管道来发明这些拼图的，
by just using lower-level plumbing, if you will, like this here.
如果你愿意，就如同这里一样。
Yeah?
对吧？
STUDENT: What would happen if you created the variable "counter"
学生：如果你在花括号内创建了变量 "counter"
inside of the curly braces?
会发生什么？
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
大卫·马兰：一个很好的问题。
What would happen if you created the variable inside of the curly braces?
如果你在花括号内创建变量会发生什么？
Short answer, it just wouldn't work in C,
简而言之，它在 C 语言中无法工作，
because if I were to try with my slide here,
因为如果我用我的幻灯片在这里尝试，
for instance, to move this line of code here down inside of this, for instance,
例如，将这行代码移到下面，
now the very top line is trying to use counter before it even exists.
现在最上面的代码行试图使用 counter 变量，但它甚至还没有存在。
So C is very literal it.
所以 C 语言非常严格。
Reads top to bottom, left to right.
从上到下，从左到右读取。
And if it hasn't seen you define or create a variable yet,
如果它还没有看到你定义或创建变量，
you're going to get some scary error message on the screen instead.
你将得到一个吓人的错误信息。
All right, other questions on this here code?
好的，还有什么关于这段代码的问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right, so if we want to then maybe tighten this up a bit,
好的，如果我们想要稍微精简一下，
let me propose that we could do this instead.
我建议我们可以这样做。
So besides this version of the code, let me just
除了这个版本的代码，我只要
do something more canonical, more conventional.
做一些更规范，更常规的事情。
So you're totally fine with using a variable like counter.
所以你完全可以接受使用像 counter 这样的变量。
It's what Scratch uses by default. It's very verbose.
这是 Scratch 默认使用的。它非常冗长。
It does what it says.
它按字面意思执行。
Frankly, once you get comfy with programming,
坦白地说，一旦你习惯了编程，
like most typical programmers, whenever they
就像大多数典型的程序员一样，当他们
have a single integer in a program whose sole purpose in life is to count,
在一个程序中有一个唯一的整数，它的唯一作用就是计数，
they'll just use "i" for integer just like I used "c" for character.
他们会像我用 "c" 表示字符一样，用 "i" 表示整数。
When you have larger programs, you don't want
当你的程序更大时，你不想
to start using A and B and C and D and E and F and so forth for your variables
开始使用 A 和 B 和 C 和 D 和 E 和 F 等等作为你的变量
because nothing's going to make any sense.
因为什么都讲不通。
But when you're doing something super simple like counting with an integer,
但是当你做一些非常简单的事情，比如用整数计数时，
using a short-named variable is totally stylistically reasonable.
使用一个简短的变量名在风格上是完全合理的。
But I can tighten this up further, not just renaming counter to i.
但我可以进一步简化，不仅仅是将 counter 重命名为 i。
What else can I do, if you recall?
你还记得我可以做什么吗？
Over here?
这里？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
大卫·马兰：当然。
STUDENT: A for loop?
学生：一个 for 循环？
DAVID MALAN: Oh, OK, for loop.
大卫·马兰：哦，好的，for 循环。
Yes, that was my spoiler.
是的，那是我的剧透。
But while in a while loop, I can tighten this up slightly more.
但在 while 循环中，我可以稍微简化一下。
Over here?
这里？
STUDENT: Instead of i equals i minus 1.
学生：不是 i 等于 i 减 1。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, instead of i equals i minus 1,
大卫·马兰：是的，不是 i 等于 i 减 1，
I can actually tighten this up this way.
我可以这样进一步简化。
And we didn't see the minus before, but it's
之前我们没有看到减号，但是
the same idea-- i minus equals 1, or even more succinctly, i minus minus.
是同一个意思——i 减等于 1，或者更简洁地说，i 减减。
So when you get comfortable with programming, any of these approaches
所以当你习惯了编程，这些方法中的任何一个
are correct.
都是正确的。
This would be more conventional at this point.
在这一点上，这将更加传统。
So if you want to write code like most other people
所以如果你想像大多数人一样写代码
write code, adopt ultimately these kinds of conventions.
写代码，最终采用这些约定。
All right, so that just does the exact same thing, though.
好的，虽然它只是做完全相同的事情。
But let's now put this into practice.
但现在让我们把它付诸实践。
Let me go back to VS Code here.
让我回到这里的 VS Code。
Let me go ahead and clear my terminal and close agree.c from before.
让我先清除我的终端并关闭之前的 agree.c。
And let me go ahead and create a file called "meow."
让我创建一个名为 "meow" 的文件。
So code meow.c.
所以代码是 meow.c。
And let me do this the sort of wrong way.
让我用一种错误的方式来做。
Let me include stdio.h.
让我包含 stdio.h。
at the top, int main(void) thereafter.
在顶部，int main(void) 之后。
Inside of there, let me do printf "meow."
在里面，让我执行 printf "meow"。
And then you know what?
然后你知道吗？
I don't want to keep typing that.
我不想一直打这个。
Let me just go ahead and copy/paste two more times.
让我继续复制粘贴两次。
So I claim this is correct, make meow.
所以我声称这是正确的，make meow。
./meow, done.
./meow，完成。
I've got code that prints "meow" three times.
我有代码打印了三次 "meow"。
But this, again, should already rub you the wrong way.
但是这，再次强调，应该已经让你感觉不舒服了。
Why?
为什么？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: There's duplication.
学生：这里有重复。
DAVID MALAN: Because what?
大卫·马兰：因为什么？
STUDENT: There's duplication.
学生：这里有重复。
DAVID MALAN: Because I have duplication.
大卫·马兰：因为我这里有重复。
I mean, I literally copied and pasted it.
我是说，我实际上是复制粘贴的。
And that's kind of a good rule of thumb.
这算是个经验法则。
If you, in the future, start finding yourself copying and pasting code
如果你在将来发现自己开始复制粘贴代码
within the same program, you're probably doing something wrong.
在同一个程序里，你可能做错了什么。
There's a better way to design it even if it's correct.
即使它正确，也存在更好的设计方法。
So this is clearly a candidate for a loop.
所以这显然适合使用循环。
So let me go ahead and actually do that.
所以让我来实际做一下。
Let me just go ahead and remove all of this duplication.
让我把所有的重复部分去掉。
Let me give myself a variable called i, set it equal to 3.
我给自己一个名为 i 的变量，将其设置为 3。
Let me go ahead and give myself a while loop
我创建一个 while 循环
and check that i is greater than 0.
并检查 i 是否大于 0。
Inside of this loop, let me print out just "meow" once.
在这个循环内，我打印一次“meow”。
But I'll reuse that code again and again because here I'm
但我会重复使用这段代码，因为这里我
going to do i minus minus.
将执行 i 自减。
So that's the exact same code, the tight version of it that we saw a moment ago.
所以这是与之前看到的紧凑版本完全相同的代码。
Let me go ahead and "make meow" again, ./meow, and it still works.
让我再次运行“make meow”，./meow，它仍然有效。
Why is this version better?
为什么这个版本更好？
Because if you want the cat to meow five times, you change it in one place.
因为如果你想让猫叫五次，你只需要在一个地方修改。
If you want to make the cat a dog, you change the meow to a woof in one place,
如果你想把猫变成狗，你只需要在一个地方把“meow”改成“woof”，
albeit changing the file name eventually, but changing it
尽管最终要修改文件名，但修改
in one place, not worrying about changing it again and again and again.
只需要在一个地方修改，而不必担心要反复修改。
But there are other ways to do this.
但还有其他的方法可以实现。
For instance, let me propose that.
例如，我建议这样做。
And actually, let's see, let me propose that instead of just doing it this way,
实际上，让我们看看，我建议，不要只是以这种方式来做，
just to be clear--
为了更清晰——
yeah, let's go ahead and propose that instead of doing this,
是的，让我们建议，不要这样做，
we can actually count in different directions.
我们可以从不同的方向进行计数。
I'm kind of forcing this idea of starting at 3, going down to 0.
我有点强迫这种从 3 开始，一直减到 0 的想法。
But when normal humans in this room, if you ever count something,
但当房间里的人，如果你们曾经数过东西，
you probably do 1, 2, 3, and done.
你们可能就会 1、2、3，然后就完成了。
Like, that's how we would count in the real world.
就像，这就是我们在现实世界中计数的方式。
Well, we can do that, too, here code-wise.
嗯，我们也可以在代码里这样做。
We could initialize i to 1.
我们可以将 i 初始化为 1。
We could check that i is less than or equal to 3.
我们可以检查 i 是否小于或等于 3。
And we've not seen this syntax before, but there's
我们之前还没有见过这种语法，但是这里
no easy way on a typical keyboard to type a less than or equal sign
没有简单的方法可以在标准键盘上输入小于或等于符号
like in a math book.
就像数学书中的那样。
So we use two characters, a less-than sign and then an equal sign
所以我们使用两个字符，一个小于号，然后是一个等于号
back to back.
并排在一起。
And that means less than or equal to.
这意味着小于或等于。
And this is the same idea so long as I plus plus i inside of it
只要我在循环中将 i 加加，这个想法就一样
because that'll start at 1, then 2, but it won't stop then.
因为这会从 1 开始，然后是 2，但不会在 2 处停止。
It will go up to until i is equal to 3.
它会一直循环直到 i 等于 3。
Once i becomes 4, then that Boolean expression isn't going to be true.
一旦 i 变成 4，那么那个布尔表达式将不再为真。
So it stops after three "meow"s total.
所以它会在总共三次 "喵" 之后停止。
But there's another way, too, and this is probably
但是还有另一种方法，这可能是
the most conventional and the way you should do it
最传统的，也是你应该使用的方法
even though it's just as correct.
即使它同样正确。
In CS, if you've seen already last week, we almost always start counting from 0.
在 CS 中，如果你上周已经见过，我们几乎总是从 0 开始计数。
Why?
为什么？
Just because, so we're not wasting a pattern of bits.
仅仅因为这样，所以我们不会浪费一组比特位。
So generally when you start writing code that counts,
所以一般来说，当你开始编写计数代码时，
you should, quote, unquote, "almost always" start at 0,
你应该，引用一下，"几乎总是"从 0 开始，
count up to but not through the total you
计数到但不包括你所关注的总计，
care about so you don't get one extra by accident.
这样你就不会意外地多加一个。
And so this would be the most conventional way
所以这将是我们刚刚描述的最传统的方式
of doing what we just described.
去做我们刚刚描述的事情。
But they're all correct.
但它们都是正确的。
You can make an argument that all of them are equally good.
你可以争辩说，它们都同样好。
This is what most people, quote, unquote, "would do."
这是大多数人，引用一下，"会做的事情"。
OK, other questions on this here syntax or logic?
好的，关于这个语法或逻辑还有其他问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right, how about--
好的，那我们呢--
we got some cookies on the horizon.
我们已经有一些饼干在路上了。
But before we get there, let's meow a few more times, if we may.
但我们还没到那里之前，我们再喵几声，如果可以的话。
So how about doing a little bit differently versus the while loop.
那么，我们来尝试一下与 while 循环略微不同的方式。
And I think we heard it over here.
我想我们从这里听到了。
Turns out there's another type of loop altogether.
事实证明，还有另一种类型的循环。
So this one here.
所以，这个循环。
And this one, if you can believe it, is probably even more conventional
而这个，如果你能相信的话，可能比另一个方法更传统
than the other way.
。
And this is going to be thematic in programming.
这在编程中将是主题性的。
There's rarely one way, one right way to do things.
很少有一条正确的方式去做事情。
You're going to have bunches of different tools in your toolkit.
你的工具箱里会有很多不同的工具。
And your code might look different from someone else's because each of you
你的代码可能与其他人的代码看起来不同，因为你们每个人
tends to reach for a different tool in that toolkit.
倾向于从那个工具箱中选择不同的工具。
And here's another tool--
还有一个工具--
and as you proposed earlier--
就像你之前提议的那样--
a for loop.
一个 for 循环。
A for loop is just another way of achieving the exact same idea
一个 for 循环只是另一种实现完全相同想法的方式
using slightly different syntax.
使用稍微不同的语法。
And it's appealing, frankly in general, because it's a little more succinct.
坦率地说，它在一般情况下更吸引人，因为它更简洁。
It just saves some keystrokes even though you have to memorize
它只是节省了一些按键，即使你必须记住
the order in which it works.
它的工作顺序。
This code is identical to this code here functionally.
这段代码在功能上与这边的代码相同。
But aesthetically, of course, it looks different.
但在美学上，当然，它看起来不同。
How does it work?
它是如何工作的？
In a for loop, notice that in the parentheses
在一个 for 循环中，注意在括号中
is not a single simple Boolean expression.
不是一个简单的布尔表达式。
There are three things.
有三个部分。
One, before a semicolon, is a place to initialize a variable
第一部分，在分号之前，是初始化变量的地方
to do your counting typically.
通常用于计数。
Second is the Boolean expression.
第二个是布尔表达式。
So it's still there.
所以它还在那里。
It's just surrounded on the left and the right by two other things.
它只是被左右两边的其他两件事包围着。
Lastly is the update.
最后是更新。
What do you want to do at the end of every loop through this block of code?
在每次循环遍历这段代码块的最后，你想做什么？
So you can probably imagine where we're going with this.
所以你可能已经想到我们要往哪里走了。
How does this work?
这是如何工作的？
The first thing that happens is that a variable
首先发生的事情是，一个变量
called i is defined and initialized to the value of 0.
名为i被定义并初始化为0的值。
That happens once and only once.
这只会发生一次。
Then we check the condition.
然后我们检查条件。
Is 0 less than 3?
0是否小于3？
Obviously yes.
显然是的。
So now we don't do the plus plus yet.
所以现在我们还没有做加加操作。
We go into the loop.
我们进入循环。
And this is where the for loop's a little confusing at first.
这就是for循环一开始让人感到有点困惑的地方。
We print out "meow."
我们打印出"喵"。
Then what happens?
然后发生了什么？
There's no more lines.
没有更多行。
So we go back to the for loop, and we increment i at that point.
所以我们回到for循环，并在那一刻递增i。
So now i is 1.
所以现在i是1。
Then we check the condition. i is less than 3?
然后我们检查条件。i是否小于3？
Yes, because 1 is less than 3.
是的，因为1小于3。
We go back into the loop and print "meow."
我们回到循环并打印"喵"。
Now we go back to the plus plus, so i is now 2.
现在我们回到加加操作，所以i现在是2。
We check the condition.
我们检查条件。
2 is less than 3 obviously.
2显然小于3。
So we go back into the loop and print "meow."
所以我们回到循环并打印"喵"。
Then we do the increment. i is now 3.
然后我们进行递增。i现在是3。
Is 3 less than 3?
3是否小于3？
No, so we exit the loop, and we're done, or we keep
不，所以我们退出循环，我们完成了，或者我们继续
going down here if there's more code.
向下走，如果有更多代码。
But how many times did I say "meow?"
但我说了多少次"喵"？
1, 2, 3 total, when my hand was 0, 1, and 2.
一共1, 2, 3次，当我的手是0, 1, 2的时候。
Questions on this alternative syntax?
关于这种替代语法，有什么问题吗？
It takes some getting used to, but most people
它需要一些时间去习惯，但大多数人
would write loops using a for loop, I would say.
会使用for循环编写循环，我会说。
STUDENT: Could you now in the curly braces, use just one line of code?
学生：现在你能在花括号中只用一行代码吗？
DAVID MALAN: Yes.
大卫·马兰：是的。
If you really want to be cool and save syntax,
如果你真的想酷一点，节省语法，
yes, it is correct and common to eliminate the curly braces if you only
是的，如果你只有一行代码，去掉花括号是正确且常见的。
have one line of code therein.
其中有一行代码。
We in class will always put the curly braces there
我们在课堂上会始终在那里放置花括号
because this is the kind of thing where, if you get forgetful, you go in later
因为这是那种，如果你健忘，之后再进去
and add a second line.
添加第二行。
Like, darn it, like you forgot the curly braces,
就像，该死，就像你忘记了花括号，
things will not work as expected.
事情将不会按预期进行。
So in general, use the curly braces, but you do not have to strictly.
所以一般来说，使用花括号，但你并不一定要严格使用。
Other questions on 6?
关于6还有什么其他问题吗？
Yes?
是的？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Can be used without, what?
大卫·马兰：可以不用什么？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Oh, could you do it without the condition?
大卫·马兰：哦，你可以不用条件吗？
Yes, there are very fancy things you can do that we won't focus on today.
是的，你可以做很多很花哨的事情，但我们今天不会重点关注。
But yes, if you want to get rid of the condition, you could get rid of this
但是，是的，如果你想摆脱条件，你可以摆脱这个
here.
这里。
And that would actually make the loop go forever,
这实际上会导致循环永远运行，
which may be a good thing if it's like a clock
如果它像一个时钟一样，这可能是一件好事，
that you want to tick forever, but often not a good thing in code.
你希望它永远滴答作响，但通常在代码中不是一件好事。
Good question, though.
不过，好问题。
All right, so beyond that, let's just go ahead and put this into context.
好吧，除此之外，让我们继续把它放在上下文中。
Just in case it helps you to think about this,
以防它有助于你思考这个问题，
this is just another flow chart, if you're
这只是另一个流程图，如果你
more of a visual thinker, that represents
更喜欢视觉思考，它代表着
what it is this loop is now doing.
这个循环现在正在做什么。
Previously, all of our arrows went from top to bottom and stopped.
之前，我们所有的箭头都是从上到下，然后停止。
But now there's an arrow going back, up, and around
但现在有一个箭头向后、向上、环绕
because of this loop, this cycle.
因为这个循环，这个周期。
So when we start this program, we set i equal to 0.
所以当我们启动这个程序时，我们将 i 设置为 0。
We then check, is i less than 3?
然后我们检查，i 是否小于 3？
Obviously it is, so we print "meow."
显然是的，所以我们打印 "meow"。
We increment i, and then we go back to that same condition.
我们增加 i，然后返回到相同的条件。
We check the condition.
我们检查条件。
We print "meow."
我们打印 "meow"。
i plus plus, go back, go back.
i 加加，返回，返回。
Now, if i equals 3, 3 is not less than 3, so the answer is false.
现在，如果 i 等于 3，3 不小于 3，所以答案是 false。
And we stop.
然后我们停止。
So again, it's just another way of thinking
所以，再次强调，这只是另一种思考方式
about how the code in Scratch, how the code in C
关于 Scratch 中的代码，C 中的代码
might alternatively work in each of these contexts.
可能会在这两种情况下交替使用。
But there's this one other puzzle piece in Scratch,
但是 Scratch 中还有另一个拼图块，
recall, that's not the repeat block, which
回想一下，那不是 repeat 块，它
is for finite numbers of repetitions, but forever.
用于有限次数的重复，但永远是。
And in C, there is a way to do this, but it's a little weird looking.
在 C 中，有一种方法可以做到这一点，但这看起来有点奇怪。
There's no forever keyword.
没有 forever 关键字。
But you can use the while loop or, as you inferred,
但是，你可以使用 while 循环，或者像你推断的那样，
you can actually use the for loop without a condition in the middle.
你实际上可以使用 for 循环，中间没有条件。
So here, I can actually say this.
所以这里，我可以这样说。
If I want to do something forever, I want
如果我想永远做某事，我想
to make sure that the answer to my question, the Boolean expression,
确保我的问题的答案，布尔表达式，
is always true, always true, always true,
始终为真，始终为真，始终为真，
the easiest way to achieve that goal is just literally write "true" there
实现这个目标最简单的方法就是直接在那里写 "true"
because true is true no matter what.
因为 true 无论如何都是真的。
And it's a trick for making the loop forever
这是一个让循环永远运行的小技巧，
go around and around, as you might if you
一遍又一遍地循环，就像你可能想要做的那样，
want the cat to live forever and meow incessantly
让猫永远活着，不停地喵喵叫，
or if it is a clock that you want to tick forever or the like.
或者如果你想要一个永远滴答作响的时钟之类的。
So here, for instance, is how we might have a cat meow endlessly,
例如，这里是如何让猫不停地喵喵叫，
using this so-called for loop instead.
而是使用这种所谓的for循环。
But recall that in Scratch, we also had this ability
但回想一下，在Scratch中，我们也有这种能力
to create some of our own puzzle pieces.
创建我们自己的积木块。
And this, too, is something that we're going to be able to do here in C.
这也是我们将在C语言中可以做到的事情。
And let me propose that we do exactly that
我建议我们正是这样做
by introducing the C analog of this.
通过引入C语言的类似物。
So here, for instance, is, in Scratch, our definition
例如，这里是在Scratch中，我们的定义
of a function called meow whose sole purpose in life
一个名为“喵”的函数，它的唯一生命目标
was to just play the sound "meow" until it's done.
就是播放“喵”的声音，直到完成。
This is going to look a little weird at first.
乍一看，这会有点奇怪。
But you'll notice some similarities with main.
但你会注意到它与main函数有一些相似之处。
So recall this thing I keep typing with main, int main(void), int main(void).
所以回想一下我一直用main键入的这个东西，int main(void)，int main(void)。
That's just the "when green flag clicked" equivalent for today.
这只是今天“当绿旗点击时”的等效项。
But if you want to create your own puzzle piece or your own function in C,
但是如果你想在C语言中创建自己的积木块或自己的函数，
you, for now, literally do this.
现在，你就照着做就行了。
You say, void, the name of the function you want to create, and then
你说，void，你要创建的函数名，然后
void in parentheses.
括号里的void。
And technically what this means is that this function has no return value.
从技术上讲，这意味着这个函数没有返回值。
It doesn't hand you anything back like get_string or get_int.
它不会像get_string或get_int那样给你返回任何东西。
And the "void" in parentheses means it takes no inputs.
括号里的“void”表示它不接受任何输入。
It only meows.
它只会喵。
You don't have to tell it how to meow.
你不需要告诉它如何喵。
It's just going to meow.
它只会喵。
So no arguments, so to speak.
所以说，没有参数。
This literally just prints out "meow."
它实际上只是打印出“喵”。
But what this does for me is it abstracts away the idea of meowing.
但它对我来说，抽象掉了喵的思想。
I don't need to know how to use printf or that you're
我不需要知道如何使用printf，或者说你是否正在
using printf to make the cat meow.
使用printf让猫叫。
I now have a function in life called meow because in Scratch, recall,
我现在在生活中有一个名为“喵”的函数，因为回想一下，在Scratch中，
I used it like this.
我是这样使用的。
When the green flag is clicked, I could repeat three times this new custom
当绿旗被点击时，我可以重复三次这个新的自定义
puzzle piece.
积木块。
But in C, I could now do this.
但在C语言中，我现在可以这样做。
In my main program, I can use a for loop just like we saw a moment ago,
在我的主程序中，我可以使用一个for循环，就像我们刚才看到的那样，
copy/pasted from earlier.
从之前复制粘贴过来的。
But now I can call my own C function called meow.
但现在我可以调用我自己的C语言函数，名为“喵”。
And let me go ahead now and do this.
现在，让我继续这样做。
If I go over to my C code here, back in VS Code, let me go ahead
如果我回到这里的C代码，回到VS Code，让我继续
and delete everything inside main.
删除main函数内部的所有内容。
Let me go ahead and do for int i equals 0, i is less than 3, i++.
让我继续这样做，对于int i等于0，i小于3，i++。
Inside of my curly braces, let me go ahead and say "meow."
在我的花括号内，让我继续说“喵”。
But I now need this meow function to exist because if I
但我现在需要这个“喵”函数存在，因为如果我
do "make meow" again, notice error.
再次执行“make meow”，注意错误。
"Implicit declaration of function meow is invalid in C99"--
“函数“喵”的隐式声明在C99中无效”--
the 1999 version of C. What does that mean?
C语言的1999版本。这是什么意思？
Well, it doesn't know what the meow function is.
好吧，它不知道“喵”函数是什么。
And the meow function is not in CS50.h.
“喵”函数不在CS50.h中。
It's not in stdio.h.
它也不在stdio.h中。
I have to create it.
我必须创建它。
So let me type out or really copy/paste what I had on the screen a moment ago--
所以，让我打出来，或者直接复制粘贴我之前在屏幕上显示的内容。
"void meow meow"--
“空喵喵”
[CHUCKLES] "void meow(void)" printf, quote, unquote, "meow," close quote,
[笑声] “空喵（空）”  printf，引号，引号， “喵，”  引号，
semicolon.
分号。
But here, too, let me scooch this down a bit
但是这里，我也要稍微向下移动一下
so you can see all the code at once.
这样你就可以一次性看到所有的代码了。
Let me now do make meow.
现在让我来做 make 喵。
And unfortunately, I still have an error.
不幸的是，我仍然有一个错误。
If I scroll up, still on line 7 of meow.c,
如果我向上滚动，仍然在 meow.c 的第 7 行，
my compiler thinks that meow is invalid, that it does not exist.
我的编译器认为 meow 是无效的，它不存在。
This too is a common mistake.
这也是一个常见的错误。
And as simple as this code might be in spirit, where did I screw up?
尽管这段代码在精神上可能很简单，但我究竟错在哪里了？
Yeah, in the middle.
没错，在中间。
STUDENT: You need to define the function like above where you use it.
学生：你需要像上面那样在使用函数的地方定义它。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I need to define the function before I use it.
大卫·马兰：没错，我需要在使用函数之前定义它。
So again, C is going to take you literally.
所以，再一次，C 会严格地按照你的字面意思来执行。
If you try to call meow on line 7, you better not define it on line 11.
如果你尝试在第 7 行调用 meow，你最好不要在第 11 行定义它。
You better define it higher up.
你最好在上面定义它。
So the simplest fix is going to be just to do this.
所以最简单的解决方法就是这样做。
Let me clear my terminal.
让我清除我的终端。
Let me highlight and just delete the meow function.
让我突出显示并删除 meow 函数。
And let me just paste it up here.
然后我把它粘贴到这里。
And this will actually solve the problem.
这样就能解决问题了。
Make meow now works.
现在 make 喵可以运行了。
And if I do ./meow, that, too, works.
如果我运行 ./meow，它也能运行。
But this isn't really the best solution because if your solution is constantly,
但这不是最好的解决方案，因为如果你的解决方案总是
oh, well, just put it up there, put it up there, put it up there,
哦，好吧，把它放在那里，把它放在那里，把它放在那里，
I bet we could contrive a situation where
我敢肯定我们可以设计一种情况，
one function needs to be above the other,
一个函数需要在另一个函数之上，
but it needs to be above the other.
但它必须在另一个函数之上。
And that's just not going to work in general.
通常情况下，这是行不通的。
And more importantly, it just pushes main lower and lower and lower
更重要的是，它会不断地将 main 向下移动
in your file.
在你的文件中。
But the whole point of your main function
但是你的 main 函数的重点是
is like, that's the entry point.
它就像一个入口点。
That is what happens when the green flag is clicked.
它就像绿色的旗帜被点击时发生的事情。
And so just in terms of user conventions, it's just useful for main
所以，从用户的角度来看，让 main 始终位于文件的顶部非常有用，因为这样你就能快速找到它。
to always be at the top of a file because then you can find it fast.
你的朋友，你的 TA 可以快速找到它，如果它位于文件的顶部。
Your friends can, your TFs can find it quickly if it's at the top.
So the other solution here would be to leave meow at the bottom
所以另一个解决方法是将 meow 放在底部
and leave main at the top.
并将 main 放在顶部。
But this is the only time, if I may, that copy/paste is OK.
但是，如果可以的话，这将是唯一一次可以使用复制粘贴的地方。
What I've highlighted here in line 11 is what's called the function's prototype.
我在第 11 行突出显示的内容被称为函数原型。
It is enough information to give you the return type, the name of the function,
它包含了足够的信息，可以告诉你函数的返回类型、函数名称
and the return value--
以及返回值
and any arguments.
以及任何参数。
And so if you just copy/paste that one line and end it with a semicolon
所以，如果你只复制粘贴这一行并以分号结尾
up there, that's enough of a hint to the compiler
就在上面，这对编译器来说已经足够提示了
that, OK, it doesn't exist yet, but it will.
好的，它现在还不存在，但它会存在的。
And it will look like that.
它看起来会是这样的。
That's the only time it's OK to copy/paste
这是唯一一次可以进行复制粘贴的时候
the very first line of a function you've written
你写过的函数的第一行
to the top of the file with a semicolon so
到文件的顶部，并在后面添加一个分号，这样
that you can make the compiler happy.
就可以让编译器开心了。
So if I do make meow now, still no errors. ./meow, and it now works.
所以如果我现在做 make meow，仍然没有错误。./meow，现在它就可以工作了。
But let me add one final feature, coming back to Scratch here.
但让我在这里回到 Scratch，添加最后一个功能。
And then it's time for a snack.
然后该吃点心了。
So here, recall, was sort of the last fancy thing we did in Scratch, where
所以，你还记得吗？这是我们在 Scratch 中做的最后一个比较复杂的事情，就是
we created not only our own custom puzzle piece,
我们不仅创建了自己的自定义拼图块，
but it took an input so that we didn't need to keep using the loop ourself.
而且它还可以接收输入，这样我们就不用一直使用循环了。
We could just let the meow function be told how many times
我们只需要告诉 meow 函数，
do you want the cat to meow.
你想让猫叫几声。
So in C, we don't have to make that many changes except this.
所以在 C 语言中，除了这里以外，我们不需要做太多更改。
We change the prototype to take an argument inside of parentheses.
我们将原型更改为在括号中接收一个参数。
And this is the syntax for that.
这就是它的语法。
If you want your own function in C to take one or more arguments,
如果你想让你的 C 语言函数接收一个或多个参数，
you give the arguments a name, n, or whatever you want to call it.
你需要给参数起一个名字，比如 n，或者你想要叫什么都行。
But you have to tell C what the type of that input is.
但是你必须告诉 C，这个输入的类型是什么。
So it's an int n.
所以它是一个 int 类型的 n。
So it knows it's a number.
这样它就知道这是一个数字。
And then you can just use n in your program.
然后你就可以在你的程序中使用 n 了。
So instead of hard coding, typing manually the number 3,
所以，与其硬编码，手动输入数字 3，
I'm just using n here.
我在这里使用的是 n。
So this is equivalent to what I did with Scratch, by just dragging and dropping
所以这相当于我在 Scratch 中，通过拖放
the n variable there.
n 变量来实现的。
And then "meow" will get printed that many times.
然后 "meow" 会被打印那么多次。
If I want to then use this-- notice, this is the last version of the cat
如果我想使用它，注意，这是我们上周做的猫的最后一个版本，
that we did last week-- you just say "meow" this many times.
你只需要说 "meow" 那么多遍。
So in C, this is where now the code gets very succinct
所以在 C 语言中，这里就是代码变得非常简洁的地方
because all the main part of the program does is meow three times.
因为程序的主要部分就是让猫叫三声。
So this, again, is an abstraction.
所以这又是一个抽象。
I don't need to know, care, or remember how meow is implemented.
我不需要知道、关心或记住 meow 是如何实现的。
I just need to know what its return value, its name, and any arguments
我只需要知道它的返回值、它的名字，以及它的任何参数
thereto are.
是什么。
So if I make this change, I think we can get the cat
所以如果我做这个更改，我认为我们可以让猫
to meow any number of times.
叫任意多次。
Let me go back over to my C code here.
让我回到我的 C 代码这里。
Let me go back into the file and change "void" here to be int n,
让我回到文件，将这里的 "void" 更改为 int n，
where n just means number.
其中 n 代表数字。
I could use i, but n tends to be a quantity instead of a counter.
我也可以使用 i，但 n 往往表示一个数量，而不是一个计数器。
I then, inside of this function, am going to do a for loop--
然后，在这个函数内部，我将执行一个 for 循环，
for int i get 0; i less than n--
for int i 为 0；i 小于 n，
instead of 3-- i++.
而不是 3，i++。
And then inside of here, I'll paste that "meow" again.
然后在这里，我将再次粘贴 "meow"。
I need to change my prototype to be identical, so another copy/paste,
我需要将我的原型更改为相同的，所以再复制粘贴一次，
or just manually edit it.
或者手动编辑它。
But now notice what's cool about main, is
但现在注意一下main的妙处在于
that now I can meow maybe three times.
现在我可以喵叫三次。
Make meow, Enter, ./meow.
输入 meow，回车， ./meow。
OK, or if I really want to be cool, I can change this to 30,000 times.
好吧，如果我真想酷炫一下，可以把这改成30000次。
Go back here, make meow.
回到这里，输入 meow。
Increase the size of my terminal window for a dramatic pre-break flourish.
为了一个戏剧性的暂停效果，扩大一下我的终端窗口。
And there are 30-- that was a fast cat.
然后就有30——那只猫真快。
There are 30,000 meows.
这里有30000声喵叫。
I think now let's go ahead and take-- that's a lot-- a 10-minute break.
我觉得现在可以休息一下——这太长了——休息十分钟。
We'll see you in 10.
十分钟后再见。
Cookies are now served outside.
现在外面有饼干。
All right, so we are back.
好了，我们回来了。
And I realize this has been a lot so far, right?
我意识到到目前为止已经讲了很多东西了，对吧？
So there's a lot of new syntax.
所以有很多新的语法。
There's a lot of translation of Scratch over to C.
有很多从Scratch到C语言的转换。
But among the goals of having spent last week in Scratch
但是我们上周花时间学习Scratch的目标之一
and having spent problems at 0 in Scratch is that none of today's ideas
以及在Scratch中花费大量时间解决问题，就是为了让今天的这些想法
are really all that new.
并不真正算得上是新的东西。
It's just a lot of syntax that will get more comfortable and more
只是有很多语法，随着时间的推移，你就会越来越熟悉，越来越
in your muscle memory as time passes.
刻在你的肌肉记忆里。
Up until now, though, we've focused largely on these side effects,
不过，到目前为止，我们主要关注的是这些副作用，
like things happening on the screen.
比如屏幕上发生的事情。
And that was akin to the speech bubble appearing in the world of Scratch.
这就像在Scratch的世界里，出现了一个对话框。
But let's focus for just a bit-- before we then explore things
但我们先集中精力——在我们探索一些
we can't do very well in code-- on return
在代码中无法很好地完成的事情——关于返回值
values instead in C. We've seen them already.
在C语言中。我们已经见过它们了。
Like, get_string returns a value.
比如，get_string 函数会返回一个值。
Get_int returns a value, a string and an int respectively.
Get_int 函数会返回一个值，分别是字符串和整数。
But what if we want to make our own functions that don't just
但如果我们想创建自己的函数，它们不仅仅
meow and visually have this side effect of meowing on the screen
喵叫，并在视觉上产生在屏幕上喵叫的副作用
but actually hand us back some value?
而是真正地给我们返回一些值呢？
Well, I bet we can do this in C, as well.
嗯，我敢肯定我们也能在C语言中做到这一点。
Well, let me propose that to go that route--
嗯，我建议我们走这条路——
let me go back to VS Code here.
让我回到这里的VS Code。
And let's make our very simple calculator
让我们制作一个非常简单的计算器
that just adds some numbers together.
它只把一些数字加起来。
But the same calculator, we'll soon see, is
但我们很快就会发现，同样的计算器
going to get us into trouble if you don't understand what the computer is
如果不懂得计算机在
doing underneath the hood.
幕后做的事情，就会让我们陷入困境。
Let me go ahead and run code of, say, calculator.c.
让我运行一下代码，比如calculator.c。
And in here, let me go ahead and give myself
这里，让我给自己
access to the CS50 library with CS50.h, the stdio.h library with stdio.h,
访问 CS50 库，使用 CS50.h，访问 stdio.h 库，使用 stdio.h，
int main(void), which, again, we'll just take for granted today that we have
int main(void)，再次强调，我们今天就假设我们拥有它
to include atop any of these programs.
来包含在这些程序的顶部。
And let's just add two numbers together-- super simple calculator.
然后，我们把两个数字加起来——超级简单的计算器。
So it gives me a variable called x.
所以它给我一个叫做 x 的变量。
Assign it the return value of get_int.
给它赋值为 get_int 函数的返回值。
And I'll ask the user to give us x.
然后我让用户输入 x。
Give me another variable called y.
给我一个叫做 y 的变量。
Assign it the return value of get_int again.
再次为它赋值为 get_int 函数的返回值。
But this time, ask the user for y.
但这次，要向用户询问 y 的值。
And then, lastly, let's just go ahead and print out the value of x plus y.
最后，让我们直接打印出 x 加 y 的值。
But I don't think I can get away with something
但我认为我不能就这样做
like this, x plus y semicolon, because if I
像这样，x 加 y，分号，因为如果我
do this, based on what we've seen before,
这样做，根据我们之前看到的，
what's actually going to get printed out?
实际上会打印出什么？
STUDENT: x plus y.
学生：x 加 y。
DAVID MALAN: Right, literally like x plus y.
大卫·马兰：没错，就是字面意思 x 加 y。
So I think this is where I need the F in "printf" for formatting.
所以，我认为这就是我需要在 “printf” 中使用 F 进行格式化的原因。
What I think I really want to do is print out the value of some placeholder
我认为我真正想做的是打印一些占位符的值
because, what do I want to substitute for percent i
因为，我想用百分号 i 代替什么
maybe as a second argument to printf intuitively?
也许作为 printf 的第二个参数更直观？
Maybe just x plus y.
也许就是 x 加 y。
So indeed, I can get away with this because it turns out in C,
因此，我确实可以这样做，因为事实证明在 C 语言中，
there's a bunch of arithmetic operators, all of the ones that you might expect,
有很多算术运算符，所有你可能期望的运算符，
including addition, subtraction, multiplication, division,
包括加法、减法、乘法、除法，
and even this one, the so-called modulo operator,
甚至还有这个，所谓的模运算符，
which generally gives us the ability to calculate a remainder when
它通常使我们能够计算出当
you divide one number by another.
你用一个数除另一个数时得到的余数。
But I'll keep it simple with addition.
但我会用加法来保持简单。
And indeed, with printf, if I want to print out the value of x plus y,
实际上，如果我想使用 printf 打印出 x 加 y 的值，
I can do that.
我可以做到。
But I have to tell printf what kind of value to expect, an integer,
但我必须告诉 printf 预期得到什么样的值，一个整数，
thus the percent i instead of %s for string.
因此，使用百分号 i 而不是字符串的百分号 s。
And I think this should do the job.
我认为这应该可以完成工作。
So let me go back to my terminal.
所以，让我回到我的终端。
Make calculator, Enter.
创建 calculator，回车。
All is well so far. ./calculator, and let's keep it simple--
目前一切顺利。 ./calculator，让我们保持简单--
1 for x, 2 for y.
x 为 1，y 为 2。
And indeed, I get 3 as the output.
实际上，我得到了 3 作为输出。
It's not very dynamic.
它不是很有动态性。
It can't do a subtraction or multiplication or much more.
它不能做减法、乘法或更多。
But it does at least do those kinds of calculations.
但它至少可以进行这些类型的计算。
But let me propose now that we maybe make a reusable addition
但现在我建议我们也许可以创建一个可重复使用的加法
function, right, because addition is something I'm going to do a lot.
函数，对吧，因为加法是我要经常做的事情。
And maybe it should be abstracted away with a function
也许应该使用一个函数将它抽象出来
just like meowing was abstracted away a moment ago.
就像刚才将喵喵叫抽象出来一样。
So let me go ahead and instead of doing this,
所以，让我继续，而不是这样做，
let me go ahead and give myself a function called add,
让我继续给自己一个叫做 add 的函数，
but instead of last time where I had a meow function,
但与上次我有一个 meow 函数不同，
I'm obviously going to call this "add" instead.
我显然会把它叫做 "add"。
And instead of last time, taking in no arguments,
并且与上次不同，这次不接受任何参数，
I think I want add to work a little differently.
我认为我想让 add 有点不同。
I don't want add necessarily to take an argument yet,
我现在并不想让 add 接受任何参数，
but I do want add to return some type of value.
但我想让 add 返回某种类型的值。
And just intuitively, what type of value should an addition function return?
直觉上，加法函数应该返回什么类型的值？
STUDENT: An integer.
学生：一个整数。
DAVID MALAN: An integer, so an int.
大卫·马兰：一个整数，所以是 int 类型。
So I'm going to change void, which means the absence of a return value--
所以我将要改变 void，它意味着没有返回值 -
nothing's coming back-- to literally "int."
什么都没有返回 - 变成“int”类型。
But I'm not going to change the thing inside parentheses yet.
但现在我不会改变括号里面的内容。
I'm going to go ahead and copy my prototype up here.
我将把我的原型复制到这里。
And I'm going to make this change, return x plus y.
然后我会进行这个修改，返回 x 加 y。
And then here, instead of printing out x plus y, let's go ahead and do this.
然后在这里，而不是打印出 x 加 y，我们来做这个。
Let me give myself a third variable just for now.
让我现在给自己一个第三个变量。
z equals the return value of this brand-new
z 等于这个全新的
add function that's going to add x plus y for me.
add 函数的返回值，它会帮我计算 x 加 y。
And then let me print out the value of z.
然后让我打印出 z 的值。
Instead of x plus y, I'm outsourcing now to this add function
现在我将 x 加 y 的计算外包给这个 add 函数
so it will do the addition of x plus y.
这样它就可以完成 x 加 y 的运算。
So similar in spirit to meowing, but the return values, I claim,
所以和喵喵叫类似，但我认为返回值
are about to create an issue.
即将导致问题。
So let me make calculator again.
所以让我重新构建计算器。
And there's definitely some errors.
并且肯定存在一些错误。
So here we have, "use of undeclared identifier x."
所以这里我们看到，“使用未声明的标识符 x”。
And that's on line 17.
它在第 17 行。
So that's pretty far down in the file.
所以这在文件中的位置比较靠下。
So specifically, my compiler does not like my use of x on line 17.
具体来说，我的编译器不喜欢我在第 17 行使用 x。
But wait a minute, x is clearly defined on line 8.
等等，x 在第 8 行明显被定义了。
What intuitively might explain this issue
即使你以前从未编程过，什么直觉可以解释这个问题
even if you've never programmed before?
呢？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: Well, because x and y are defined in the main function, not
学生：嗯，因为 x 和 y 定义在 main 函数中，而不是
the add function.
add 函数中。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, because x and y are defined in the main function,
大卫·马兰：没错，因为 x 和 y 定义在 main 函数中，
not in the add function.
而不是 add 函数中。
So the term of art here that we're about to introduce
所以我们即将介绍的技术术语
is something called "scope."
叫做“作用域”。
So "scope" just refers to the context in which variables exist--
所以“作用域”指的是变量存在的上下文 -
the context in which variables exist.
变量存在的上下文。
So by that, I mean this.
我的意思是，
On line 8, I've declared x.
在第 8 行，我声明了 x。
On line y, I've declared--
在第 y 行，我声明了 -
[CHUCKLES] on line 9, I've declared y.
[笑声] 在第 9 行，我声明了 y。
But the catch is-- and here's where the curly braces are helpful--
但是关键是 - 这里花括号就很重要 -
those variables only exist in the context of the outer curly braces
这些变量只存在于最靠近它们的外部花括号的上下文中
that are nearest to them, like this.
就像这样。
So I can use x and y on lines 10, 11, 12, and even up to 13,
所以我在第 10 行、第 11 行、第 12 行，甚至第 13 行都可以使用 x 和 y，
but not thereafter.
但之后就不行了。
So I certainly can't use x down here on line 7.
所以，我肯定不能在第 7 行使用 x。
But this is a problem, because if add's purpose in life is to add x and y
但这是个问题，因为如果 add 函数存在的意义是计算 x 加 y
but add can't access x plus y, well, we have an issue of scope.
但 add 函数无法访问 x 加 y，那么我们就有作用域的问题。
Like, x and y are not in scope for this add function.
也就是说，x 和 y 不在 add 函数的作用域内。
But that's OK because remember that every function we've seen thus far
但这没关系，因为我们记得，到目前为止，我们看到的所有函数
can have maybe a return value or a side effect,
都可以有一个返回值或者副作用，
but it can also take 0 or one or two or more inputs, known as arguments.
但它也可以接受 0 个、1 个、2 个或更多个输入，称为参数。
So what if I instead do this?
那如果我改为这样做呢？
Let me clear my terminal window.
让我清理一下我的终端窗口。
And let me update add to not take nothing
让我更新 add 函数，不要接收任何东西
as input but maybe two integers.
作为输入，而是接受两个整数。
And I'll call them arbitrarily a and b.
我会随意地将它们命名为 a 和 b。
But I have to tell the compiler what type of arguments
但我必须告诉编译器这些参数是什么类型
they are-- two integers, one after the other.
它们是什么——两个整数，一个接一个。
And now what I can do is this.
现在我可以这样做。
Let me change this up here, too-- int a, int b--
让我在这里也修改一下——int a, int b——
just so that the prototype is exactly the same.
这样原型就完全一样了。
And the only purpose of this prototype is just to avoid the previous error,
这个原型的唯一目的是为了避免先前的错误，
where the compiler didn't realize add was going to exist
编译器没有意识到 add 函数会存在
because it came later in the file.
因为它在文件中出现的比较晚。
So here on line 11 now, if I want to add two values, x and y,
现在，在第 11 行，如果我想添加两个值，x 和 y，
this is now the syntax.
这就是语法了。
We saw syntax in Scratch for passing in inputs
我们在 Scratch 中看到了传递输入的语法
to tell it how many times to meow.
来告诉它要喵多少次。
So this is just telling add what two numbers to add together.
所以这只是在告诉 add 函数要将哪两个数字加在一起。
So now I have to change this to a plus b, for reasons we'll soon see.
所以现在我必须将它改为 a 加 b，原因我们很快就会看到。
And let me see if this is right.
让我看看这是否正确。
Make calculator.
生成 calculator。
So far so good. ./calculator.
目前为止一切顺利。./calculator。
Let's do 1 and 2 for x and y respectively.
我们分别将 1 和 2 赋给 x 和 y。
And hopefully we should, again, see 3.
我们希望再次看到结果为 3。
Now, what's going on?
现在，发生了什么？
So here, again, if I zoom in on my add function, this "int" here on the left,
这里，我再次放大 add 函数，这个左边的 "int"，
on line 15, means what about add?
在第 15 行，意味着关于 add 函数什么呢？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生：[听不见]
DAVID MALAN: This means that it has a return value, that it's an int.
大卫·马兰：这意味着它有一个返回值，它是一个整数。
So it's going to hand me back, metaphorically, a slip of paper
所以它会形象地说，将一张纸条传给我
with an answer on it that is of type integer.
上面写着答案，这个答案是整数类型。
It's not a word, like my name.
它不是一个单词，比如我的名字。
It's a number instead.
它是一个数字。
These mentions of int here and here are inside the parentheses, which means
这里提到的 int，这里和这里，都在括号里面，这意味着
this function, add, takes two inputs.
这个函数，add，接受两个输入。
The first is an int.
第一个是整数。
The second is an int.
第二个也是整数。
And just so we have something to call them, I call them a and b respectively.
为了方便我们称呼它们，我分别将它们命名为 a 和 b。
So what happens essentially when I call the add function now on line 11,
所以，实际上，当我在第 11 行调用 add 函数时，
I'm kind of passing in x.
我相当于传递了 x。
I'm passing in y.
我传递了 y。
But the add function is going to think of them as a and b respectively.
但是 add 函数会将它们分别视为 a 和 b。
It could call them anything I want.
我可以随意地称呼它们。
I could change this to the word "first" and "second."
我可以将它们改为 "first" 和 "second"。
And then I could literally change this to "first + second."
然后我可以将这里直接改为 "first + second"。
Those are perfectly acceptable as argument or variable names.
这些都是可以接受的参数名或变量名。
But who really cares?
但谁在乎呢？
Like, a and b for such a simple function is perfectly reasonable, too.
比如，对于这样一个简单的函数，用 a 和 b 来命名也是很合理的。
Technically, if your mind is going there,
技术上来说，如果你这么想，
I could even call them the exact same thing.
我甚至可以称它们为完全相同的东西。
But let me propose for today, certainly don't do that because it just
但让我今天提出，当然不要那样做，因为那样做只会
confuses things if you've got x's and y's here, x's and y's here,
让事情变得混乱，如果你这里有 x 和 y，这里也有 x 和 y，
but they're clearly different.
但它们显然是不同的。
Just don't do that.
就不要那样做。
Try to come up with different variables just to keep yourself sane.
尽量想出不同的变量，只是为了让自己保持理智。
But here, I have a function that takes now two integers, a and b respectively.
但是在这里，我有一个函数，它现在接受两个整数，分别是 a 和 b。
It just returns the sum of them so that I can now store the return
它只是返回它们的总和，这样我就可以存储返回
value of add in a variable called z.
add 的值到一个名为 z 的变量中。
And then, quite simply, print it out.
然后，很简单，打印出来。
But there's one other thing I can do here.
但这里我还有一件事可以做。
Now, if we think about design, even if you've never programmed before,
现在，如果我们考虑设计，即使你以前从未编程过，
do I really need the variable z?
我真的需要变量 z 吗？
Because I'm defining it on line 11, and then I'm quickly using it on line 12,
因为我在第 11 行定义了它，然后我在第 12 行很快地使用它，
and that's it?
就这样吗？
Like, sometimes you don't need variables.
就像，有时候你不需要变量。
And they might make your code more readable.
它们可能会让你的代码更易读。
But strictly speaking-- and this is just kind of like substitution in math--
但严格来说，这就像数学中的替换一样，
if z is the same thing as "add (x, y)," well, let me go ahead
如果 z 和 “add (x, y)” 是同一个东西，那么，让我继续
and just delete line 11 altogether.
并直接删除第 11 行。
Let me get rid of mention of z.
让我摆脱对 z 的提及。
You can actually get away with doing this.
你实际上可以做到这一点。
And much like the Join block in Scratch, where I kind of overlaid it
就像 Scratch 中的 Join 模块一样，我把它覆盖了
on the Say block, kind of stacking them, you can stack functions in C,
在 Say 模块上，将它们叠起来，你可以在 C 中叠加函数，
or nest them really, kind of mathematically.
或者说真的将它们嵌套起来，有点像数学上的嵌套。
Honestly, it makes it a little harder to read
说实话，这会让它有点难以阅读
because your mind has to dive in conceptually deeper and deeper
因为你的思维必须在概念上越来越深入
into this second argument.
到这个第二个参数中。
But it's perfectly acceptable, too.
但这也是完全可以接受的。
And just to connect the dots to maybe something from high school,
只是为了将这些点连接起来，可能与高中的一些东西有关，
this is kind of analogous to a function in math class
这有点类似于数学课上的函数
being like f of x, where f is some function name,
就像 f of x 一样，其中 f 是某个函数名，
x is some arbitrary input to that function.
x 是该函数的任意输入。
And when you start to put functions inside of functions
当你开始将函数放在函数内部时
so that the output of one becomes the input to the next,
这样，一个函数的输出就成为下一个函数的输入，
it's like using this syntax, f of g of x and so forth.
这就像使用这种语法，f of g of x 等等。
If you've never seen that before, don't worry.
如果你以前从未见过，别担心。
But if you have, it's a way to connect some of these dots.
但如果你有，这是一个连接一些这些点的方法。
Any questions, though, on just this idea of now
不过，关于现在这个想法，有什么问题吗？
having a function that doesn't just have a side effect
拥有一个不只是有副作用的函数
but instead has a return value?
而是具有返回值？
Yeah, in back?
好的，后面那位？
STUDENT: In our declaration of main, why did we
学生：在我们对 main 的声明中，为什么我们
show it as returning an integer instead of void?
把它显示为返回一个整数而不是 void？
DAVID MALAN: In our definition of main, why did I do, what?
大卫·马兰：在我们对 main 的定义中，我做了什么？
STUDENT: Why do we show it as returning an integer
学生：为什么我们把它显示为返回一个整数
instead of returning as void?
而不是返回 void？
DAVID MALAN: Oh, a really good question that I was trying
哦，这是一个很好的问题，我今天一直在试图
to sweep under the rug for today.
掩盖过去。
But in every one of our programs thus far,
但在我们迄今为止的每一个程序中，
I have indeed said "int main(void)."
我确实说过“int main(void)”。
Technically speaking, whenever you write a program and it finishes running,
从技术上讲，每当你编写一个程序并完成运行时，
it actually returns a value somewhat secretly.
它实际上会秘密地返回一个值。
It returns the number 0 by convention, which means all is well.
按照惯例，它返回数字 0，表示一切正常。
And it can return any other integer if something goes wrong.
如果出现问题，它可以返回任何其他整数。
In fact, on your Mac, PC, or even phone, if you've ever
事实上，在你的 Mac、PC 甚至手机上，如果你曾经
gotten like a weird message on the screen, like something went wrong
在屏幕上看到过奇怪的提示，比如出了点问题
and it's like a weird numeric code, like error negative 129, or something
并且它看起来像一个奇怪的数字代码，比如错误 -129，或者类似的东西
arbitrary like that, that tends to mean that some program running
任意之类的，这意味着运行的某个程序
on your Mac, PC, or phone had something go wrong with the main function.
在你的 Mac、PC 或者手机上，主函数出现了一些问题。
And that is the number that was returned.
这就是返回的数字。
But that's more than we want to talk about today.
但今天我们不想讨论太多。
But we'll come back to this.
但我们会再回来谈这个。
But main always returns a number.
但 main 总是返回一个数字。
By default, it is 0.
默认情况下，它是 0。
More on that soon.
很快就会谈到这一点。
All right, so with that said, let's actually tease
好了，话虽如此，让我们真正地揭示
apart what it is we've been using underneath the hood
我们在幕后使用的是什么
here a little bit by returning to VS Code's interface itself.
这里，通过返回 VS Code 的界面本身。
It turns out that all this time, even though I
事实证明，一直以来，尽管我
keep alluding to macOS and Windows, which like 99% of us
一直提到了 macOS 和 Windows，我们中 99% 的人
are probably running on our laptops or desktops,
可能正在我们的笔记本电脑或台式机上运行，
there's actually other very popular operating systems in the world,
实际上，世界上还有其他非常流行的操作系统，
among which is Linux.
其中之一就是 Linux。
So Linux is a very popular operating system,
所以 Linux 是一个非常流行的操作系统，
the thing that turns on-- the thing that boots up
当你在第一次开机时，它启动——它启动
when you first turn on a computer.
你的电脑。
And it's very commonly used for servers nowadays.
如今它广泛用于服务器。
All of CS50's own servers run some version of Linux.
CS50 自己的服务器都运行着某种版本的 Linux。
Those students more comfortable sometimes
那些有时更习惯使用 Linux 的学生
run Linux on their own Macs or PCs even.
甚至会在他们自己的 Mac 或 PC 上运行 Linux。
So Linux is a very popular operating system.
所以 Linux 是一个非常流行的操作系统。
And it's particularly characterized by its textual interface,
它最显著的特征是其文本界面，
its command-line interface, even though it also comes with graphical ones,
它的命令行界面，即使它也带了图形界面，
as well.
也是。
So again, this term we started today with, a graphical user interface
所以，我们今天开始提到的这个词，图形用户界面
is a thing with menus and buttons.
是一个带菜单和按钮的东西。
It's literally what you and I use every day on our devices,
它就是我们每天在设备上使用的东西，
otherwise known as a GUI.
也就是我们所说的 GUI。
But today onward, you'll get more comfortable
但从今天开始，你会更加熟悉
with and more practice with this terminal window
并更多地练习使用这个终端窗口
down here, which represents a command-line interface, or CLI.
这里，它代表命令行界面，或 CLI。
And just so you have a mental model of what's going on in the cloud here,
为了让你对这里云中发生的事情有一个心理模型，
when you access cs50.dev, you are accessing this version of VS Code
当你访问 cs50.dev 时，你就是在访问这个版本的 VS Code
in the cloud, a piece of software just running in a browser.
在云端，一段软件正在浏览器中运行。
But that piece of software is automatically
但这段软件会自动
connected to your very own personal server in the cloud, so to speak.
连接到你自己的个人云服务器，可以这么说。
Technically speaking, it's a "docker container."
从技术上讲，它是一个“Docker容器”。
But it means that you have essentially your own mini server in the cloud
但这意味着你基本上在云端拥有了自己的小型服务器
that only you have access to.
只有你可以访问。
And that server or container is running an operating system called Linux.
这个服务器或容器运行着一个名为Linux的操作系统。
And in fact, every time I've been running a command down here,
实际上，每次我在这里运行命令时，
whether it's code or make or ./hello or anything else,
无论是代码、make、./hello还是其他任何东西，
I've been running commands from here in Sanders Theatre on a server somewhere
我一直在桑德斯剧院的某个服务器上运行命令
in the cloud, my own Linux container or server.
在云端，我自己的Linux容器或服务器。
And you'll have the same yourself.
你也会拥有相同的。
This is the thing that we have pre-configured
这是我们预先配置好的
for you by installing the compiler in so many other pieces of software
为你安装编译器和其他许多软件
you'll soon see in the class.
你很快就会在课堂上看到。
But underneath the hood, then, of Linux is a soon-to-be familiar environment
但Linux的底层是一个即将熟悉的环境
that allows you to run different types of commands.
它允许你运行不同类型的命令。
And those commands include things like this.
这些命令包括以下内容。
And this is something you'll develop muscle memory for over time.
随着时间的推移，你会对此形成肌肉记忆。
But I wanted to give you a sense of some of the most popular textual commands
但我希望让你了解一些最流行的文本命令
because we're essentially about to take away
因为我们实际上要带走
muscle memory you have from a GUI world and have you type out words that
你在GUI世界中所拥有的肌肉记忆，让你输入代表的文字
represent double-clicking on things, dragging on other things,
双击某些东西，拖动其他东西，
and other such commands that you and I take for granted.
以及其他我们习以为常的命令。
It'll be a little painful at first in the first days or weeks,
最初的几天或几周会有点痛苦，
but it will make you far more productive long term so that even after CS50,
但从长远来看，它会让你更有效率，即使在CS50之后，
if you start using your programming skills in some other domain, class,
如果你开始在其他领域、课堂
or real-world job, you'll just be a lot faster at the keyboard
或现实世界的工作中使用你的编程技能，你会在键盘上更快
and able to do more work more quickly.
并且能够更快地完成更多工作。
So with that said, let me go back to VS Code over here.
也就是说，让我回到这里的VS Code。
I'm going to go ahead and open up my File Explorer over here.
我将打开我的文件资源管理器。
And you'll see at left all of the files that I've
在左侧，你会看到我创建的所有文件
created thus far in class and all of the programs
在课堂上创建的所有程序
that I've compiled thus far in class.
我在课堂上编译的所有程序。
I also have this source 1 directory, which
我还有这个source 1目录，它
you can download from the course's website, which has all of today's code
你可以从课程网站上下载，它包含了今天的所有代码
pre-written in advance, so you don't have to type everything
提前写好了，所以你不必输入所有内容
that I literally type.
我字面上输入的内容。
But all of these files are things that I've created.
但所有这些文件都是我创建的。
And you'll see that in white are the C files.
你会看到用白色显示的是C文件。
And grayed out are actually the binary files, the machine code
用灰色显示的是二进制文件，也就是我创建并运行的机器代码。
that I created that I was running.
我创建并运行的机器代码。
So you can click on any of these files in VS Code to open them.
因此，你可以在VS Code中点击任何这些文件来打开它们。
For instance, here is hello.c.
例如，这是hello.c。
And voila, it opens in the text editor.
瞧，它在文本编辑器中打开了。
But if I try to open "hello," that's not going to work,
但是如果我尝试打开“hello”，它就无法正常工作，
because that's zeros and ones.
因为那是 0 和 1。
And frankly, the computer could show me all those zeros and ones,
坦白说，电脑可以向我展示所有这些 0 和 1，
but it's just not going to be useful.
但这毫无用处。
And honestly, it's too easy to make one mistake and break the whole thing.
老实说，犯一个错误就很容易破坏整个程序。
So instead, VS Code says that it can't display the text, because it's binary
因此，VS Code 表示它无法显示文本，因为它为二进制
or maybe unsupported more generally.
或更普遍地说是不受支持的。
So know that you want to only click on the .c files when writing C code.
所以记住，在编写 C 代码时，你只想点击 .c 文件。
But let me go ahead and do something else.
但让我继续做其他事情。
Suppose that I decide that, wait a minute, we're nearing the end of class.
假设我决定，等等，我们快下课了。
And we're not done yet, but what if I want to change hello.c to goodbye.c
我们还没结束，但如果我想把 hello.c 改成 goodbye.c
or if I want to change meow.c to woof.c and turn it into a dog?
或者如果我想把 meow.c 改成 woof.c，把它变成一条狗？
Well, let's actually do that.
好吧，让我们实际操作一下。
I could go over here and right click or Control click on the file,
我可以到这里，右键单击或 Control 点击该文件，
just like on a Mac or PC.
就像在 Mac 或 PC 上一样。
I can find the Rename option.
我可以找到重命名选项。
And I can do it all via the GUI.
我可以用 GUI 完成所有操作。
But you should get more comfortable using commands like these here.
但是你应该习惯使用像这样的命令。
And among the commands on this list are "mv" for move, a.k.a.
该列表中的命令包括“mv”表示移动，也称为
rename.
重命名。
So for instance, if I want to change meow.c to be woof.c instead,
例如，如果我想把 meow.c 改成 woof.c，
I literally type "mv" space, the original file name, space,
我只需要输入“mv”空格，原始文件名，空格，
and the new file name.
和新文件名。
So this is very similar to what I've already
所以这非常类似于我已经
been doing with the code program or the make program.
用 code 程序或 make 程序做的。
I not only type the name of the command but also the thing
我不仅输入命令的名称，还输入
that I want to code or the thing that I want to make.
我想要编写的代码或想要制作的东西。
In this case, I type the thing that I want to move from old to new.
在这种情况下，我输入我要从旧位置移动到新位置的东西。
Now, if I hit Enter in a moment, watch on the left-hand side,
现在，如果我马上按下 Enter，注意左侧，
meow.c in the GUI should automatically change
GUI 中的 meow.c 应该自动更改
even though I'm doing this all via the command-line keyboard interface.
即使我是在通过命令行键盘界面完成这一切。
And now it becomes woof.c.
现在它就变成了 woof.c。
I mean, it's not all that exciting.
我的意思是，这并不令人兴奋。
But this is just to say that they are one and the same.
但这只是为了说明它们是一回事。
One is a GUI, one is a CLI, but it's the same exact thing.
一个是 GUI，一个是 CLI，但它们完全相同。
Moreover, let me go ahead and close now the GUI
此外，让我继续关闭左侧的 GUI
at left, the so-called explorer.
也就是所谓的资源管理器。
And in my terminal window alone, now I'm kind of out of my element,
现在我只有终端窗口，有点不知所措，
like wait a minute, what was the file I created earlier?
就像等等，我之前创建的文件是什么？
Well, there's other commands as well.
好吧，还有其他命令。
On this list is, coincidentally, "ls," which lists
这个列表中，巧合的是，有“ls”，它列出
the file in your current folder.
当前文件夹中的文件。
And as you might have gleaned here, "mv" for move, "ls" for list,
你可能已经知道，这里“mv”表示移动，“ls”表示列出，
CS people like to be succinct, terse, and type
计算机科学专业的人喜欢简洁、简明，并输入
the minimal number of keystrokes.
最少的键击次数。
That's why these are all abbreviated commands instead of full words.
这就是为什么这些都是缩写命令而不是完整的单词。
But if I go back to my terminal window and type "ls," voila,
但如果我回到我的终端窗口并键入“ls”，瞧，
there is exactly the same contents of my server but displayed textually.
我的服务器的相同内容都在这里，但以文本形式显示。
And there's some heuristics here.
这里有一些启发式方法。
In green with an asterisk is all of the programs
用绿色和星号标记的是所有程序
that I made with make that are executable.
我用 make 制作的可执行程序。
So the asterisks just means this is executable with dot-slash.
所以星号只是意味着这是可以用点斜杠执行的。
Meanwhile, the source 1 directory, which only I have because I downloaded it
同时，source 1 目录，只有我拥有，因为我提前下载了它
in advance, has a slash to indicate that it's a folder instead of a file.
事先，它有一个斜杠来表示它是一个文件夹，而不是一个文件。
But all of these white files ending in .c we created together here today.
但所有这些以 .c 结尾的白色文件都是我们今天一起创建的。
Now, what if I really am embarrassed by my very first program, hello.c?
现在，如果我真的对我的第一个程序 hello.c 感到很尴尬呢？
Well, I can very destructively go and use the rm command for remove.
好吧，我可以非常具有破坏性地去使用 rm 命令来删除。
And rm hello.c is going to prompt me, a little cryptically,
而 rm hello.c 会提示我，有点神秘，
"remove regular file 'hello.c'?"
“删除普通文件‘hello.c’吗？”
And amazingly, this rm program has code just like we wrote earlier for agree.c,
令人惊讶的是，这个 rm 程序有代码，就像我们之前为 agree.c 编写的代码一样，
where I can type 'y' to delete it.
在那里我可以键入“y”来删除它。
I can type 'n' not to delete it.
我可以键入“n”来不删除它。
But let's delete it.
但让我们删除它。
Let's go ahead and hit y, enter.
让我们继续按下 y，然后回车。
Nothing seems to happen.
似乎什么也没发生。
But in general, that's a good thing.
但总的来说，这是一件好事。
But if I type "ls" again, notice what is now missing?
但如果我再次键入“ls”，请注意现在缺少什么？
And in fact, the list is a little shorter.
事实上，列表短了一些。
So it's one line instead of two.
所以是一行，而不是两行。
"hello.c" is now gone.
“hello.c”现在不见了。
Now, if you do that, there are not easy ways to get the file back.
现在，如果你那样做，没有简单的方法可以找回文件。
So don't do that unless you really want to.
所以不要那样做，除非你真的想要。
But there are backups maintained of these files, as well.
但这些文件也都有备份。
Well, what else is there, too?
好吧，还有其他什么？
Well, there's all of these other commands.
好吧，还有所有这些其他命令。
And you'll experience them over time.
你将随着时间的推移体验到它们。
Like, "cp" is copy.
比如，“cp”是复制。
"mkdir" is make directory. "rmdir" is remove directory.
“mkdir”是创建目录。“rmdir”是删除目录。
And for instance, let me just show you one folder.
例如，让我只展示一个文件夹。
If I type "ls," there's that source 1 folder
如果我键入“ls”，那里是那个 source 1 文件夹
that I claimed I downloaded in advance.
我声称我提前下载了它。
If you want to see what's there, you can type "cd"
如果你想看看里面有什么，你可以键入“cd”
for change directory, source 1, enter.
用于更改目录，source 1，回车。
And voila, notice that your prompt has now changed.
瞧，请注意你的提示现在已经改变了。
And let me clear the screen.
让我清理一下屏幕。
Just as a visual reminder of where you are, you can see before the dollar sign
为了让你直观地了解你在哪里，你可以在美元符号之前看到
now the name of the folder that you're inside of.
你现在所处的文件夹的名称。
So in Mac or Windows, you'd see obviously a graphical folder.
所以在 Mac 或 Windows 中，你显然会看到一个图形文件夹。
Here, you just see a little textual reminder of where you now are.
在这里，你只会看到一个小的文本提醒，表明你现在在哪里。
And if I type "ls," you'll see that I wrote a crazy number of files
如果我键入“ls”，你会看到我写了很多文件
before class.
课前。
And each of these represents different versions of the files
每一个都代表了不同版本的程序
that we've been coding here in real time that I usually
我们一直在实时编写，我通常
have printouts of just to go through things in series
只需打印出来以便按顺序查看
so you have copies online, as well.
您也可以在线获取副本。
So in short, all of these commands, if you've never used them before,
简而言之，如果您以前从未使用过这些命令，
they will soon become like muscle memory.
它们很快就会变成肌肉记忆。
And they do the most basic of operations.
它们执行最基本的操作。
But there will be other commands that we'll see over
但随着时间的推移，我们将看到其他执行更多功能的命令。
time that do even much more than that.
它们的功能远不止这些。
But let's go ahead now and solve some actual problems.
但现在让我们继续解决一些实际问题。
And it's no coincidence that we keep showing or alluding
我们不断展示或影射超级马里奥兄弟并非偶然，
to Super Mario Brothers in some form, an older game
这是一款来自任天堂娱乐系统的较老游戏，
from the Nintendo Entertainment System, that allows you ultimately
它最终允许您
to have this two-dimensional world, where Mario moves up and down
拥有这个二维世界，马里奥可以在其中上下移动
and side scrolls from left to right.
并从左到右滚动。
But you'll see we can distill even some aspects of "Mario"
但您会发现，我们甚至可以将“马里奥”的某些方面
into some fairly representative programming problems.
提炼成一些相当有代表性的编程问题。
And in fact, let me propose that we consider this screen
实际上，我建议我们考虑一下这个屏幕
from the original Super Mario Brothers.
来自原始的超级马里奥兄弟。
So there's these four blocks in the sky, each with a question mark.
天空中有四个方块，每个方块上都有一个问号。
And if you click on one of these-- or if Mario jumps up
如果你点击其中一个，或者马里奥跳到
underneath each of these question marks, he
每个问号的下方，他
gets like a coin or something else that pops out.
会获得一枚硬币或其他弹出的东西。
Let's distill this, though, into its essence and consider in C, how can
让我们将其提炼到本质，并考虑在 C 语言中，我们如何
we make, not a blue sky yet, not a green grassy hill, and so forth,
创建，不是蓝色的天空，也不是绿色的草地等等，
but how can we just make four question marks in a row,
而是如何仅仅在一行中创建四个问号，
because I dare say that we do have the building blocks via which to do this.
因为我敢说我们确实有用于实现此目的的构建块。
Well, the simplest way might be to go over here and run code of mario.c.
好吧，最简单的方法可能是到这里运行 mario.c 的代码。
And then in mario.c, let's include some stdio.h so we have printf.
然后在 mario.c 中，让我们包含一些 stdio.h，以便我们拥有 printf。
Let's do int main(void), as we keep doing.
让我们像往常一样做 int main(void)。
And inside of main, let's keep it super simple--
在 main 内部，让我们保持超级简单——
1, 2, 3, 4, backslash n.
1，2，3，4，反斜杠 n。
Doesn't get much simpler than that.
没有比这更简单的了。
This is not going to be the prettiest of games.
这将不会是最漂亮的游戏。
But if I make Mario now, ./mario, I get my four question marks in the sky.
但如果我现在创建马里奥，./mario，我将在天空中得到我的四个问号。
All right, so it's not all that interesting.
好吧，所以这并不那么有趣。
But this is clearly a candidate for what type of programming feature.
但这显然是哪种编程功能的候选者？
STUDENT: Scratch.
学生：Scratch。
DAVID MALAN: Not to Scratch, though Scratch would make it more interesting.
戴维·马兰：不是 Scratch，虽然 Scratch 会让它更有趣。
yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: A loop.
学生：循环。
DAVID MALAN: So some kind of loop, right?
戴维·马兰：所以某种循环，对吧？
So print the thing out iteratively instead.
所以用迭代的方式打印出来。
So let me do that.
所以让我来做。
Instead of just printing this out all at once,
与其一次性打印所有内容，
let me go ahead and remove this and do for int i gets zero; i less than 4;
让我继续删除这个，然后做 for int i gets zero; i less than 4;
i++.
i++。
And then in here, let me go ahead and print out just one question mark
然后在这里，让我继续打印出一个问号
instead.
而不是所有。
And now let's run this.
现在让我们运行一下。
So "make mario" to recompile it, ./mario.
所以要重新编译它，就输入“make mario”，然后 ./mario。
And does anyone not want me to hit Enter yet?
还有谁不想让我按回车？
Why?
为什么？
STUDENT: Because it's gonna print a new line.
学生：因为这样会打印一个新行。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's going to print out a new line every time.
戴维·马兰：是的，它每次都会打印一个新行。
So notice it's four question marks, but there each on its own line.
所以请注意，这里有四个问号，但它们分别占一行。
All right, well, let me fix this.
好的，让我来解决一下。
It's obviously because of the backslash n.
很明显，这是因为反斜杠 n。
So let me remove that.
所以让我把它去掉。
Let me rerun make mario, ./mario.
让我重新运行 make mario， ./mario。
And it's better in one way but worse in another.
这样在一个方面有所改进，但在另一方面却更糟糕。
So wait, but now the dollar sign is doing
等等，但现在美元符号正在
that thing where it's on the same line, which
做那件事，它在同一行，这
just looks stupid if nothing else.
至少看起来很蠢。
So how can I fix that?
那么我怎样才能解决这个问题？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so logically, we don't have that many building blocks
戴维·马兰：是的，所以从逻辑上讲，我们没有那么多的构建块
today.
今天。
It's a lot of new syntax, but it's not that many new ideas.
有很多新的语法，但新的想法却不多。
Let's just use printf to print out literally one and only
让我们只使用 printf 来打印一个，也只有一个
one of these backslash n's, but outside of the loop so
反斜杠 n，但要在循环之外，这样
it happens after all four of those have been printed.
它将在这四个被打印之后发生。
All right, let me do make mario again, ./mario.
好的，让我再次运行 make mario， ./mario。
And OK, now we're back in business.
好的，我们现在回来了。
So sort of silly syntactical details, but if you
所以，这是一些愚蠢的语法细节，但如果你
reduce the problem to its essence, it should hopefully, logically,
将问题简化为其本质，它应该，希望，逻辑上，
become clear over time.
随着时间的推移会变得清晰。
All right, well, how about not just something like that but vertical?
好的，怎么样，不仅仅是像这样，而是垂直的？
Well, we've done something vertical already.
嗯，我们已经做过垂直的事情了。
And so I can imagine we could change the program
所以我可以想象，我们可以改变程序
to very simply print out three bricks instead of four question marks.
简单地打印出三个砖块，而不是四个问号。
But what if we consider a two-dimensional world?
但是如果我们考虑二维世界呢？
And later on in this game if you go underground,
在游戏的后半部分，如果你进入地下，
everything looks like this with lots of bricks.
所有东西看起来都像这样，有很多砖块。
And let me propose, for the sake of discussion,
让我提议，为了讨论起见，
that this big wall here is like a 3-by-3 grid of bricks.
这堵大墙就像一个 3x3 的砖块网格。
So it's not just a single brick.
所以它不仅仅是一块砖块。
It's like three by three, or nine total.
它就像 3x3，或者总共 9 个。
Now things get interesting.
现在事情变得有趣了。
And let me go back to mario.c.
让我回到 mario.c。
I could take the easy road out and just say, all right, well,
我可以走捷径，直接说，好吧，
let's printf, how about 1, 2, 3, backslash n, close quote.
让我们 printf，怎么样，1、2、3、反斜杠 n、关闭引号。
And then, OK, let me just copy/paste.
然后，好的，让我复制粘贴。
And I'm using hashes instead of the actual bricks.
而我使用的是井号而不是真正的砖块。
But aesthetically, it's pretty close.
但从美学角度来看，它非常接近。
Let me now go ahead and "make mario" again, ./mario.
现在让我再次运行“make mario”， ./mario。
And it doesn't quite look like a square.
它看起来不像一个正方形。
But that's just because the hashes are a little taller than they are wide.
但这仅仅是因为井号比它们宽略高一些。
But it is correct, but not well designed.
但它是正确的，但设计得不好。
So here, too, what would be better designed than just hardcoding, typing
所以在这里，除了硬编码和输入之外，还有什么更好的设计方法呢？
literally all of these hashes?
这些哈希值呢？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: We could use maybe two loops.
学生：也许我们可以使用两个循环。
DAVID MALAN: Interesting, two loops.
大卫·马兰：有趣，两个循环。
And why two loops instead of one?
为什么要用两个循环而不是一个循环呢？
STUDENT: Oh, wait, nevermind.
学生：哦，等等，算了。
Well, I was going to say you could do it one for vertical and one
嗯，我本来想说你可以用一个循环来表示垂直方向，另一个循环来表示水平方向。
for horizontal.
表示水平方向。
DAVID MALAN: OK, it's the right instinct.
大卫·马兰：好的，这是正确的直觉。
So one for vertical, one for horizontal.
所以一个循环表示垂直方向，另一个循环表示水平方向。
And even though these predate most of us,
即使这些东西比我们大多数人出现的时间都要早，
old-school typewriters you might know or might
你可能知道或记得老式打字机，
recall that if you feed a piece of paper into it, you can print like line,
如果你把一张纸放进去，你可以像这样打印一行，
then it scrolls, line, then it scrolls, line, then it scrolls.
然后它滚动，一行，然后它滚动，一行，然后它滚动。
This is kind of how the terminal window works, too.
终端窗口也是这样工作的。
You can print rows and columns, but you have
你可以打印行和列，但是你必须
to print one row at a time, one row at a time, one row at a time.
一次打印一行，一次打印一行，一次打印一行。
It's not easy, but it is possible to go backwards and go up and down.
这并不容易，但可以向后走，上下走。
But just going row by row by row is more typical.
但是一行一行地走是更常见的。
So how can I do this?
那么我该怎么做呢？
Well, I could use at least one and maybe even indeed two loops.
好吧，我至少可以使用一个循环，甚至可以使用两个循环。
And this is where we're just now composing different ideas
而这正是我们现在将不同的想法组合在一起的地方
from today and even last week.
来自今天，甚至上周。
So let me go ahead and say, for int i gets 0; i less than 3--
所以让我说，对于int i获取0；i小于3--
for a 3-by-3 grid--
对于3x3的网格--
i++.
i++。
And now let me cheat slightly.
现在让我稍微作弊一下。
Let me print out just three of these here, and that's it.
让我在这里打印出这三个，就这些。
So I'm kind of cheating.
所以我在某种程度上作弊了。
I'm printing out rows dynamically, but I'm still printing three columns all
我动态地打印行，但我仍然在一次打印三列。
in one breath.
一口气打印。
But let's see what happens.
但让我们看看会发生什么。
Make mario, ./mario, and it does work.
创建马里奥，./马里奥，它确实有效。
But what if you said, no, I want 4 by 4 or 5 by 5 or 6 by 6?
但是如果你说，不，我想要4x4或者5x5或者6x6呢？
Now I have to change the 3 to a 6, and I have to add another three hashes here.
现在我必须把3改为6，并且我必须在这里添加另外三个哈希值。
Things get messy if we don't do this mathematically.
如果我们不以数学的方式这样做，事情就会变得很乱。
So let me now do this instead.
所以现在让我这样做。
Why don't I go ahead and print out every row at a time.
为什么我不一次打印一行呢？
But for each row, let me use another loop to decide, like, rat-a-tat-tat,
但是对于每一行，让我使用另一个循环来决定，比如，哒哒哒，
from left to right, how many do I want to print.
从左到右，我想打印多少个。
So to do this, I could do another for loop.
所以为了做到这一点，我可以使用另一个for循环。
I could call this variable something different. j is pretty common.
我可以给这个变量起一个不同的名字。j很常见。
We start at i, we go to j.
我们从i开始，我们到j。
If you go past k, maybe l, you're probably doing something wrong.
如果你超过k，也许是l，你可能做错了什么。
You don't want nested, nested, nested loops, but two is OK.
你不想使用嵌套、嵌套、嵌套的循环，但两个循环是可以的。
j equals 0; j is less than 3; j++.
j等于0；j小于3；j++。
And then here, I can print out a single one of these and no new line.
然后在这里，我可以打印出一个，并且没有换行符。
I don't want to screw up like I did before.
我不想像以前那样搞砸了。
So I'll just do one.
所以我就做一次。
Let me go ahead and do make mario now, ./mario.
让我现在来做 make mario，./mario。
But when I hit Enter, this is not correct yet.
但是当我按下回车键时，这还不正确。
What's it going to look like?
它会是什么样子？
STUDENT: A single line?
学生：一条线？
DAVID MALAN: A single line of nine hashes, I think,
大卫·马兰：我想是一条有九个井号的线，
because I never used a single backslash n.
因为我从未使用过一个反斜杠 n。
So that looks wrong.
所以看起来不对。
So between what line number should I insert a printf of backslash n?
那么我应该在哪个行号之间插入一个打印反斜杠 n 的语句？
Let me look a little farther back if I can.
如果可以，让我再往回看看。
How about over here?
这里怎么样？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: 10 and 11.
学生：10 和 11 之间。
DAVID MALAN: Between 10 and 11.
大卫·马兰：在 10 和 11 之间。
So I'm going to go in here.
所以我要到这里。
I'm going to add printf, quote, unquote, "backslash n" semicolon.
我要添加 printf，引号，引号，“反斜杠 n” 分号。
Let me go back and recompile mario--
让我回去重新编译 mario--
./mario.
./mario。
And crossing fingers-- voila, perfect.
然后祈祷-- 瞧，完美。
I printed out now a 3-by-3.
我现在打印了一个 3x3 的。
Now, it's correct.
现在，它是正确的。
It's not, if we want to be really nitpicky, maybe still not
如果我们真的要挑剔的话，它可能仍然不是
the best design.
最好的设计。
Where am I perhaps repeating myself?
我可能在哪里重复了自己？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I mean, it's not a huge deal.
大卫·马兰：是的，我的意思是，这没什么大不了的。
But now I have two, people would call these magic numbers.
但是现在我有两个，人们会称之为魔数。
"Magic" in the sense of, where did that come from?
“魔数”的意思是，它从哪里来的？
You just randomly put it in the middle of your code.
你只是随机把它放在代码的中间。
And you also put the same thing here.
你也把相同的东西放在这里。
Now I have to make sure I don't screw up and make one change but not the other.
现在我必须确保我不会搞砸，做了一个改变，但另一个没有改变。
So it turns out we can factor these out.
所以事实证明我们可以把它们分解出来。
I can actually do something like this, int n equals 3.
我实际上可以这样做，int n 等于 3。
And then I can just change this to n and this
然后我可以把这个改成 n，把这个
to n, which is marginally better because now
改成 n，这稍微好一点，因为现在
I only have to change n in one place if I want
如果我想改变这个东西的大小，我只需要在一个地方改变 n。
to make this thing bigger or smaller.
让它变大或变小。
It's still going to work the same.
它仍然会以同样的方式工作。
So make mario, ./mario.
所以 make mario，./mario。
There's our 3-by-3.
这是我们的 3x3。
But if I want to make a 5-by-5, let me change the n to 5, rerun make mario,
但是如果我想做一个 5x5 的，让我把 n 改成 5，重新运行 make mario，
./mario.
./mario。
And now it's a bigger grid, 5-by-5.
现在它是一个更大的网格，5x5。
But this is a little fragile.
但这有点脆弱。
And it turns out there's another trick we should introduce.
事实证明，我们应该引入另一个技巧。
It turns out that C supports what are called constants,
事实证明，C 语言支持所谓的常量，
whereby if you have a variable that you want to exist because it's useful
也就是说，如果你有一个变量，你希望它存在，因为它很有用
but you don't want to accidentally change it,
但是你又不想意外地改变它，
or if you're working with a partner in class or a colleague at work,
或者如果你在课堂上与搭档合作或在工作中与同事合作，
you don't want your partner or colleague to accidentally change
你不想你的搭档或同事意外更改
that value with their own code, you can go into your code and tell C,
该值使用他们自己的代码，你可以进入你的代码并告诉 C，
this is actually a constant integer, a const, so to speak.
这实际上是一个常数整数，一个 const，可以这么说。
And this will just prevent you or someone else
这将阻止你或其他人
from doing something stupid by accidentally changing it elsewhere.
意外地将它更改在其他地方而做一些愚蠢的事情。
The code is still going to work the same, ./mario,
代码仍然会以相同的方式工作，./mario，
but you won't be accidentally able to change it very easily to something
但你不会很容易地意外地将它更改为某物
else.
别的。
And honestly, what we've now done, too, is set ourselves
坦率地说，我们现在也做的事情，是让自己
up to make this more dynamic.
能够让它更具动态性。
Let me go up here, and let me add the CS50 library so that we have access
让我到这里，让我添加 CS50 库，以便我们可以访问
to get_int because now we could do something
get_int，因为现在我们可以做一些事情
fancy like ask the get_int function for the size of this brick wall.
有趣的事情，比如向 get_int 函数询问这堵砖墙的大小。
And then we can use n dynamically.
然后我们可以动态地使用 n。
So for instance, let me increase the size of my terminal, make mario,
例如，让我增加终端的大小，创建 mario，
./mario, size 3.
./mario，大小为 3。
Gives me a 3-by-3.
给我一个 3x3 的。
./mario size 5 gives me a 5-by-5.
./mario 大小为 5 给我一个 5x5 的。
./mario, how about 50, gives me a crazy big one, but it's all dynamic.
./mario，50 怎么样，给我一个超大的，但它都是动态的。
And now I don't have to even change the code.
现在我甚至不需要更改代码。
It just now works.
它现在就可以工作了。
As an aside, if you're wondering how I type so darn fast,
顺便说一句，如果你想知道我为什么打字这么快，
sometimes it's just because I'm hitting the up arrow.
有时只是因为我在按向上箭头。
It turns out that Linux will remember, if you
事实证明，如果你配置 Linux，它会记住
configure it this way, all of your previous commands.
以这种方式，你之前的所有命令。
So if you hit up, up, up, I can go through the past couple of hours
所以如果你按向上，向上，向上，我可以查看过去几个小时
of commands that I've typed, which is useful sometimes--
我输入的命令，这有时很有用——
not for hours of commands but the past few--
不是几个小时的命令，而是过去几个——
just to save yourself some keystrokes.
只是为了节省一些按键。
And another trick in a terminal window is to do this.
在终端窗口中，还有一个技巧。
If I do ./ma and I get bored and I don't want to type out "rio,"
如果我输入 ./ma，我厌倦了，不想再打出 “rio”，
I can also just hit Tab, and it will autocomplete based on the characters
我也可以直接按 Tab 键，它会根据匹配的字符自动补全。
that do match.
匹配的字符。
So those kinds of tricks, too, will save you time over time.
所以，这些技巧也能随着时间的推移节省你的时间。
But let's do this.
但让我们试试这个。
It's kind of broken, arguably, if I do this.
如果我这样做，可以说它有点问题。
How about "cat?"
“cat” 怎么样？
All right, well, that works.
好的，它确实可以。
That prevents me from doing something stupid
这阻止了我做一些愚蠢的事情
because get_int only accepts integers.
因为 get_int 只接受整数。
But it will accept 0, which does nothing.
但它会接受 0，它什么也不做。
It will accept negative 1, which does nothing.
它会接受负 1，它什么也不做。
And that's not bad.
这不是坏事。
It's not doing something weird.
它没有做一些奇怪的事情。
But it would be nice to catch that and force the user
但如果能捕获到这一点，并强制用户
to give us a positive integer instead so we at least
给我们一个正整数，这样我们至少
see something on the screen.
在屏幕上看到一些东西。
So let me go back into my code, and let me propose that now
所以让我回到我的代码，并且我现在建议
that we have the CS50 library, why don't we do something like this?
既然我们有了 CS50 库，为什么不尝试一下呢？
I'm going to change this.
我要更改一下。
I'm going to get rid of the constant just in case
为了以防万一，我要去掉这个常数
the user needs to type it again.
用户需要重新输入。
And what if I do this?
如果我这样做呢？
While n is less than 1--
当 n 小于 1 时...
so if it's 0, negative 1, negative 2, or whatever, let's go ahead
所以如果是 0、负 1、负 2 或其他，让我们继续
and again ask the user for an int, and ask them for the size again.
并再次询问用户一个整型值，并再次询问他们大小。
And therefore, only once n is not less than 1 will
因此，只有当 n 不小于 1 时，
this loop break out and will proceed with the rest of the code.
这个循环才会跳出并继续执行代码的其余部分。
So now let me try this.
现在让我试试。
Make mario, ./mario 0--
创建 mario，./mario 0...
didn't like that.
不喜欢这样。
Negative 1-- didn't like that.
负 1...不喜欢这样。
Negative 2-- didn't like that.
负 2...不喜欢这样。
3-- it did like that.
3...它喜欢这样。
So using a loop now, I can ensure that the human is providing me
现在使用循环，我可以确保用户提供给我
with input that I actually want.
我真正想要的输入。
So this is correct.
所以这是正确的。
But I dare say 6 through 10 could be done better.
但我敢说 6 到 10 可以做得更好。
Why is this poorly designed instinctively?
为什么这直觉上设计得很糟糕？
Yeah?
是吧？
STUDENT: There's repetition.
学生：存在重复。
DAVID MALAN: What's the repetition, to be clear, what lines?
大卫·马兰：重复的是什么，说清楚点，是哪几行？
STUDENT: Lines 6 and 9.
学生：第 6 行和第 9 行。
DAVID MALAN: 6 and 9.
大卫·马兰：第 6 行和第 9 行。
OK, so they're literally the same, and that's generally not a good thing.
好的，它们完全一样，这通常不是一件好事。
And maybe I could change this one to remind the user like, hey,
也许我可以修改这行代码，提醒用户，嘿，
that's not a positive number.
这不是一个正数。
So you might want to customize the message.
所以你可能想要自定义消息。
But just having copy/paste here for the most part is not a good thing.
但仅仅在这里进行复制粘贴，在很大程度上不是一件好事。
So it turns out-- and there's just one feature of C we wanted to introduce you
事实证明——我们今天想向你介绍 C 语言的一个特性——事实证明，还有一个方法可以帮助我们
to today-- it turns out there's one other way that would actually help us
消除使用 get_int 两次，尤其是询问
eliminate this redundancy of using get_int twice and particularly asking
完全相同的问题——大小——
literally the same question-- size--
两次重复。
twice in duplicate.
So I'm actually going to go into my code here,
所以我要进入我的代码，
and I'm going to delete the loop as we've written it thus far.
并且我要删除我们目前为止编写的循环。
And instead of using a while loop, I'm going
而不是使用 while 循环，我将
to introduce instead something that we typically
引入一个我们通常
call a do while loop, which is a little bit different.
称为 do while 循环，它略有不同。
Indeed, we begin with the keyword "do," and then
事实上，我们从关键字“do”开始，然后
inside of the curly braces, what I'm going to do here
在花括号内，我要在这里做的事情
is that thing I might want to do once and more times thereafter.
是我可能想做一次，然后再次做的事情。
So for instance, I'm going to say n equals get_int quote, unquote, "size."
例如，我要说 n 等于 get_int，引号，引号，"size"。
And then at the bottom of this block of code, then
然后在这段代码块的底部，
I'm going to use the keyword "while," as well as parentheses as always
我要使用关键字“while”，以及始终使用的括号
for a Boolean expression.
用于布尔表达式。
And here.
以及这里。
I'm going to ask the question, do this while n is less than 1.
我要问一个问题，当 n 小于 1 时，执行这段代码。
But there's one fix I still need to do here because notice on the current line
但是，这里还有一处需要修复的地方，因为请注意当前行
8, I actually haven't given n a type.
8，实际上我还没有给 n 指定类型。
I haven't declared n yet.
我还没有声明 n。
But it would not be correct to declare n here, inside of that do block.
但是在这里，在这个 do 代码块中声明 n 是不正确的。
But why might that be?
但是为什么呢？
Why would it not be a good thing to declare n inside of these curly braces?
为什么在这些花括号内声明 n 不是一个好主意呢？
Yeah, so recall that this is an issue of scope.
是的，请记住，这是一个作用域问题。
Recall that the scope of a variable is generally
请记住，变量的作用域通常
confined to the most recently opened curly braces in which that variable is
被限定在最近打开的花括号中，其中该变量是
declared.
声明的。
And so if I declare this variable on line 8,
所以如果我在第 8 行声明这个变量，
I'm not going to be able to use it on line 10.
我将无法在第 10 行使用它。
But there is a fix, even though it might look a little strange.
但是，即使它看起来有点奇怪，也有一种解决办法。
I'm going to go above my do block here.
我要到我的 do 代码块上面去。
And before I go into this loop, I'm actually
在进入这个循环之前，我实际上
going to declare n to be an integer, but semicolon, end of thought.
要声明 n 是一个整数，但分号，思想结束。
I'm not going to bother giving it a value, because I
我不会费心给它赋值，因为我知道
know logically I'm going to end up giving it a value anyway now on line 9.
从逻辑上讲，我现在最终会在第 9 行给它赋值。
And so what's different about this version of the code
所以，这个版本的代码有什么不同
is that the do while loop ensures that we prompt the user for input at least
是 do while 循环确保我们至少提示用户输入一次
once.
。
And then while that input is not what we expect, for instance less than 1, then
然后，当输入不符合我们的预期时，例如小于 1，那么
it's going to execute again, again, again.
它会再次执行，再次执行，再次执行。
And indeed, the semantics are just that.
实际上，语义就是这样。
Do the following while this Boolean expression is true.
当这个布尔表达式为真时，执行以下操作。
So if I go ahead now and rerun make mario, compiles OK-- ./mario.
所以，如果我现在继续运行 make mario，编译成功-- ./mario。
And now I'll go ahead and input something that's not correct, like 0.
现在，我将输入一些不正确的东西，比如 0。
But I'm prompted again.
但是我又被提示了。
I'll input something like negative 1, and I'm prompted again.
我将输入类似负 1 的东西，然后我又被提示了。
But if I go ahead and input, for instance, 10,
但是如果我继续输入，例如，10，
now, because that's a positive integer, I indeed get a 10-by-10 grid of bricks.
现在，因为这是一个正整数，我确实得到一个 10x10 的砖块网格。
And there's one other thing we should introduce here, too, in C, too.
在 C 中，我们也应该在这里介绍另一件事。
C supports comments.
C 支持注释。
And a couple of you have asked about this
你们中的一些人问过这个问题
if you come from other programming languages.
如果你来自其他编程语言。
Suppose I want to remember what it is I just did with this program.
假设我想记住我刚刚用这个程序做了什么。
Let me go in between lines 5 and 6 here and do "// prompt user for positive
让我在这里在第 5 行和第 6 行之间加上 "// prompt user for positive
integer."
This is what's known as a comment.
这就是所谓的注释。
And it's grayed out only in the sense that the compiler is not
它只是在灰色的意义上，编译器不会
going to care about this.
关心这件事。
The computer is not going to care about this.
计算机不会关心这件事。
This is a note to self, like a sticky note in the context of Scratch.
这就像在 Scratch 中的一个便签，是自己给自己留的便签。
And it starts with "//," which essentially tells the compiler ignore
它以 "//" 开头，这实质上告诉编译器忽略
this, this is for the human, not for the computer.
这个，这个是给人看的，不是给计算机看的。
But this comment, so to speak, is a way of just reminding yourself, reminding
但是，这个注释，可以这么说，是一种提醒自己、提醒自己的方式，
your colleague, reminding your TF what it
你的同事，提醒你的 TF 是什么
is a few lines of code are meant to do.
几行代码应该做什么。
And now this comment might be print, and how about n-by-n grid of bricks?
现在这个注释可能是打印的，那么n*n的砖块网格呢？
And what's nice about comments is that theoretically you can get away with,
注释的好处是，理论上你可以摆脱，
or someone else can get away with, just reading this comment
或者其他人可以摆脱，只读这个注释
and then not even have to look at the rest of the code.
然后甚至不必看代码的其余部分。
They can look at this comment and not have to look at the rest of the code
他们可以查看此注释，而不必查看代码的其余部分
because you've described for them what it's meant to do.
因为你已经为他们描述了它应该做什么。
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: I just had a question about the hashtag [INAUDIBLE]
学生：我有一个关于井号 [听不清] 的问题
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
大卫·马兰：当然。
STUDENT: That's for [INAUDIBLE]
学生：那是 [听不清] 的
DAVID MALAN: Correct, the hash sign in Python is a comment,
大卫·马兰：正确，在 Python 中，井号是注释，
is not the same thing in C. In C, hash include means to include the library's
在 C 中则不是这样。在 C 中，hash include 表示包含库的
header files in that way.
头文件。
Other questions on these here tricks?
还有其他关于这些技巧的问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right, so as promised, what is maybe C not actually good at?
好吧，正如承诺的那样，C 可能不擅长什么？
Well, let me propose that we consider what's
好吧，我想建议我们考虑一下什么是
actually inside of your computer.
实际上在你电脑里。
At the end of the day, whether it's a Mac, PC, iPhone, Android, phone,
归根结底，无论是 Mac、PC、iPhone、Android 手机，
or some other computer device, there's something that looks like this.
还是其他任何电脑设备，都有一些东西看起来像这样。
And this is memory, otherwise known as RAM, or random access memory,
这就是内存，也称为 RAM，即随机存取内存，
for reasons we'll get to in a few weeks.
原因我们将在几周后讲到。
But this is where data is stored.
但数据就存储在这里。
This is where "hello, world" is stored.
“hello, world” 就存储在这里。
This is where 1 and 2 and all of those numbers are stored.
1 和 2 以及所有这些数字都存储在这里。
Any data in your program is stored ultimately in the computer's memory.
程序中的任何数据最终都存储在计算机的内存中。
And the most important takeaway for today is that all of us
今天最重要的收获是，我们所有人
only have a finite amount of memory in our devices.
在我们的设备中只有有限的内存。
You might have a high-end device which has a lot of memory,
你可能有一个高端设备，它有很大的内存，
but it's still finite, which means you can only
但它仍然是有限的，这意味着你只能
count so high with that device.
用那个设备数到那么高。
You can only store so many files with that device.
你只能用那个设备存储那么多文件。
There are fundamental physical limitations even though mathematically,
即使在数学上，也存在基本的物理限制，
theoretically, we should be able to count toward infinity.
理论上，我们应该能够数到无穷大。
So what are the implications for this?
那么，这对我们有什么影响呢？
Well, consider this.
好吧，想想看。
In the world of numbers, as per week 0, if you're only using three digits--
在数字世界中，按照第 0 周，如果你只使用三位数——
and I've grayed out the fourth one just to make the point-- if you're only
我把第四位数涂成灰色，只是为了说明这一点——如果你只
using three digits, we can count from 0 to 1 in decimal, to 2, to3, to 4,
使用三位数，我们可以从 0 数到 1（十进制），到 2，到 3，到 4，
to 5, to 6, to 7.
到 5，到 6，到 7。
And as soon as you count to 8, you technically, per last week,
一旦你数到 8，你就需要，根据上周的内容，
need a fourth bit.
需要第四位。
But if you don't have it, the number 7 might seem
但如果你没有，数字 7 可能会看起来
to be followed by what number instead?
紧跟着什么数字？
STUDENT: 0.
学生：0。
DAVID MALAN: 0.
大卫·马兰：0。
The number overflows, so to speak, right?
这个数字就溢出了，可以这么说，对吧？
You carry the 1.
你进位了1。
But if there's no place to put the 1, because there's no fourth light bulb,
但如果没地方放这个1，因为没有第四个灯泡，
if there's no fourth transistor, if there's no fourth bit,
如果第四个晶体管不存在，如果第四个位不存在，
the lower bits, the zeros, are going to be mistaken for the number you
那些较低的位，那些0，会被误认为是你
and I know is 0.
以及我知道的数字0。
So integer overflow is a thing in computers
所以整数溢出是计算机中的一件事
whereby if you don't have enough memory, if you count high enough,
如果内存不足，如果你计数足够高，
the number will wrap around back to 0.
这个数字就会回绕到0。
Or sometimes it will wrap around to a negative number,
或者有时它会回绕到一个负数，
depending on whether the code supports negative and positive numbers and 0
取决于代码是否支持负数、正数和0
alike.
等等。
So that has some very real world implications
所以这在现实世界中有一些非常实际的影响
in integer overflow that's sort of a fundamental limitation of how
在整数溢出中，这是一种关于如何处理数字的基本限制。
numbers are typically stored.
数字通常是如何存储的。
Now, thankfully, we typically don't store things
现在，谢天谢地，我们通常不存储东西
based on number of digits but number of bits.
是基于位数而是基于位数。
And a bit is just a 0 or 1.
一个位仅仅是0或1。
And recall from last week that a common unit of measure
还记得上周我们提到的一个常见计量单位
is minimally eight bits, or a byte, but even more commonly is 32.
是至少8位，也就是一个字节，但更常见的是32位。
So for instance, here are 32 bits, all zeros.
例如，这里有32位，全是0。
And if you do out the math, this is the number
如果你算一下，这个数字
you and I know in decimal is of course 0.
你我用十进制都知道当然就是0。
But if I change all 32 zeros to ones, this is a really big number now.
但如果我把所有32个0都改为1，现在就变成了一个很大的数字。
If we're only using positive numbers, not negatives,
如果我们只使用正数，不使用负数，
what number roughly is this, 32 ones?
这个数字大致是多少，32个1？
It's roughly 4 billion in total-- roughly 4 billion in total.
总共大约是40亿——总共大约是40亿。
Why?
为什么？
Well, if you've got 32 bits, each can be two possible values, 0 or 1, that's
嗯，如果你有32位，每个位都有两种可能的值，0或1，那就是
2 to the 32nd power, which is roughly--
2的32次方，大约是——
I'll stipulate-- roughly 4 billion total.
我承认——总共大约是40亿。
The problem is, what if you want to count to 4,000,000,001?
问题是，如果你想数到4,000,000,001怎么办？
That's a bit of a white lie.
那有点说谎了。
It's not precisely that.
并不完全是那样。
But what if you want to count just higher than that?
但如果你想数到比那还高怎么办？
You'd need a 33rd bit because all of the others
你需要一个第33位，因为其他所有位
are going to go to 0 at that point, and you might count from 1 to 2
在那一点会变成0，你可能会从1数到2
to 3 to 4 billion back to 0, or worse if you're dealing with negative numbers,
到3到40亿再回到0，或者更糟的是，如果你在处理负数，
too.
也是一样。
So the fact that there are finitely many bits used in computers is a problem.
所以计算机中使用的位数是有限的，这是一个问题。
And negative numbers do add a complexity because this is specifically
而负数确实增加了复杂性，因为这个数字具体来说是
the 4 billion in question--
我们要讨论的40亿——
4,294,968,295.
4,294,968,295。
That is as high as you can count with 32 bits
用32位你能数到的最大数字
if you don't bother with negatives.
如果你不考虑负数的话。
But if you want negative numbers, you've got to half
但如果你想要负数，你必须把它们减半
that because you've got to save half of them for negative, half of them
因为你必须留出其中的一半用于负数，另一半用于正数，或多或少。
for positive, give or take.
或多或少。
And so if you're supporting negative numbers, as you probably
所以如果你支持负数，就像你可能
should for a calculator, for Microsoft Excel, Google Spreadsheets,
应该为计算器、微软 Excel、Google 表格做的那样，
you can only count as high up as 2 billion roughly,
你只能数到大约 20 亿，
or negative 2 billion roughly instead.
或者大约负 20 亿。
So it turns out that when you are using data types in C,
所以事实证明，当你使用 C 语言中的数据类型时，
you have some control over how many bits are actually used.
你可以控制实际使用的位数。
And this list is longer than we've covered today,
这个列表比我们今天讨论的要长，
but we did talk about integers for a while.
但我们确实讨论了一段时间的整数。
Those are, by convention nowadays, 32 bits.
如今，按照惯例，它们是 32 位。
If that's not enough, you can upgrade your variables to longs, which
如果这还不够，你可以将变量升级为 longs，它们
tend to be 64 bits instead, which isn't just twice as big as an integer,
通常是 64 位，这不仅仅是整数的两倍大，
it's actually 64 bits, which is exponentially more.
它实际上是 64 位，指数级地更大。
It's an unpronounceable number, at least for me.
至少对我来说，这是一个无法发音的数字。
That's a crazy big number, but it's available to you.
这是一个非常大的数字，但你可以使用它。
Moreover, we can see this if we actually are a little reckless with how
此外，如果我们在使用代码的方式上稍微鲁莽一些，我们就能看到这一点。
we're using code.
我们使用代码。
And just so you know too, though, there are
另外，你也要知道，有
functions even in CS50's library that let
即使在 CS50 的库中也有函数，可以让
you use these larger values, get long of course, will get you a long.
你使用这些更大的值，当然，获取 long 会给你一个 long。
And this one's a little non-obvious, but "%li" is the format code for printf,
这有点不明显，但是 “%li” 是 printf 的格式代码，
just so you know, for printing a long integer and not just an integer.
你只要知道，用于打印长整数，而不仅仅是整数。
So it's two characters instead of one.
所以它是两个字符，而不是一个字符。
Suppose, though, we actually want to use code involving some large numbers.
但是，假设我们实际上想要使用涉及一些大数字的代码。
It turns out that certain bad things can happen.
事实证明，某些不好的事情可能会发生。
So let me go ahead and do this.
所以让我继续做这个。
I'm going to go back over to VS Code here,
我将回到这里的 VS Code，
and I'm going to modify my calculator to do something that, at glance, should
我会修改我的计算器，做一些看起来很合理的事情，
be perfectly reasonable.
应该是完全合理的。
Let me go ahead and open up calculator.c, as before.
让我继续打开 calculator.c，像以前一样。
And where we left off, we had this add function.
我们在停下的地方，我们有这个 add 函数。
And you know what?
你知道吗？
I'm going to simplify it back to its very original version.
我将把它简化回它最初的版本。
I'm going to go ahead and get rid of the add function
我将继续删除 add 函数
and just distill it to its essence, which is not to add any more.
并将其简化为其本质，即不再添加任何东西。
But let's just do division.
但我们只做除法。
I want to print out this time maybe x divided by y.
这次我想打印出 x 除以 y。
So here we go. x divided by y is a nice simple program in my calculator.
所以，我们开始吧。x 除以 y 是我计算器中一个简单的程序。
Let me do make calculator again, ./calculator.
让我再次执行 make calculator，然后 ./calculator。
And let's divide something like 1 divided by 3, which should--
让我们除一些东西，比如 1 除以 3，这应该——
hm, OK, weird.
嗯，好吧，奇怪。
It gave me 0 instead of probably 0.3333333,
它给了我 0，而不是可能出现的 0.3333333，
as you might have expected for 1/3.
正如你可能预期 1/3 应该给出的结果。
So what might the takeaway there be?
所以，你从中能得到什么结论呢？
Why am I seeing zero perhaps?
为什么我看到了零？
Yeah?
是吗？
STUDENT: If 0's the integer [INAUDIBLE],, then if you want decimals [INAUDIBLE]..
学生：如果 0 是整数 [不可识别]，那么如果你想要小数 [不可识别]…
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so 0 is an integer.
大卫·马兰：是的，所以 0 是一个整数。
And indeed, that's what I'm telling the thing to print.
实际上，这就是我告诉程序要打印的内容。
And in fact, if we go over to my little cheat sheet here of format codes,
事实上，如果我们看一下我的格式代码备忘单，
I'm currently using %i.
我目前使用的是 %i。
I should actually, when I do division of numbers that might have floating point
实际上，当我进行可能包含浮点数的数字除法时，
values, a decimal point that floats left to right,
也就是小数点在左右浮动的值，
otherwise known as a real number, I want to use %f for float instead.
也称为实数，我想要使用 %f 来表示浮点数。
So I'm actually going to go back to my code here.
所以我打算回到我的代码。
And let's try this-- %f instead of %i.
我们试试这个，使用 %f 代替 %i。
And let me go ahead and "make calculator."
我直接执行 “make calculator”。
Huh, all right.
嗯，好吧。
Well, this didn't work then.
看来这个方法行不通。
"Format specifies type 'double,' but the argument has type 'int.'
“格式指定类型为 'double'，但参数类型为 'int'。”
All right, so that, too, is not quite working.
好吧，这个也不太奏效。
So I think I actually need to make a change here further.
我想我需要在这里做进一步的改变。
Let me actually go ahead and do this.
我直接执行一下。
It turns out that besides integers, there
事实证明，除了整数之外，还有
are these things called floats, and also doubles.
称为浮点数和双精度数的东西。
A float uses 32 bits, and a double uses 64 bits.
浮点数使用 32 位，双精度数使用 64 位。
And that doesn't necessarily mean you can
这并不一定意味着你可以
count higher as much as it means you can have
计数更多，而是指你可以拥有
more numbers after the decimal point.
更多的小数位数。
So if you want a more precise value, you throw memory at it
所以，如果你想要一个更精确的值，你可以用更多的内存来存储它
by using a double and 64 bits instead of a float.
通过使用双精度数和 64 位而不是浮点数。
But we'll keep it simple, and let me go ahead and do this.
但我们还是先简单一点，我直接执行一下。
Let me just do the math using the type of variable that I should be here.
我直接用这里应该使用的变量类型进行计算。
Let me do not int, but float z equals x divided by y.
我直接使用 float z 等于 x 除以 y，而不是 int。
And now let me go ahead and print out the value of z.
现在我打印 z 的值。
Strictly speaking, I don't need the variable.
严格地说，我不需要这个变量。
But I'm trying to be pedantic and actually use a float explicitly
但我想严格一点，显式地使用一个浮点数
this time so we see a real number.
这次，这样我们就能看到一个实数。
All right, let me go ahead and do make calculator, ./calculator.
好的，我直接执行 make calculator，./calculator。
1 divided by 3 equals--
1 除以 3 等于——
damn, now it's just showing me more zeros, which clearly isn't the case.
糟糕，现在只是显示了更多零，这显然不正确。
Well, this is because of an issue that we'll generally call truncation.
好吧，这是因为一个问题，我们通常称之为截断。
So truncation is just a term of art that means if you take an integer
所以，截断只是一个专业术语，意思是如果你取一个整数
and you divide it by an integer, even if you get a fractional value,
并将其除以一个整数，即使你得到一个分数，
the fraction just gets thrown away because you're only
这个分数就被扔掉了，因为你只是在
doing integer-based math.
进行基于整数的运算。
So if there's anything after the decimal point,
所以，如果小数点之后有任何内容，
it just gets truncated, literally discarded.
就会被截断，也就是说被丢弃。
So what should 1 divided by 3 be?
那么 1 除以 3 应该等于多少呢？
Obviously, 0.33333333-- ad nauseum.
显然，0.33333333——无穷无尽。
Fortunately, you throw away everything after the decimal point,
幸运的是，你扔掉了小数点之后的所有内容，
which leaves you still with just 0.
剩下的是 0。
And even though I'm seeing more zeros, that's because we threw away all
虽然我看到了更多的零，但那是因为我们扔掉了所有的
of the 3's.
3。
That is just what happens when you use integers and do
这就是使用整数进行运算时发生的事情。
any kind of division like that.
像这样的任何一种除法。
But there is a solution.
但是有一个解决方法。
We can actually convert, or cast, integers to floating point values.
我们实际上可以将整数转换为浮点数。
So we can tell C, I know this is an integer now.
所以我们可以告诉C，我知道这现在是一个整数。
But go ahead and treat it as though it has a decimal point, even
但是继续把它当作有小数点一样对待，即使
if it's .0 At the end of the number.
如果它在数字的末尾是 .0。
So I can go into this, and I can use parentheses and literally write
所以我可以进入这里，我可以使用括号，并逐字写下
"float" in parentheses.
括号中的“float”。
And over here for y, I can literally use parentheses and convert y to a float.
而在这里对于y，我也可以使用括号，并将y转换为浮点数。
The term of art here is type casting.
这里专业的术语是类型转换。
You're converting one type to another effectively, or technically treating
你实际上将一种类型转换为另一种类型，或者从技术上讲是将
one type as though it's another even if it doesn't necessarily
一种类型当作另一种类型对待，即使它不一定
have a mathematical impact.
有数学上的影响。
But what it means now is that z will be defined
但现在这意味着z将被定义
by dividing one float by another.
通过将一个浮点数除以另一个浮点数。
So truncation will not now happen.
所以现在不会发生截断。
So let me do make calculator, ./calculator.
所以让我来制作计算器，./calculator。
And now 1 divided by 3, there it is.
现在1除以3，就在那里。
Now the math is actually correct.
现在数学实际上是正确的。
But my God, we had to jump through hoops just to get this to work.
但我的天哪，我们不得不跳过障碍才能让它工作。
So to be clear, the two issues we-- well, the issue we encountered
所以要明确地说，我们遇到的两个问题，或者说我们遇到的问题是
was truncation.
截断。
If you divide an int by an int, you will get an int no matter
如果你将一个整数除以一个整数，无论如何你都会得到一个整数
what it should be mathematically.
它在数学上应该是什么。
But if you instead type cast the values, the variables to a floating point
但如果你改为将值，将变量类型转换为浮点数
value, or a double for that matter, then a float divided by a float will give
值，或者说一个双精度数，那么一个浮点数除以一个浮点数将得到
you a float and preserve all of those 3's.
一个浮点数，并保留所有这些3。
But here's another catch, or at least a limitation potentially with computers.
但这里还有另一个问题，或者说至少是计算机潜在的限制。
What if I go ahead here and do--
如果我在这里继续做--
let me do this.
让我做这个。
Let me show you one trick here, even though the syntax is a bit weird.
让我在这里给你展示一个技巧，即使语法有点奇怪。
Instead of printing out %f alone, let me print out % dot,
而不是只打印 %f，让我打印 % 点，
maybe 5f So this is weird syntax.
也许是5f。所以这个语法很奇怪。
And it's only specific to printf.
它只适用于 printf。
"%.5f" means 'show me five decimal places specifically.'
“%.5f”表示“具体地显示我五个小数位”。
So if I do make calculator, ./calculator, 1, 3, voila,
所以如果我做 make calculator，./calculator，1，3，瞧，
I get five decimal places.
我得到了五个小数位。
If I want six, let's do this.
如果我想要六个，让我们这样做。
I'll change the code to 6.
我会将代码改为 6。
Make calculator, ./calculator, 1, 3, and now I get six 3's instead.
制作计算器，./calculator，1，3，现在我得到六个3而不是五个。
All right, well, wouldn't it be nice to be even more precise?
好吧，如果更精确一点会怎么样？
Let's give me 20 significant digits after the decimal point.
让我们在小数点后给我 20 位有效数字。
So make calculator, ./calculator, 1 divided by 3, and-- woo.
所以制作计算器，./calculator，1 除以 3，然后--哇。
So your middle school teacher seems to have lied to you at this point.
所以你的初中老师似乎在这个时候对你撒了谎。
1 divided by 3 is apparently not 0.33333 with a line over it,
1 除以 3 显然不是 0.33333，上面有一条线，
or just infinite number of 3's.
或者只是无限个3。
OK, that's not quite the right conclusion, though.
好的，但这并不是完全正确的结论。
Oops.
哎哟。
Why might I be seeing these weird numbers instead
为什么我看到的不是一堆3，而是这些奇怪的数字？
of just lots of 3's, intuitively?
从直觉上来说？
Why this rounding error?
为什么会出现这个舍入误差？
Yeah?
对吧？
STUDENT: The computer just has a [? limited ?] [? memory. ?] So
学生：电脑的内存是有限的。所以
there's [INAUDIBLE]
就会出现这种情况。
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·马兰：没错。
The computer only has limited memory, finite memory.
电脑的内存是有限的，是有限的。
So it just can't represent every possible number in the universe
所以它无法表示宇宙中所有可能的数字
because we know from grade school there are infinitely many of those numbers.
因为我们从小学就知道，这些数字是无限的。
So what you're essentially seeing is the closest it can actually get.
所以你看到的实际上是最接近的值。
It's rounding to the nearest floating point value, if you will.
它将值舍入到最接近的浮点数，如果你愿意的话。
And it also relates to how the numbers themselves are represented
这还与这些数字在内存中的表示方式有关
in memory underneath the hood.
在引擎盖下的内存中。
I can do a little better, though.
不过，我还可以做得更好。
Let me zoom out.
让我缩小一下。
And let me upgrade, so to speak, from 32 bits to 64 bits and use
我们可以进行升级，从32位升级到64位，使用
doubles instead.
双精度浮点数。
I can still use %f.
我仍然可以使用%f。
You don't use %d for double.
双精度浮点数不用%d。
Let me do make calculator again, ./calculator, 1, 3.
我再运行一遍calculator，./calculator，1，3。
I get more 3's but still some rounding.
我得到了更多的3，但仍然存在一些舍入。
It's more precise, but it's not 100% accurate,
精度更高了，但不是100%准确，
because that's just not going to be possible in terms
因为这在计算机内存方面是不可能的
of the computer's memory.
。
So this is a whole other issue known as floating point imprecision, which
所以，这是一个全新的问题，称为浮点数精度问题，它
is another type of limitation.
是另一种类型的限制。
We saw integer overflow, if integers can only
我们看到了整数溢出，如果整数只能
count so high before you run out of bits and things wrap around.
计算到一定程度就会用完位，然后就会发生溢出。
Floating point imprecision means that you can't possibly
浮点数精度问题意味着你不可能
represent the infinite number of real numbers that exist in the universe
用有限的内存表示宇宙中无限多的实数
if you only have a finite amount of memory.
。
You would need an infinite number of bits, it would seem.
看来你需要无限多的位。
So these are two issues that actually fundamentally
所以，这两个问题实际上从根本上
can influence the correctness not only of
会影响你的代码以及现实世界中代码的正确性，不仅仅是
your code but code in the real world.
你的代码，还有现实世界中的代码。
And case in point, back in my day--
举个例子，在我那个年代--
I graduated in 1999-- and a lot of the world
我毕业于1999年，世界上很多人
thought the world was going to end around then
认为世界将在那时结束
because around the time the years rolled over from 1999 to 2000,
因为在年份从1999年翻到2000年的时候，
there was a lot of old software still running in the world.
世界上还有很多旧软件在运行。
And in fact, that old software, reasonably so,
事实上，这些旧软件，理所当然地，
only used two digits to represent years.
只用两位数来表示年份。
Why?
为什么？
Memory was very expensive early on.
早期内存非常昂贵。
And if you could use half as much memory to store a year, that was a win.
如果你可以用一半的内存来存储一年，那可是胜利。
That saved you money.
省钱。
That saved you memory.
省内存。
The problem though, of course, is that a lot
问题是，当然，有很多
of old software from the '70s and prior was still running in 1999.
很多上世纪70年代或更早期的旧软件还在1999年运行。
And unless companies or individuals updated that software,
除非公司或个人更新这些软件，
1999 might be mistaken for the year 1900 instead of 2000,
1999年可能会被误认为是1900年而不是2000年，
because all of the code just assumed that, of course,
因为所有的代码都假设，当然，
we're talking about the 1900s.
我们指的是20世纪。
This code is not going to be running 50 years later,
这些代码不可能在50年后继续运行，
but it was still in that case.
但事实上它仍在运行。
So people had to scramble, and they essentially
因此人们不得不手忙脚乱，他们实际上
had to solve this by using more digits, so upgrading from two to four.
不得不通过使用更多位数来解决这个问题，因此从两位数升级到四位数。
Nowadays, and really since the '70s too, we've
如今，实际上从70年代开始，我们已经
used 32-bit integers to keep track of time,
使用32位整数来跟踪时间，
specifically keeping track of the number of seconds
具体来说，跟踪的是从
using an integer from January 1, 1970, the so-called epoch whereby
1970年1月1日开始的秒数，这个日期被称为纪元，即
that's just an arbitrary date early on where we just started counting time.
一个早期的任意日期，我们从这个日期开始计算时间。
So all of the clocks in your Macs, PCs, and phones pretty much
所以你电脑的Mac、PC和手机里的所有时钟基本上
just have a single integer that gets updated every second,
只有一个整数，每秒更新一次，
but it's just keeping track not of absolute time per se,
但它只是跟踪的是并非绝对的时间，
but how many seconds have passed since January 1, 1970,
而是从1970年1月1日至今过去了多少秒，
just because that's the date humans chose.
仅仅是因为那是人类选择的日期。
The problem is you can only count as high as 4 billion,
问题是，使用32位整数，你最多只能计数到40亿，
give or take, with 32 bits and actually 2 billion, give or take,
大约如此，实际上是20亿，大约如此，
if you support negative numbers, as well.
如果你也支持负数的话。
And the problem with that is that we're about to trip over the same issue
而问题是，我们很快就会再次遇到同样的问题，
again in not too long from now.
在不久的将来。
This is the 2038 problem because in the year 2038, on that date, mark my words,
这就是2038年问题，因为在2038年，在那个日期，记住我的话，
things could break again.
事情可能会再次崩溃。
Why?
为什么？
Because that 32-bit value is going to accidentally wrap
因为那个32位的值会意外地回绕到
around back to a 0 or a negative value.
0或负值。
So we're going to go through the whole darn process again.
所以我们又要经历整个过程一遍。
Now, thankfully the solution, as you might expect, is kind of just
现在，幸运的是，正如你可能预料的那样，解决方法仅仅是
to kick the can even further down the road
把问题推迟到更远的将来，
and use 64 bits, which I think will get us another 290 million years of runway.
使用64位，我认为这将给我们再延长2.9亿年的时间。
It's more than twice.
这不止是两倍。
So it's not our problem anymore at that point.
所以到那时，这就不再是我们的问题了。
But that's fundamentally going to be the solution.
但从根本上来说，这将是解决方法。
But it will still be finite.
但它仍然是有限的。
So we're just deferring to our descendants
所以我们只是把问题推给我们的后代，
to actually deal with the issue some millions of years from now
让他们在数百万年后去解决这个问题，
if these things are still running.
如果这些东西还在运行的话。
So if that does happen, here's the specific date
所以如果真的发生了，以下是具体的日期，
that, in 2038, all of a sudden our clocks will still
在2038年，我们的时钟会突然
think because a negative number will get subtracted to the current epoch time.
认为时间是错误的，因为一个负数会被从当前的纪元时间中减去。
So it will think we're back in 1901.
所以它会认为我们回到了1901年。
So this has had some fun and very real world implications.
所以这带来了一些有趣且非常现实的影响。
So for instance, this is the game Pac-Man, which you might have played.
例如，这是你可能玩过的游戏《吃豆人》。
It kind of came out around my day, back in time.
这大概发生在我那个时代，在很早以前。
And if you get to the 256th level, this unfortunately
如果你达到了第256关，很不幸地，
is what happens because they didn't really
这就是会发生的事情，因为他们并没有真正地
expect that players would spend all this much time playing Pac-Man apparently.
预料到玩家会花这么多时间玩吃豆人。
And they didn't really have a condition saying,
而且他们并没有一个条件说，
you win if you get to the 255th or 266th level.
如果你达到第255关或第266关，你就赢了。
And so what happens here essentially is that the whole screen gets very
所以这里本质上发生的事情是整个屏幕变得非常
garbled because there's an integer in the original Pac-Man that
混乱不堪，因为在最初的吃豆人游戏中有一个整数，
counts to 256, but that's too big, so it wraps back around to 0.
它可以计数到256，但它太大了，所以它会回绕到0。
And it doesn't know when to stop printing fruits on the screen,
它不知道什么时候停止在屏幕上打印水果，
as in this case, to collect.
就像在这种情况下，去收集水果。
Another example of this is actually from the original Donkey Kong
另一个例子实际上来自最初的《大金刚》
game, which looks something like this in my day, too, whereby in Donkey Kong,
游戏，在我的时代它看起来像这样，在《大金刚》中，
there was this mathematical formula, whereby
有一个数学公式，通过它
the number of seconds you have to solve the game was a function of 10 times
你玩游戏所需的时间是当前关卡编号乘以10加上4的函数。
your current level number plus the number 4.
这就是决定你获得多少秒时间。
That dictated how many seconds you get.
当然，关卡越高，你获得的时间就越多
So of course, the higher the level, you get more and more time
随着关卡的提升。
as the level climbs.
不幸的是，一旦你达到了第22关，
Unfortunately, once you hit level 22, the math ends up being 10 times
计算结果就是22乘以10加上4，得到数字260。
22 plus 4, which gives you the number 260.
而且他们也使用了8位值，一个字节
And they, too, were using 8-bit values, a single byte
来表示数字，这意味着260大于256。
to represent numbers, which means 260 is bigger than 256.
而且这个数学计算的结果是，
And the way that math worked out was, well,
260减去256，如果它回绕，就会给玩家4秒钟时间来玩第
260 minus 256, if it wraps back around, gave people four seconds to solve level
22关，这几乎是不可能的。
22, which is just impossible.
就像，马里奥甚至都无法从他所在的位置向上爬几关。
Like, Mario can't even get up a couple of levels
所以这也算是一个众所周知的错误，
or so from where he actually was.
因为它确实存在。
So that, too, was sort of a well-known bug,
最后，这个错误就更加真实了，在2015年，
as well, since that works out to be there.
波音787被记录为出现了一个软件错误，而不是硬件错误
Lastly, and this one is all the more real, in 2015,
从以下意义上来说。
Boeing 787 was documented as having not a hardware bug but a software bug
“一架连续运行了248天的787型号飞机
in the following sense.
可能会因为控制单元同时进入安全模式而失去所有电源。
"A model 787 airplane that has been powered continuously for 248 days
这种情况是由一个软件计数器引起的，该计数器会在连续运行248天后溢出。
can lose all of its power due to the control unit simultaneously going
波音当时正在开发一个CPU软件升级，
into failsafe mode.
将解决不安全状况。”
This condition was caused by a software counter that will overflow
人们做了计算。
after 248 days of continuous power.
事实证明，波音可能使用了一个32位的整数。
Boeing at the time was in the process of developing a CPU software upgrade that
而且它们用来记录时间并不是以秒为单位，而是以百分之一秒为单位，
will remedy the unsafe condition."
因为如果你做一下计算，
And people did the math.
在一个32位的值达到40亿——
It turns out that Boeing was probably using an integer that was 32 bits.
或者20亿百分之一秒之后，
And they were keeping track of time not in seconds but hundredths of seconds,
这个数字会回绕到0，
because if you do out the math, after a 32-bit value has reached 4 billion--
它会将一个32位的整数回绕到0，
or 2 billion one hundredths of a second, the number wraps around back to 0,
这就是为什么如果你让你的计算机运行足够长的时间，
or negative 2 billion.
或者负20亿。
And the implications was literally the plane's power would stop.
而这意味着飞机的动力会停止。
And if you can believe it, if you grew up with Windows, macOS, or whatnot,
如果你相信，如果你在Windows、macOS或其他系统下长大，
anyone want to conjecture what the solution was
有人想知道解决方案是什么
until Boeing updated their software?
直到波音更新了他们的软件？
STUDENT: Turn it off, turn it back on.
学生：关机重启。
DAVID MALAN: Turn the plane off, and turn it
大卫·马兰：关掉飞机，然后打开
back on because that has the effect of resetting its memory and therefore
它，因为这会重置它的内存，因此
all of its variables back to 0.
它所有的变量都重置为0。
So this is ultimately to say as you dive into problem set 1, your first in C,
所以最终我们要说，当你开始做问题集1，你的第一个C语言问题集时，
you, too, will make quite a few mistakes when it comes to correctness.
你也会犯不少错误，尤其是在正确性方面。
You, too, will encounter opportunities for better design and better style.
你也会遇到改进设计和风格的机会。
In the real world, there are very much these issues.
在现实世界中，有很多这样的问题。
So even if you struggle, know that for better or for worse,
所以即使你遇到了困难，也要知道，无论好坏，
you're in very good company.
你并不孤单。
But some three months from now, you will be in much better shape
但是三个月后，你会好很多
because this was week 1, and this is CS50.
因为这是第一周，这里是CS50。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
[INTRIGUING MUSIC]
[引人入胜的音乐]